<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schott" date="1834">nephrolepis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Nauman" date="1979">×averyi</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>69: 69. 1979</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus nephrolepis;species ×averyi</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stem scales loosely appressed to spreading, essentially concolored. Tubers absent.  Leaves  8--30 × 0.5--1.3 dm.  Petiole  1.2--5 dm, moderately to densely scaly; scales spreading, reddish to light brown throughout.  Blade  moderately scaly, glabrous to occasionally pubescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially, hairs pale to light brown, 0.2--0.7 mm. Rachis 5--26 dm, points of pinna attachment 9--25 mm apart; scales scattered, brown throughout. Central pinnae narrowly deltate to oblong-deltate, 3.6--9 × 0.7--2 cm, base truncate, sometimes rounded basiscopically, barely auriculate acroscopically, acroscopic lobe obtuse to acute, margins serrulate, apex narrowly acute to attenuate, falcate to slightly so; costae adaxially sparsely pubescent, hairs pale, erect, 0.1--0.5 mm.  Indusia  horseshoe-shaped to circular, attached at narrow sinus or peltate, 0.9--1.1 mm wide. 2 n  = 164.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Terrestrial or epiphytic in forested, often moist habitats, e.g., swamps, hammocks, or relatively open, disturbed habitats;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.; Mexico; West Indies.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Avery's sword fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Nephrolepis × averyi is an allotetraploid derived from hybridization between N . biserrata and N . exaltata and is known to occur only in mixed populations of both parent species. It is distinguished from N . exaltata by its sparsely hairy adaxial costae, larger size, and misshapen spores, and from N . biserrata by its falcate pinnae and narrower leaves.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
