<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Miller" date="1768">rigida</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict., ed. 8</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>Pinus no. 10. 1768</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species rigida</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 31m; trunk to 0.9m diam., straight or crooked, commonly with adventitious sprouts; crown rounded or irregular.  Bark  red-brown, deeply and irregularly furrowed, with long, irregularly rectangular, flat, scaly ridges, resin pockets absent.  Branches  arching-spreading to ascending, poorly self-pruning; 2-year-old branchlets stout (mostly over 5mm thick), orange-brown, aging darker brown, rough.  Buds  ovoid to ovoid-cylindric, red-brown, ca. 1--1.5cm, resinous; scale margins fringed, apex cuspidate.  Leaves  3(--5) per fascicle, spreading to ascending, persisting 2--3 years, 5--10(--15)cm × 1--1.5(--2)mm, straight, twisted, deep to pale yellow-green, all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins serrulate, apex abruptly subulate-acuminate; sheath 0.9--1.2cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  cylindric, ca. 20mm, yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter or variously serotinous and long-persistent, often clustered, symmetric, conic to ovoid before opening, broadly ovoid with flat or slightly convex base when open, 3--9cm, creamy brown to light red-brown, sessile to short-stalked, base truncate, scales firm, with dark red-brown border on adaxial surface distally; apophyses slightly raised, rhombic, with strong transverse keels; umbo central, low-triangular, with slender, downcurved prickle.  Seeds  broadly obliquely obovoid-deltoid; body 4--5(--6)mm, dark brown, mottled darker, or near black; wing 15--20mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Upland or lowland, sterile, dry to boggy soils;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="boggy" />
        <character name="habitat" value="upland" />
        <character name="habitat" value="lowland" />
        <character name="habitat" value="sterile" />
        <character name="habitat" value="dry to boggy soils" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1400m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont., Que.; Conn., Del., Ga., Ky., Maine, Md., Mass., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., R.I., S.C., Tenn., Vt., Va., W.Va.</description>
  <number>21</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pitch pine</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">pin rigide</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus rigida often has poor form and is not valued highly as saw timber. It is fire successional, sprouts adventitiously, and is frequently shrubby in the northern part of its range. It is known to hybridize naturally with P . echinata .</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
