<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Christopher H. Haufler</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="E. Fournier in Baillon" date="1829">Bommeria</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Baillon,Dict. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 448. 1877 [Named for the Belgian pteridologist. 1829</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus Bommeria</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Stems  prostrate, long-creeping, often branched [short, seldom branched]; scales pale brown to yellowish, lanceolate, concolored, margins entire.  Leaves  monomorphic, scattered, 4--30 cm.  Petiole  chestnut brown to dark purple, rounded or with single groove adaxially, indument of scales and/or trichomes, especially proximally and distally, with single vascular bundle.  Blade  pentagonal, pedately divided into 3 segments, deeply pinnate-pinnatifid, herbaceous, abaxially with scales, unicellular coiled trichomes, and unicellular needlelike trichomes, adaxially dull, not striate, with unicellular needlelike trichomes; rachis straight.  Segments  of blade sessile, 1--3(--5) mm wide, distal segment 1--2-pinnatifid in proximal portion, pinnatifid in distal portion; proximal segments usually connected to distal by narrow wing along rachis, inequilaterally elongate-deltate, proximal basiscopic portion elongate, 1--2-pinnatifid; margins not recurved to form false indusia.  Veins  in segments obscure, free to anastomosing, pinnately branched and divergent distally.  False indusia  absent.  Sporangia  borne along veins, covering most veins or somewhat marginally restricted, containing 64 [32] spores, paraphyses and glands absent.  Spores  brown, globose, trilete, exospore smooth, perispore surfaces crested or reticulate, equatorial flange absent.  x  = 30.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, Central America.</description>
  <number>9</number>
  <discussion>Species 5 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Gastony, G. J. and C. H. Haufler. 1976. Chromosome numbers and apomixis in the fern genus  Bommeria . Biotropica 8: 1--11.</reference>
    <reference>Haufler, C. H. 1979. A biosystematic revision of  Bommeria . J. Arnold Arbor. 60: 445--476.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
