<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Roth" date="1799">polystichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(D. C. Eaton) Diels in Engler &amp; Prantl" date="1899">californicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Engler &amp; Prantl,Nat. Pflanzenfam.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(4): 191. 1899</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus polystichum;species californicum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Aspidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="D. C. Eaton" date="unknown">californicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 555. 1865</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Aspidium;species californicum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polystichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Roth" date="unknown">aculeatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(D. C. Eaton) Jepson" date="unknown">californicum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polystichum;species aculeatum;variety californicum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  erect or ascending.  Leaves  monomorphic, arching or erect, 2--8 dm; bulblets absent.  Petiole  1/5--1/3 length of leaf; scales light brown, abruptly diminishing in size distally, falling off early distally.  Blade  lanceolate to linear-lanceolate, 1-pinnate-pinnatifid, base slightly narrowed.  Pinnae  oblong to lanceolate to falcate, shallowly to deeply divided, pinnae overlapping or not, in 1 plane, 2--10 cm; base oblique, acroscopic auricle lobed; margins not incised to costae, serrulate-spiny with teeth ascending; apex acute-attenuate, subapical and apical teeth same size (southern form) or obtuse and cuspidate with subapical teeth smaller than apical teeth (northern form); microscales filiform, dense abaxially, sparse adaxially.  Indusia  ciliate.  Spores  brown. 2 n  = 164.</description>
  <description type="habitat">On forest floor in southern part of range and in rock crevices at cliff bottoms (most commonly andesite) to north;</description>
  <description type="elevation">100--850 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Calif., Oreg., Wash.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">California sword fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Polystichum californicum is restricted to the Coast Ranges and the Sierra-Cascade axis. It is most abundant in the Coast Range north of San Francisco.</discussion>
  <discussion>Polystichum californicum is an allopolyploid, the evolutionary roots of which include P . dudleyi as the 2-pinnate ancestor. Morphologic and ecological data indicate P . imbricans is ancestor to the northern forms and P . munitum is ancestor to southern forms, suggesting P . californicum is an amalgam of interfertile tetraploids with polyphyletic origins (D. H. Wagner 1979). Cytological analysis corroborates this (A. D. Callan 1972; W. H. Wagner Jr. 1973), but chloroplast DNA studies have detected only the involvement of P . imbricans in the ancestry of P . californicum (P. S. Soltis et al. 1991).</discussion>
  <discussion>The more xeric, rock-inhabiting members of the complex (showing the parental influence of P . imbricans ) occupy the northern half of the range whereas plants of more mesic habitats are found to the south. Hybrids with both P . dudleyi and P . munitum are found frequently, because these three species are often sympatric (W. H. Wagner 1973). The hybrid with P . dudleyi (a triploid) will key to that species. The hybrid with P . munitum resembles a less-incised form of P . californicum with aborted sporangia. Polystichum californicum × imbricans has been found only once, in Oregon (A. D. Callan 1972). Another hybrid that will key here, based on its overall appearance, is P . munitum × scopulinum . It lacks filiform microscales and also has malformed sporangia. Such a specimen was the basis of the report of Polystichum californicum in eastern Washington (C. L. Hitchcock et al. 1955--1969, vol. 1). The sterile diploid hybrid between P . dudleyi and P . munitum is indistinguishable from P . californicum except for aborted sporangia and chromosome number (W. H. Wagner Jr. 1973).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
