<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Siplivinskij" date="1974">sibiricum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 329. 1974</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus polypodium;species sibiricum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  often whitish pruinose, slender, to 6 mm diam., acrid-tasting; scales concolored to weakly bicolored, uniformly dark brown, often lighter near base, lanceolate, contorted distally, margins denticulate.  Leaves  to 25 cm.  Petiole  slender, to 1 mm diam.  Blade  oblong-linear, pinnatifid, usually widest at or near middle, to 4 cm wide, somewhat leathery; rachis sparsely scaly to glabrescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially; scales lanceolate-ovate, usually more than 6 cells wide.  Segments  oblong, less than 7 mm wide; margins entire to crenulate; apex rounded to broadly acute; midrib glabrous adaxially.  Venation  free.  Sori  midway between margin and midrib to nearly marginal, less than 3 mm diam., circular when immature.  Sporangiasters  present, less than 40 per sorus, heads normally without glandular hairs.  Spores  less than 52 µm, tuberculate with tubercles, surface projections more than 3 µm tall. 2 n  = 74.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--early fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cracks and ledges on rock outcrops, on a variety of substrates including granite and dolomite;</description>
  <description type="elevation">100--1000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; Alta., B.C., Man., N.W.T., Ont., Que., Sask., Yukon; Alaska; n Asia.</description>
  <number>8</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Polypode de Sibérie</other_name>
  <discussion>This boreal diploid has traditionally been identified as Polypodium virginianum (T. M. C. Taylor 1970; F. A. Lang 1971), but recent investigations indicate that it is conspecific with the eastern Eurasian species P . sibiricum (C. H. Haufler and M. D. Windham 1991). The sporangiasters of P . sibiricum normally lack glands, but some collections have sporangiasters with a few glandular hairs. Although such collections could be misidentified, the spores of P . sibiricum are less than 52 µm and clearly distinguish it from P . virginianum , P . amorphum , and P . saximontanum . Hybridization occurs between P . sibiricum and P . virginianum where these species overlap in Canada, forming triploid individuals with misshapen spores (C. H. Haufler and Wang Z. R. 1991).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
