<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David M. Johnson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">Marsileaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Marsileaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  aquatic or amphibious, rhizomatous.  Stems  growing on soil surface or subterranean, main stem long-creeping and giving rise to long or short shoots only at nodes; hairs laterally attached, multicellular.  Roots  arising at nodes and also along internodes.  Leaves  distichous, long-petioled, sometimes filiform and lacking expanded blades.  Sori  within hard bean- or pea-shaped bodies (sporocarps) arising on short stalks from near or at base of petioles.  Sporangia  of 2 kinds, borne within the same sorus and sporocarp; megasporangia containing a single megaspore; microsporangia containing 20--64 microspores.  Gametophytes  remaining within spores; microgametophytes of only a few cells; megagametophytes protruding from spores, each bearing 1 simple archegonium.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, temperate and tropical regions.</description>
  <number>23</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Water clover Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Spore germination in the family occurs after rupture of the sporocarp wall allows the sporocarp contents to be hydrated. A gelatinous structure emerges from the sporocarp, breaking it into valves and carrying the sori into the water. Spore germination (gametophyte growth) and fertilization occur immediately.</discussion>
  <discussion>Regnellidium diphyllum Lindman was introduced into a wildlife pond in Mahoning County, Ohio, in 1985 and continues to persist (C. F. Chuey, in litt. 1991). Regnellidium is similar to Marsilea but differs from it in having two leaflets instead of four.</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera 3, species ca. 50 (2 genera, 7 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Braun, A. 1871. Hr. Braun theilte neuere Untersuchungen über die Gattungen  Marsilea  und  Pilularia . Monatsber. Königl. Preuss. Akad. Wiss. Berlin 1870: 653--753.</reference>
    <reference>Johnson, D. M. 1986. Systematics of the New World species of  Marsilea  (Marsileaceae). Syst. Bot. Monogr. 11: 1--87.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves with blades palmately divided into 4 obdeltate or cuneate pinnae.</description>
      <determination>1 Marsilea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves filiform, lacking expanded blades.</description>
      <determination>2 Pilularia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
