<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Jermy" date="1986">Tetragonostachys</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fern Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 118. 1986</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus Tetragonostachys</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  radially symmetric or upperside and underside structurally different, not articulate, prostrate, creeping, or erect, few to many branched; vessel elements present.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems, throughout stem length or confined to base of stem.  Leaves  monomorphic, tightly appressed and spirally arranged, or upperside and underside leaves slightly differentiated; all leaves linear or linear-lanceolate, thick or fleshy (seldom thin); margins dentate, serrate, or ciliate; abaxial groove with stomates, these arranged along vein; axillary leaves absent.  Strobili  quadrangular.  Sporophylls  differentiated from vegetative leaves, most sporophylls fertile; megasporophylls and microsporophylls same size, in 4 alternating ranks, appressed, base usually with 2 diverging flaps or auricles, auricles protecting sporangia below.</description>
  <description type="distribution">widespread, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa including Madagascar.</description>
  <number>1b</number>
  <discussion>This treatment of subg. Tetragonostachys generally follows that of R. M. Tryon (1955). Some problems, however, remain to be resolved, particularly for Selaginella arenicola and S . densa , in which taxa have been recognized at the infraspecific (R. M. Tryon 1955) and specific (L. H. Snyder Jr. and J. G. Bruce 1986; J. W. Thieret 1980; J. M. Beitel and W. R. Buck, pers. comm.) levels. Based on examination of a wide range of specimens in the S . arenicola complex, I recognize two species, one of which contains two subspecies. In the S . densa complex, I recognize three well-defined species: S . densa , S . scopulorum , and S . standleyi . The phylogenetic relationships among the different series proposed by Tryon need further study.</discussion>
  <discussion>Within the series Arenicolae R. M. Tryon, a tendency toward structural differentiation occurs between the stem's upperside and its underside (e.g., S . rupincola ). This feature may link series Arenicolae to species such as S . hansenii and S . wrightii , which I place in the series Eremophilae R. M. Tryon and which may represent an early intermediate stage toward full stem differentiation. According to Tryon, this "transitional stage" is primitive within the series Eremophilae , where it is found in S . peruviana .</discussion>
  <discussion>The occurrence of hybrids within Selaginella subg. Tetragonostachys is best shown in S . × neomexicana . Hybridization may be a more common phenomenon, however, than previously acknowledged.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (26 species and 1 hybrid in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Clausen, R. T. 1946.  Selaginella  subgenus  Euselaginella , in the southeastern United States. Amer. Fern J. 36: 65--82.</reference>
    <reference>Tryon, R. M. 1955.  Selaginella rupestris  and its allies. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 42: 1--99, plates 1--6.</reference>
    <reference>Tryon, R. M. 1971. The process of evolutionary migration in species of Selaginella . Brittonia 23: 89--100. Van</reference>
    <reference>Eseltine, G. P. 1918. The allies of Selaginella rupestris in the southeastern United States. Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 20(5): 159--172.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems prostrate, undersides and uppersides differentiated; leaves conspicuously to slightly dimorphic; rhizophores throughout stem length.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems pendent, erect, ascending, or rarely prostrate, radially symmetric or undersides and uppersides slightly differentiated (if so, leaves decurrent as in S. densa complex); leaves not to rarely dimorphic; rhizophores throughout stem length or restricted to stem base.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Underside and upperside leaves abruptly adnate to stem; leaves slightly dimorphic.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Underside leaves decurrent, upperside leaves abruptly adnate to stem; leaves strongly to moderately dimorphic.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Apex of leaves with white or whitish bristle 0.5--1.4 mm; marginal cilia white to whitish, strongly ascending; leaves green, usually with red spots or wholly reddish wine-colored; sporophylls ovate-deltate, short-attenuate toward apex.</description>
      <determination>6 Selaginella hansenii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Apex of leaves with yellowish bristle 0.2-- 0.5 mm or absent; marginal cilia transparent, spreading; leaves green, never reddish; sporophylls lanceolate, long-attenuate toward apex.</description>
      <determination>5 Selaginella wrightii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves with tortuous (twisted) bristle at tip, becoming acute to mucronate; upperside leaves lanceolate; plants forming dense mats.</description>
      <determination>2 Selaginella eremophila</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves acute to bristled, bristle straight; upperside leaves linear-lanceolate; plants forming rather loose mats.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Underside leaves lanceolate, widest at middle; leaf apex acute or with short and flattened bristle 0.1--0.3 mm (mostly at branch tips or buds); sporophylls acute to acuminate.</description>
      <determination>3 Selaginella arizonica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Underside leaves narrowly linear- lanceolate, widest at base; leaf apex with long round bristle 0.3--0.8 mm; sporophylls bristle-tipped.</description>
      <determination>4 Selaginella peruviana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants epiphytic, seldom terrestrial; aerial stems long-pendent, usually forming festoonlike or overlapping mats; leaves loosely appressed; strobili 1--6 cm.</description>
      <determination>20 Selaginella oregana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants on rock or terrestrial, never epiphytic; aerial stems erect, ascending, long- to short- creeping, decumbent, radially symmetric or slightly differentiated, forming long- or short- spreading mats, cushionlike mats, or cespitose mats; leaves usually tightly appressed; strobili 0.2--4.5(--9) cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Aerial stems erect or ascending, sometimes decumbent or creeping; rhizome or rhizomatous stem present; budlike arrested branches usually present on rhizome or lowermost aerial stem.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Aerial stems creeping or decumbent, never erect, radially symmetric or lower stem and upper stem slightly differentiated; rhizome or rhizomatous stem absent; budlike arrested branches absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Base of leaf abruptly adnate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Base of leaf decurrent or long-decurrent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins short-ciliate throughout, cilia 0.02--0.08 mm; leaf base cordate to almost peltate.</description>
      <determination>7 Selaginella bigelovii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins long-ciliate at least at base, cilia 0.06--0.2 mm; leaf base rounded.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bristle 0.65--1.85 mm; marginal cilia long and spreading throughout, 0.1--0.2 mm; sporophylls strongly tapering toward apex.</description>
      <determination>8 Selaginella rupincola</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bristle 0.3--0.46 mm; marginal cilia long and spreading at base, short to dentiform and ascending toward apex, 0.06--0.17 mm; sporophylls not strongly tapering.</description>
      <determination>9 Selaginella ×neomexicana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scalelike leaves on rhizome loosely appressed; stem leaves without hairs along abaxial groove.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scalelike leaves on rhizome tightly appressed or rhizome absent; stem leaves with hairs along abaxial groove.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scalelike leaves on rhizome incurved; leaf apex bristle-tipped; sporophyll bristle-tipped.</description>
      <determination>10 Selaginella weatherbiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scalelike leaves on rhizome straight; leaf apex acute or obtuse; sporophyll apex acute to obtuse.</description>
      <determination>11 Selaginella viridissima</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bristle tortuous (twisted); leaf base glabrous; abaxial groove and ridges on leaf not prominent, often obscure; strobili 0.4--0.6 cm.</description>
      <determination>12 Selaginella tortipila</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bristle straight, never twisted; leaf base pubescent; abaxial groove and ridges on leaf prominent; strobili (0.5--)1--3(--3.5) cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Underground (rhizomatous) stem leaves scalelike; rhizophores mostly subterranean; sporophyll base glabrous; leaf and sporophyll apices glabrous.</description>
      <determination>13 Selaginella arenicola</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Underground (rhizomatous) stem leaves not scalelike; rhizophores mostly aerial; sporophyll base pubescent; leaf and sporophyll apices often puberulent.</description>
      <determination>14 Selaginella acanthonota</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on main stem adnate to stem (distinct from stem in color), bases rounded or seldom slightly decurrent and cuneate (on underside leaves or in plants from wet places).</description>
      <next_statement_id>16</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on main stem decurrent (not distinct from stem in color), bases cuneate or oblique (seldom adnate and rounded on upperside).</description>
      <next_statement_id>18</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex abruptly short- to long- bristled, bristle puberulent or sometimes entire, (0.16--)0.2--0.46(-- 0.9) mm; leaves in whorls of 4; strobili often paired, 1--4.5(--9) cm.</description>
      <determination>21 Selaginella wallacei</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex blunt or acute to acuminate or seldom short-bristled, bristle if present entire, 0.03--0.45 mm; leaves in whorls of 3; strobili usually solitary, 0.2--3 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves tightly appressed, apex keeled, mucro or bristle if present 0.03--0.45 mm; stems radially symmetric; strobili (0.6--)1--3 cm.</description>
      <determination>17 Selaginella mutica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves loosely appressed, apex plane, not bearing bristle; stems slightly structurally differentiated; strobili 0.2--0.4 cm.</description>
      <determination>18 Selaginella cinerascens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Main stems with upperside and underside slightly differentiated; upperside and underside leaves unequal in size, bases decurrent and oblique (S. densa complex).</description>
      <next_statement_id>19</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Main stems radially symmetric; leaves equal in size, if stem slightly differentiated then leaf bases decurrent and cuneate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex bearing conspicuously puberulent bristle, (1--)1.25-- 1.9 mm; leaf margins usually long- ciliate, cilia 0.07--0.17(--0.2) mm; sporophyll margins entirely ciliate. 26. Selaginella densa</description>
      <next_statement_id>19</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex bearing slightly puberulent or entire bristle, 0.4-- 1.25 mm; leaf margins relatively short-ciliate, cilia 0.02--0.07(-- 0.15) mm; sporophyll margins short- ciliate or denticulate in parts.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporophylls deltate-ovate; apex keeled, strongly truncate in profile; bristle usually yellowish; margins short-ciliate to denticulate on distal 3/4.</description>
      <determination>28 Selaginella standleyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporophylls ovate-lanceolate to lanceolate or seldom ovate; apex attenuate or slightly keeled, not truncate in profile; bristle usually whitish transparent, seldom yellowish (in old leaves); margins short-ciliate to denticulate on proximal 1/2, lacking cilia toward apex.</description>
      <determination>27 Selaginella scopulorum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on main stems in alternate pseudowhorls of 5 or 6.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on main stem in alternate pseudowhorls of 4.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on main stem in alternate pseudowhorls of 5; leaf base decurrent and cuneate on upperside; leaf apex truncate in profile; sporophyll apex truncate in profile.</description>
      <determination>16 Selaginella sibirica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on main stem in alternate pseudowhorls of 6; leaf base sometimes adnate and rounded on upperside; leaf apex attenuate in profile; sporophyll apex not truncate in profile.</description>
      <determination>15 Selaginella rupestris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lateral branches spreading, not ascending; stems forming festoonlike mats or rarely compact mats; dry stems not readily fragmenting; strobili sometimes paired.</description>
      <determination>19 Selaginella underwoodii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lateral branches usually strongly ascending; stems forming compact cushionlike, usually rounded mats or less often loose mats; dry stems readily fragmenting or not; strobili solitary.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex bearing bristle 0.5- -1.4 mm; leaf base pubescent; sporophyll base often pubescent.</description>
      <determination>23 Selaginella asprella</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex mucronate, blunt or acute, bearing bristle or mucro 0--0.6 mm; leaf base glabrous, seldom pubescent; sporophyll base always glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Dry stems not readily fragmenting; lateral branches 1--3-forked; leaf apex strongly keeled.</description>
      <determination>22 Selaginella watsonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Dry stems readily fragmenting; lateral branches 1-forked; leaf apex keeled, slightly attenuate or obtuse.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex bearing puberulent bristle 0.2-- 0.6 mm; leaves not in well-defined alternate pseudowhorls.</description>
      <determination>24 Selaginella leucobryoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex blunt, acute or only ending in very short entire bristle or mucro 0--0.4 mm; leaves in defined alternate pseudowhorls.</description>
      <determination>25 Selaginella utahensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
