<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1841">pellaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Cavanilles) Link" date="1841">ternifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fil. Spec.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>59. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus pellaea;species ternifolia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pteris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Cavanilles" date="unknown">ternifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Descr. Pl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>266. 1802</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pteris;species ternifolia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales bicolored, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, centers black, thick, margins brown, thin, erose-dentate.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered on stem, 10--50 cm; croziers sparsely to densely villous.  Petiole  black or dark purple, lustrous, rounded or slightly flattened adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  linear to ovate, deeply pinnate-pinnatifid proximally, 2.5--8 cm wide; rachis black or purple throughout, straight, often flattened adaxially, glabrous or villous.  Pinnae  perpendicular to rachis or slightly ascending, not decurrent on rachis, ternate at base of leaf; costae absent.  Ultimate segments  linear-oblong, 10--40 mm, leathery, glabrous to sparsely villous abaxially on midrib; margins recurved on fertile segments, rarely covering more than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, entire; apex mucronate.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  long-stalked, containing 64 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <discussion>Pellaea ternifolia is represented in the flora by three morphologically and chromosomally distinct taxa. These discrete genetic entities also show a tendency toward geographic isolation and are treated here as subspecies. Diploid populations referred to P . ternifolia subsp. ternifolia are scattered from Texas through Mexico to South America. The pubescent tetraploid ( P . ternifolia subsp. villosa ) follows the Sierra Madre Oriental from Puebla, Mexico, north to Texas; the glabrous tetraploid ( P . ternifolia subsp. arizonica ) occurs in Arizona, Texas, and northern Mexico. Isozyme and chromosome studies suggest that both tetraploids are segmental allopolyploids produced by hybridization between subsp. ternifolia and other (as yet unidentified) diploid elements within P . ternifolia .</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachises villous, especially in axils of pinnae; pinnae with hairs scattered along main veins abaxially.</description>
      <determination>6a subsp. villosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachises glabrous or with a few widely scattered hairs; pinnae completely glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest ultimate segments (excluding terminal pinnae) usually less than 18 mm; distal portion of petioles grooved or flattened adaxially; spores usually 39–45 µm diam.</description>
      <determination>6b subsp. ternifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest ultimate segments (excluding terminal pinnae) usually more than 18 mm; distal portion of petioles rounded or slightly flattened adaxially; spores usually 46–53 µm diam.</description>
      <determination>6c subsp. arizonica</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
