<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martius" date="unknown">hymenophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">trichomanes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Farrar" date="1992">intricatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>82: 68. 1992</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hymenophyllaceae;genus trichomanes;species intricatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  on rock, occasionally epiphytic.  Sporophytes  not known.  Gametophytes  entirely filamentous, much branched, persistent.  Gemmae  composed of short filaments of undifferentiated cells.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>On noncalcareous rocks in deeply sheltered crevices and grottoes;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="on noncalcareous rocks in sheltered crevices and grottoes" modifier="deeply" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">150--1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Conn., Ga., Ill., Ind., Ky., Md., Mass., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., S.C., Tenn., Vt., Va., W.Va.</description>
  <number>8</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Appalachian trichomanes</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">weft fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Throughout the eastern uplands of the United States, gametophytes of Trichomanes intricatum form feltlike populations covering up to a square meter or more of rock surface in climatically moderated rock shelters and narrow canyons. Sporophytes are not produced, and reproduction is by gemmae and by perennial gametophyte growth and branching.</discussion>
  <discussion>Filamentous gametophytes of the various Trichomanes species have not been distinguished morphologically. Enzyme electrophoresis, however, has shown the vast majority of independent Trichomanes gametophyte populations, as well as all of those existing beyond the range of sporophytes of T . boschianum and T . petersii , to be T . intricatum . (All populations of gametophytes tested in Arkansas and several populations in the immediate vicinity of sporophytes of T . petersii and T . boschianum in eastern states have enzyme banding patterns identical to one or the other of those species.) The adaptation of T . intricatum to far northern habitats and its inability to produce sporophytes suggest that this is a distinct taxon, possibly derived from a pre-Pleistocene North American species possessing a normal alternation of generations (D. R. Farrar 1985, 1992).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
