<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martius" date="unknown">hymenophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">trichomanes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">membranaceum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1097. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hymenophyllaceae;genus trichomanes;species membranaceum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lecanium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) C. Presl" date="unknown">membranaceum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lecanium;species membranaceum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic, on rock, or terrestrial.  Stems  long-creeping, threadlike, bearing scattered leaves, covered with dark hairs of 2 types, multicellular gland-tipped hairs and elongate rhizoidlike hairs.  Leaves  subsessile, irregularly ovate to oblong and often irregularly cleft, 2.5--6.5 × 1--3 cm, bearing multicellular gland-tipped hairs and elongate rhizoidlike hairs on petiole; margin fringed with minute, paired, roundish scales.  Blades  2 cell layers thick between veins.  Venation  flabellate with many unconnected false veins.  Soral involucres  5--15 per leaf, marginal on leaf apices, narrowly conic with flaring lips.  Gametophytes  unknown. 2 n  = 68.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Terrestrial in acid humus;</description>
  <description type="elevation">below 10 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Miss.; epiphytic and on rock, Mexico; West Indies; Central America; South America.</description>
  <number>7</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Scale-edged bristle fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Trichomanes membranaceum resembles species of subg. Didymoglossum in its growth form and chromosome number, and it has been considered by some authors to be of that subgenus. Its marginal scales, absence of stellate hairs, and leaf blades 2 cell layers thick set it apart from other species of subg. Didymoglossum and all other American Trichomanes .</discussion>
  <discussion>The single population reported from Harrison County, Mississippi, in 1929 (E. T. Wherry 1964) may be extirpated, and no other occurrences of Trichomanes membranaceum are currently known in the flora. Because it is a common and adaptable species of varied habitats throughout tropical America, occurrences along the Gulf Coast and in Florida are not unlikely.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
