<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">marsileaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">marsilea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">quadrifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1099. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family marsileaceae;genus marsilea;species quadrifolia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  forming diffuse clones.  Roots  arising at nodes and 1--3 on internodes.  Petioles  5.4--16.5 cm, sparsely pubescent to glabrous.  Pinnae  7--21 × 6--19 mm, sparsely pubescent to glabrous.  Sporocarp stalks  ascending, frequently branched, attached 1--12 mm above base of petiole; unbranched stalks or ultimate branches of stalks 3--16 mm; common trunk of branched stalks 1--4 mm (rarely 2--3 unbranched stalks attached separately to same petiole).  Sporocarps  perpendicular to ascending, 4--5.6 × 3--4 mm, 2.3--2.8 mm thick, rounded, oval, or elliptic in lateral view, pubescent but soon glabrate; raphe 1.4--1.9 mm, proximal tooth usually absent, distal tooth absent or 0.1--0.2 mm.  Sori  10--17.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <discussion>Marsilea quadrifolia was introduced in Connecticut about 1860. Many of the localities from which it is known at present are artificial bodies of water. This may indicate intentional introduction of the plant as a curiosity.</discussion>
  <discussion>Because its leaves are glabrous to essentially glabrous, Marsilea quadrifolia is unlikely to be confused with any other Marsilea in the flora. Likewise, the petioles of the land leaves in this species tend to be procumbent rather than stiffly erect as in the others. The branched sporocarp stalks found in M . quadrifolia are found elsewhere only in M . macropoda ; the latter, however, is a hairy plant and has no distal tooth on the very large sporocarp.</discussion>
  <discussion>Marsilea minuta Linnaeus, a widespread species in the paleotropics, has recently been collected from the Florida Panhandle. It resembles M . quadrifolia in having roots both at the nodes and on the internodes and in having relatively glabrous land leaves, but it has sporocarps that are only 1.3--1.7 mm thick, with a distal tooth 0.3--0.6 mm long. Marsilea minuta also has a tendency for the terminal margins of the land leaves to be crenate rather than entire.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots both at nodes and sparsely (1–3) along internodes; stalks of sporocarps frequently branched. 1. Marsilea quadrifolia</description>
      <next_statement_id>1</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots only at nodes; stalks of sporocarps branched or unbranched.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal tooth of sporocarps 0.4–1.2 mm, acute. 6. Marsilea vestita</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal tooth of sporocarps absent or to 0.4 mm and blunt.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporocarps 6–9 mm, strongly ascending; stalks usually branched. 5. Marsilea macropoda</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporocarps 2.4–6 mm, perpendicular to strongly nodding, i.e., stalk curved or bent; stalks unbranched.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stalks recurved or prostrate, often hooked again at base of raphe; sporocarps borne underground or below stem level. 2. Marsilea ancylopoda</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stalks erect, never hooked at base of raphe; sporocarps borne aboveground or above stem level.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporocarps 2–3 mm wide, proximal tooth of sporocarp 0.2 mm or absent. 4. Marsilea mollis</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporocarps 3.6–4 mm wide, proximal tooth of sporocarp 0.2–0.6 mm and curved away from sporocarp. 3. Marsilea oligospora</description>
      <next_statement_id>1</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
