<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Masahiro Kato</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1801">Diplazium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(2): 4, 61. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Diplazium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek diplazein, double, or di, two, and plasion, oblong, referring to a double sorus]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Small ex Pichi-Sermolli" date="unknown">Homalosorus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Homalosorus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial or on rock.  Stems  creeping, ascending, or erect, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, evergreen or dying back in winter.  Petiole  ca. 1/2 to equaling length of blade, base swollen and persisting as trophopod over winter or not; vascular bundles 2, lateral, lunate in cross section.  Blade  oblong-lanceolate to deltate, 1-pinnate to 2-pinnate-pinnatifid [simple to 4-pinnate-pinnatifid], gradually reduced distally to pinnatifid apex or apical pinna similar to (conform) adjacent pinnae, herbaceous to papery.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins entire, crenulate, or serrate; proximal pinnae not reduced, sessile, equilateral or inequilateral; costae adaxially deeply grooved, grooves continuous with that of rachis; indument abaxially absent or of linear to ovate scales, adaxially absent.  Veins  free, simple or forked, or basal pairs of adjacent segments anastomosing.  Sori  single or paired back-to-back on veins, oblong to linear, straight or slightly falcate; indusia linear, laterally attached, persistent. Spores brownish, usually broadly winged.  x  = 40, 41.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Twin-sorus fern</other_name>
  <discussion>In a few species outside the flora, rachises and costae bear multicellular hairs like those of  Deparia , which differs from  Diplazium  in having grooves of costae not decurrent onto rachis groove, veins free or anastomosing, sori long or short and costular, and indusia present or absent. Many species of  Diplazium  are known to reproduce apogamously.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species about 400 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Johnson, D. M. 1986. Trophopods in North American species of  Athyrium  (Aspleniaceae). Syst. Bot. 11: 26--31.</reference>
    <reference>Kato, M. 1977. Classification of  Athyrium  and allied genera of Japan. Bot. Mag. (Tokyo) 90: 23--40.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 2-pinnate; veins anastomosing.</description>
      <determination>3 Diplazium esculentum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 1-pinnate or 1-pinnate-pinnatifid; veins free.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales brown, entire; pinnae nearly entire.</description>
      <determination>1 Diplazium pycnocarpon</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales dark brown, dentate; pinnae lobed.</description>
      <determination>2 Diplazium lonchophyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
