<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">abies</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas ex J. Forbes" date="1839">amabilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pinet. Woburn.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>125, plate 44. 1839</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus abies;species amabilis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 75m; trunk to 2.6m diam.; crown spirelike, with age becoming flat topped, cylindric.  Bark  gray, thin, smooth, with age breaking into scaly plates.  Branches  diverging from trunk at right angles, short, stiff; twigs mostly opposite, darker brown abaxially, light brown adaxially, pubescence tan.  Buds  hidden by leaves or exposed, brown, globose, small, resinous (at least apically), apex rounded; basal scales short, broad, triangular, densely pubescent, usually not resinous, margins entire, apex sharp-pointed.  Leaves  (0.7--)1--2.5cm × 1--3mm, mostly 2-ranked, flexible, ± concealing the adaxial surface of the twigs (especially in mid to upper crown), some leaves forwardly directed, others usually longer and spreading horizontally, proximal portion ± straight; cross section flat, prominently grooved adaxially; odor pungent; abaxial surface with 5--6 stomatal rows on each side of midrib; adaxial surface dark, lustrous green, lacking stomates; apex prominently notched; resin canals small, near margins and abaxial epidermal layer.  Pollen cones  at pollination red, becoming reddish yellow.  Seed cones  cylindric, 8--10(--13) × 3.5--5cm, purple, sessile, apex round to nipple-shaped; scales ca. 2 × 2cm, pubescent; bracts included.  Seeds  10--12 × 4mm, body tan; wing about as long as body, rose to tan; cotyledons 4--7.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Moist, coastal coniferous forests;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--2000m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Alaska, Calif., Oreg., Wash.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pacific silver fir</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">silver fir</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sapin gracieux</other_name>
</bio:treatment>
