<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Newman" date="unknown">aspleniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">asplenium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">rhizophyllum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1078. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family aspleniaceae;genus asplenium;species rhizophyllum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Camptosorus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Link" date="unknown">rhizophyllus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Camptosorus;species rhizophyllus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots  not proliferous.  Stems  erect or ascending, usually unbranched; scales dark brown throughout, narrowly deltate, 2--3 × (0.2--)0.5--1 mm, margins entire.  Leaves  monomorphic but fertile leaves generally larger than sterile leaves.  Petiole  reddish brown at base, becoming green distally, dull but sometimes lustrous at base, 0.5--12 cm, 0.1--1.5 times length of blade; indument of dark brown, narrowly deltate scales at base, of minute, club-shaped hairs distally.  Blades  highly variable in size and shape, even on 1 plant, narrowly deltate to linear-lanceolate, simple, 1--30 × 0.5--5 cm, leathery, sparsely pubescent, hairs more numerous abaxially than adaxially; blade base cordate, auriculate, or occasionally hastate, auricles rarely attenuate and radicant; margins entire to sinuate, rarely irregularly incised; apex rounded to very long-attenuate and, if attenuate, generally rooting at tip.  Rachis  green, dull, nearly glabrous.  Veins  obscure, anastomosing to form areoles near midrib.  Sori  numerous, scattered somewhat irregularly over blade, often joined at vein junctures.  Spores  64 per sporangium. 2 n  = 72.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Shaded, usually moss-covered boulders and ledges, usually on limestone or other basic rocks, but occasionally on sandstone or other acidic rocks, rarely on fallen tree trunks;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="shaded , moss-covered boulders and ledges , on limestone or other basic rocks , but on sandstone or other acidic rocks , on fallen tree trunks ;" modifier="occasionally rarely" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont., Que.; Ala., Ark., Conn., D.C., Ga., Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Miss., Mo., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Okla., Pa., R.I., Tenn., Vt., Va., W.Va., Wis.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Walking fern</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">doradille ambulante</other_name>
  <discussion>Asplenium rhizophyllum , a diploid species, is morphologically very distinctive within Asplenium and is segregated by many authors, along with its sister species A . ruprechtii Kurata of eastern Asia, into the genus Camptosorus Link. Proliferations arising from leaf tips result in the formation of clonal patches, often dense and extensive, on the mossy boulders and ledges where it typically grows. Naturally occurring sterile hybrids are known with A . platyneuron (these and their fertile allotetraploid derivatives are both referred to A . ebenoides ), A . ruta-muraria ( A . × inexpectatum E. L. Braun ex C. V. Morton), A . trichomanes subsp. trichomanes [ A . × shawneense (R. C. Moran) H. E. Ballard], and A . ebenoides . In addition, the allotetraploid A . pinnatifidum is derived from the hybrid A . montanum × rhizophyllum ; the sterile diploid hybrid is unknown.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
