<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1841">pellaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="D. C. Eaton" date="1865">breweri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 555. 1865</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus pellaea;species breweri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales uniformly reddish brown, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, thin, margins sinuous, nearly entire. Leaves monomorphic, clustered on stem, 2.5--20 cm; croziers sparsely villous.  Petiole  brown, lustrous, rounded adaxially, with prominent articulation lines near base.  Blade  linear-oblong, pinnate-pinnatifid proximally, 1--4 cm wide; rachis brown proximally, green distally, straight, rounded adaxially, glabrous to sparsely villous.  Pinnae  ascending or perpendicular to rachis, decurrent on rachis, deeply 2-lobed (mitten-shaped) near base of leaf; costae absent.  Ultimate segments  lanceolate-deltate, 5--25 mm, herbaceous, glabrous; margins recurved on fertile segments, covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, erose-denticulate; apex obtuse or rounded.  Veins  of ultimate segments evident.  Sporangia  sessile or subsessile, containing 64 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands. 2 n  = 58.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cliffs and rocky slopes, on a variety of substrates including granite and limestone;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1600--3800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., Nev., Oreg., Utah, Wash., Wyo.</description>
  <number>11</number>
  <discussion>Pellaea breweri is distinguished from other North American taxa (except for some populations of P . glabella ) by the presence of prominent articulation lines near the base of the petiole. The leaves are easily detached, and many herbarium specimens consist of separate leaves and stems, the latter covered with petiole bases of approximately equal length.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
