<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Dale M. Benham , Michael D. Windham</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="D. M. Benham &amp; Windham" date="1992">Astrolepis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>82: 55. 1992</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus Astrolepis</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek astro, star, and lepis, scale, in reference to the starlike scales on the adaxial blade surface]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  usually on rock.  Stems  compact to short-creeping, erect to ascending, sparingly branched; scales tan to chestnut brown, concolored to weakly bicolored, linear-attenuate, margins ciliate-dentate to entire.  Leaves  monomorphic, densely clustered, 7--130 cm.  Petiole  dull chestnut brown or straw-colored, rounded adaxially, sparsely to densely covered with scales, with 2 vascular bundles.  Blade  linear to linear-oblong, 1-pinnate to pinnate-pinnatifid, leathery, abaxially covered with overlapping, lanceolate to ovate, ciliate scales with underlying layer of stellate scales, adaxially sparsely to densely covered with stellate or coarsely ciliate scales, often glabrescent when mature, dull, not striate; rachis straight.  Ultimate segments  (pinnae) stalked to subsessile, free from axis, ovate, oblong or elongate-deltate, cordate to subcordate or rarely truncate at base, usually more than 4 mm wide; segment margins plane, undifferentiated, not recurved to form false indusia.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure, pinnately branched and divergent distally.  False indusium  absent.  Sporangia  scattered along veins near pinna margins (often clustered near notches between pinna lobes), containing 32 or 64 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands.  Spores  light to dark brown, tetrahedral-globose, rugose, lacking prominent equatorial ridge.  Gametophytes  glabrous.  x  = 29.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Star-scaled cloak ferns</other_name>
  <discussion>The species of Astrolepis have traditionally been assigned to either Notholaena (R. M. Tryon 1956) or Cheilanthes (J. T. Mickel 1979b; R. M. Tryon and A. F. Tryon 1982). Recent biosystematic analyses by D. M. Benham and M. D. Windham (1992) indicate, however, that the star-scaled cloak ferns form a distinctive, monophyletic group worthy of generic recognition. The combination of a chromosome base number of x = 29, pinnate leaves, two vascular bundles in the petioles, unique stellate or coarsely ciliate scales on the adaxial blade surface, and other characteristics separate Astrolepis from related genera.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 8 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Benham, D. M. 1989. A Biosystematic Revision of the Fern Genus Astrolepis (Adiantaceae). Ph.D. dissertation. Northern Arizona University.</reference>
    <reference>Benham, D. M. and M. D. Windham. 1992. Generic affinities of the star-scaled cloak ferns. Amer. Fern J. 82: 47--58.</reference>
    <reference>Hevly, R. H. 1965. Studies of the sinuous cloak fern ( Notholaena sinuata ) complex. J. Arizona Acad. Sci. 3: 205--208.</reference>
    <reference>Tryon, R. M. 1956. A revision of the American species of  Notholaena . Contr. Gray Herb. 179: 1--106.</reference>
    <reference>Benham, D. M. 1992. Additional combinations in Astrolepis . Amer. Fern J. 82: 59--62.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest pinnae usually 4–7 mm; most adaxial scales circular to elliptic, peltate; abaxial scales ovate, usually 0.5–1 mm.</description>
      <determination>1 Astrolepis cochisensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest pinnae usually 7–35 mm; most adaxial scales elongate, attached at their base; abaxial scales lanceolate, 1–1.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial scales dense, usually persistent; largest pinnae asymmetrically lobed or entire; body of adaxial pinna scales 5–7 cells wide.</description>
      <determination>2 Astrolepis integerrima</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial scales sparse, often deciduous; largest pinnae usually symmetrically lobed; body of adaxial pinna scales 1–4 cells wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial pinna surface sparsely scaly, at least some scales persistent; body of adaxial scales 2–4 cells wide; abaxial scales ciliate with coarse marginal projections; pinnae shallowly lobed, lobes usually broadly rounded.</description>
      <determination>3 Astrolepis windhamii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial pinna surface sparsely scaly to glabrescent, most scales deciduous with age; body of adaxial scales 1–2 cells wide; abaxial scales ciliate-dentate with delicate marginal projections; pinnae usually deeply lobed, lobes often acute.</description>
      <determination>4 Astrolepis sinuata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
