<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Roth" date="1799">polystichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="W. H. Wagner" date="1966">kruckebergii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>56: 4. 1966</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus polystichum;species kruckebergii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  ascending.  Leaves  erect, 1--2.5 dm; bulblets absent.  Petiole  1/10--1/5 length of leaf, sparsely scaly; scales light brown, gradually diminishing in size distally.  Blade  linear, 1-pinnate-pinnatifid, base narrowed.  Pinnae  rhombic-ovate to short-falcate, proximal pinnae ± triangular; pinnae overlapping, twisted somewhat out of plane of blade, 0.5--1.5 cm; base oblique, acroscopic auricle well developed; margins shallowly incised to merely dentate or serrulate, teeth spreading and spiny at tip; apex acute with subapical and apical teeth same size; microscales lanceolate with few projections, confined to costa, on abaxial surface only.  Indusia  entire.  Spores  dark brown. 2 n  = 164.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Rocks and cliffs in subalpine to alpine habitats;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="rocks and cliffs in subalpine to alpine habitats ;" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">1500--3200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Calif., Idaho, Mont., Nev., Oreg., Utah, Wash.</description>
  <number>8</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Kruckeberg's holly fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Polystichum kruckebergii is widely but sporadically distributed in small numbers in both the Sierra-Cascade and Rocky Mountain systems. Populations sometimes consist of only two or three dwarfed plants that are difficult to distinguish from P . scopulinum , with which they may occur. The spreading teeth of equal size at the pinna apex will usually distinguish this species. Polystichum kruckebergii is a tetraploid presumed to be of hybrid origin, with P . lonchitis and P . lemmonii as its diploid progenitors (W. H. Wagner Jr. 1973), although this hypothesis has not been confirmed. The hybrid with P . munitum has been found in Washington (P. S. Soltis et al. 1987) with both parents, and it is distinguished by intermediate morphology and abortive sporangia.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
