<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Bartlett" date="unknown">cupressaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">juniperus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">communis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1040. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cupressaceae;genus juniperus;species communis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs  or small trees dioecious, to 4 m (if trees, to 10 m), multistemmed, decumbent or rarely upright; crown generally depressed.  Bark  brown, fibrous, exfoliating in thin strips, that of small branchlets (5--10 mm diam.) smooth, that of larger branchlets exfoliating in strips and plates.  Branches  spreading or ascending; branchlets erect, terete.  Leaves  green but sometimes appearing silver when glaucous, spreading, abaxial glands very elongate; adaxial surface with glaucous stomatal band; apex acute to obtuse, mucronate.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, of 2 distinct sizes, with straight peduncles, globose to ovoid, 6--13 mm, bluish black, glaucous, resinous to obscurely woody, with 2--3 seeds.  Seeds  4--5 mm. 2 n  = 22.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Eurasia.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Common juniper</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">genévrier commun</other_name>
  <discussion>Juniperus communis is the most widespread juniper species, and many subspecies and varieties have been described. A major study, including chemical characters, is needed to clarify the taxonomy. J. D. A. Franco (1962) recognized four subspecies (here considered varieties); two of these---var. communis and var. hemisphaerica (J. Presl &amp; C. Presl) Parlatore---do not occur in the flora and a fifth, recognized here, was not treated by Franco.</discussion>
  <discussion>The seed cones of Juniperus communis are used to flavor gin.</discussion>
  <discussion>Varieties 5 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones 9--13 mm, longer than leaves.</description>
      <determination>1a var. megistocarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones 6--9 mm, shorter than leaves.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Glaucous stomatal band on adaxial leaf surface 2 or more times as wide as each green marginal band; spreading to matlike shrubs; leaves linear-lanceolate, to 2 mm wide, apex acute to obtuse and mucronate.</description>
      <determination>1b var. montana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Glaucous stomatal band on adaxial leaf surface about as wide as each green marginal band; prostrate, low shrubs with ascending branchlet tips (occasionally spreading shrubs, rarely small trees); leaves linear, to 1.6 mm wide, apex acute and mucronate to acuminate.</description>
      <determination>1c var. depressa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
