<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Walter" date="1788">glabra</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Carol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>237. 1788</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species glabra</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 30m; trunk to 1m diam., straight; crown conic to rounded.  Bark  gray, fissured and cross-checked into elongate, irregular, scaly plates, resin pockets absent, on upper sections of trunk ± smooth, gray, looking slick.  Branches  whorled, spreading to ascending; twigs slender, purple-red to red-brown, occasionally glaucous, aging gray, smooth.  Buds  ovoid to ovoid-cylindric, red-brown, ca. 0.5--1cm, slightly resinous; scale margins finely fringed.  Leaves  2 per fascicle, spreading to ascending, persisting 2--3 years, 4--8(--10)cm × 0.7--1.2mm, straight, slightly twisted, dark green, all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins finely serrulate, apex sharply conic; sheath 0.5--1cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  lance-cylindric, 10--15mm, purple-brown.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter, semipersistent, spreading to recurved, nearly symmetric, lance-ovoid before opening, ovoid-cylindric when open, 3.5--7cm, red-brown, aging gray, nearly sessile or on stalks to 1cm, scales lacking contrasting border on adaxial surfaces (as in  P .  echinata ); apophyses but slightly thickened and raised; umbo central, depressed, unarmed or with small, curved, weak, deciduous, short-incurved prickle.  Seeds  deltoid-obovoid; body ca. 6mm, brown, mottled darker; wing to ca. 12mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy alluvium and mesic woodland;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--150m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Fla., Ga., La., Miss., S.C.</description>
  <number>20</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Spruce pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus glabra is more shade tolerant than most yellow pines. Although the trees grow large, the wood is not much valued. The species is similar in tree form to P . strobus . It resembles P . echinata in shoot and leaf but has less prickly cones and deeper green leaves.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
