<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas ex Loudon" date="1838">contorta</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Arbor. Frutic. Brit.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 2292, figs. 2210, 2211. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species contorta</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees  to 50m; trunk to 0.9m diam., straight to contorted; crown various according to genetic race.  Bark  brown to gray- or red-brown, platy to furrowed.  Lower branches  often descending, the upper spreading or ascending.  Twigs  slender, orange to red-brown, aging darker brown, rough.  Buds  narrowly to broadly ovoid, dark red-brown, to 1.2cm, slightly resinous.  Leaves  2 per fascicle, spreading or ascending, persisting 3--8 years, 2--8cm × 0.7--2(--3)mm, twisted, yellow-green to dark green, all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins finely serrulate, apex blunt to acute or narrowly acuminate; sheath 0.3--0.6(--1)cm, persistent.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid to cylindric, 5--15mm, orange-red.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years or variably serotinous, variably persistent, spreading to reflexed, often curved, nearly symmetric or variably asymmetric, lanceoloid to ovoid before opening, broadly ovoid to nearly globose when open, 2--6cm, tan to pale red-brown, lustrous, nearly sessile or on stalks to 1cm; apophyses nearly rhombic, variously elongate, cross-keeled, often mammillate toward outer cone base and on inside above middle; umbo central, depressed-triangular, prickle barely elongate to stubby or slender and to 6mm.  Seeds  compressed, obovoid; body ca. 5mm, red-brown, mottled with black, or all black; wing 10--14mm. 2 n =24 (variety not indicated).</description>
  <description type="distribution">only in the flora.</description>
  <number>33</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Lodgepole pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus contorta is fire successional over most of its range and is characterized by prolific seeding and high seed viability in disturbed habitats, often resulting in extremely slow-growing, overly dense stands. Some authors consider it to consist of 4 races; these have been given various infraspecific ranks, but perhaps they are more conventionally treated as 3 varieties.</discussion>
  <discussion>Varieties 3:</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 2-7 cm × 0.7-0.9(-1.1) mm, dark green; mature trunk with bark evidently furrowed; seed cones strongly asymmetric, strongly recurved, persistent or variously serotinous.</description>
      <determination>33a var. contorta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves (4-)5-8 cm × (0.7-)1-2(-3) mm, yellow-green; mature trunk with bark not evidently furrowed; seed cones asymmetric to nearly symmetric, recurved to spreading, variously serotinous or soon shed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones asymmetric, recurved, variously serotinous, long-persistent; mid and lower apophyses mostly much domed; main branches mostly horizontally spreading, not ascending at tip.</description>
      <determination>33b var. latifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones nearly symmetric, mostly spreading, not serotinous, not persistent; mid and lower apophyses mostly shallowly domed; main branches ascending at tips.</description>
      <determination>33c var. murrayana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
