<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robbin C. Moran</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="C. Christensen" date="1916">Maxonia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Misc. Collect.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>66(9): 3. 1916</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Maxonia</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for William R. Maxon, (1877--1948), American pteridologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  hemiepiphytic.  Stems  long-creeping and climbing trees, stolons absent.  Leaves  strongly dimorphic, fertile leaves greatly contracted, evergreen.  Petiole  ± equaling length of blade, base not swollen; vascular bundles more than 3, arranged in an arc, ± round in cross section.  Blade  deltate, 3--4-pinnate-pinnatifid, gradually reduced distally to pinnatifid apex, somewhat leathery.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins dentate to lobed; proximal pinnae largest or nearly so, petiolulate, ± equilateral or inequilateral, basiscopic side with pinnules longer than on acroscopic side; costae adaxially deeply grooved, grooves continuous from rachis to costae to costules; indument of transparent hairs along costae on both sides, also with a few linear scales abaxially on costae.  Veins  free, simple or forked. Sori in 1 row between midrib and margin, round; indusia round-reniform with shallow sinus, persistent.  Spores  brownish, spiny to broadly rugose.  x  = 41.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical.</description>
  <number>11</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Climbing wood fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Christensen, C. 1916.  Maxonia , a new genus of tropical American ferns. Smithsonian Misc. Collect. 66(9): 1--4.</reference>
    <reference>Moran, R. C. 1987. Monograph of the neotropical fern genus  Polybotrya  (Dryopteridaceae). Bull. Illinois Nat. Hist. Surv. 34: 1--138.</reference>
    <reference>Walker, T. G. 1972. The anatomy of  Maxonia apiifolia : A climbing fern. Brit. Fern Gaz. 10: 241--250.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
