<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Jermy" date="1986">tetragonostachys</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. Braun" date="1865">tortipila</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>3: 271. 1865</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus tetragonostachys;species tortipila</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  on rock or terrestrial, forming compact clumps or mounds.  Stems  radially symmetric, underground (rhizomatous) and aerial, not readily fragmenting, irregularly forked; rhizomatous and aerial stems often with 1 branch arrested, budlike, tips straight; aerial stems erect or ascending to decumbent, budlike branches throughout.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems, restricted to rhizomatous stems or to lowermost base of aerial stems, 0.2--0.3 mm diam.  Leaves  dimorphic, in alternate pseudowhorls of 5.  Rhizomatous stem leaves  strongly appressed, overlapping, scalelike.  Aerial stem leaves  tightly appressed, ascending, green, narrowly lanceolate to linear-lanceolate, (2.5--)3--4.5 X 0.4--0.7 mm; abaxial ridges inconspicuous or more visible from apex to middle of leaf; base cuneate, decurrent, glabrous; margins short-ciliate to denticulate or entire, cilia transparent, spreading, 0.02--0.06(--0.08) mm; apex keeled (more so in dry leaves); bristle transparent or yellowish to brownish near base, puberulent, twisted, persistent or falling off early, 1.2--1.7 mm (1/3--1/2 length of leaves).  Strobili  solitary, 4--6 mm; sporophylls ovate-lanceolate to lanceolate, abaxial ridges obvious, base glabrous, margins denticulate, apex keeled, long-bristled, bristle twisted.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>soil, less often in shaded sites;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="soil" />
        <character name="habitat" value="shaded sites" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">600--1500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga., N.C., S.C., Tenn.</description>
  <number>12</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Kinky-hair spike-moss</other_name>
  <discussion>Selaginella tortipila , a very distinct species, is probably without close relatives in the flora but may be distantly related to S . rupestris . The two irregularly forked branches are particularly unusual: the larger one forms the strobilus while the smaller becomes arrested and forms either a budlike branch or grows and divides again to form a vegetative shoot.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
