<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. A. Whitmore &amp; A. R. Smith" date="1991">calirhiza</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>38: 235. 1991</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus polypodium;species calirhiza</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker &amp; Arnott" date="unknown">intermedium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>1840,</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>not Colla 1836</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polypodium;species intermedium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">vulgare</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Hooker &amp; Arnott) Fernald" date="unknown">intermedium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polypodium;species vulgare;variety intermedium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  rarely whitish to glaucous, moderately stout to slender, to 8 mm diam., acrid- or slightly sweet-tasting; scales concolored brown or slightly darker near point of attachment, lanceolate-ovate, symmetric, margins entire to erose.  Leaves  to 70 cm.  Petiole  usually slender, to 3 mm diam.  Blade  lanceolate-ovate to oblong, pinnatifid, widest below middle or occasionally at base, to 16 cm wide, leathery to herbaceous; rachis sparsely scaly to glabrescent abaxially, puberulent adaxially; scales lanceolate-ovate, usually more than 3 cells wide.  Segments  linear-lanceolate to oblong, usually less than 15 mm wide; margins conspicuously serrate; apex obtuse to acute; midrib puberulent adaxially.  Venation  weakly to moderately anastomosing, some to many segments lacking areoles.  Sori  midway between margin and midrib or slightly closer to midrib, usually less than 4 mm diam., oval when immature.  Sporangiasters  absent.  Spores  more than 58 µm, verrucose, surface projections less than 3 µm. 2 n  = 148.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating winter--summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cliffs and rocky slopes, sometimes epiphytic, on a variety of substrates but usually on granite or other igneous rocks;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif., Oreg.; Mexico.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <discussion>Although originally considered a cytotype of Polypodium californicum , P . calirhiza is an allotetraploid involving P . californicum and P . glycyrrhiza (S. A. Whitmore and A. R. Smith 1991) and therefore should be treated as a distinct species. Some individuals of P . calirhiza can be difficult to distinguish from the two parental species (see comments under P . californicum and P . glycyrrhiza ); most collections can be identified based on a combination of blade shape, venation pattern, spore size, and geographic distribution. Polypodium calirhiza hybridizes with P . glycyrrhiza to produce sterile triploid plants with misshapen spores.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
