<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Masahiro Kato</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hooker &amp; Greville" date="1829">Deparia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Icon. Filic.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(8). 1829</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Deparia</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek depas, saucer, referring to the saucerlike indusium of the type species, Deparia prolifera, which is aberrant in the genus]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants terrestrial.  Stems creeping, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, dying back in winter. Petiole 1/3--2/3 length of blade, base swollen and persisting as trophopod over winter or not; vascular bundles 2, lateral, lunate in cross section.  Blade  elliptic to ovate-lanceolate, 1-pinnate-pinnatifid [pinnatifid to 3-pinnate-pinnatifid], gradually reduced distally to pinnatifid apex, herbaceous.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins entire, crenulate, or serrate; proximal pinnae (several pairs) reduced or not, sessile, equilateral; costae adaxially shallowly grooved, grooves not continuous with that of rachis; indument on rachis and costae (both sides) of multicellular hairs.  Veins  free, simple or forked.  Sori  on veins, elongate, ± straight, or hooked at distal end; indusia linear, laterally attached, persistent.  Spores  brownish, broadly winged.  x  = 40.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, e Asia, se and tropical Africa including Madagascar, Pacific Islands, Australia.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <discussion>Petiole bases are swollen and toothed in sect. Lunathyrium (Koidzumi) M. Kato but not or only slightly thickened and without teeth in sects. Athyriopsis (Ching) M. Kato, Deparia , and Dryoathyrium (Ching) M. Kato.</discussion>
  <discussion>Two American species, one native and the other introduced, are usually placed in Athyrium or Diplazium . The genus Deparia , however, including these two species, is sufficiently distinct to warrant generic separation because of its nondecurrent costal grooves and the presence of multicellular hairs on blades (M. Kato 1984).</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kato, M. 1984. A taxonomic study of the athyrioid fern genus  Deparia  with main reference to the Pacific species. J. Fac. Sci. Univ. Tokyo, Sect. 3, Bot. 13: 375--430.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves markedly narrowed to base; petiole bases swollen and dentate.</description>
      <determination>1 Deparia acrostichoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not or only slightly narrowed to base; petiole bases neither markedly swollen nor dentate.</description>
      <determination>2 Deparia petersenii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
