<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">acrostichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Langsdorff &amp; Fischer" date="1810">danaeifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pl. Voy. Russes Monde</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 5, plate 1. 1810</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus acrostichum;species danaeifolium</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Acrostichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Jenman" date="unknown">lomarioides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Acrostichum;species lomarioides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  usually erect, infrequently branched.  Leaves  ascending or erect, 1.5--5 m × 15--60 cm.  Rachis  shallowly grooved abaxially, flat or shallowly grooved adaxially.  Pinnae  20--32(--64), distant to closely spaced, usually overlapping, 7--37 × 1.5--5.5 cm, tapering toward apex, abruptly acute at tip; costal areoles less than 3 times longer than wide; most pinnae of fertile leaves bearing sporangia.  Sporangia  spread over abaxial surface of fertile pinnae; paraphyses stalked, ending with horizontally extended, smooth or little-lobed cell.  Spores  (44--)54(--72) µm diam., surface minutely roughened with small projecting papillae. 2 n  = 60.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Somewhat saline to freshwater swamps, canal and pond margins, commonly in sinkholes in hammocks, disturbed marl sites, inland to coastal regions;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="somewhat saline to freshwater swamps" />
        <character name="habitat" value="canal" />
        <character name="habitat" value="pond margins" />
        <character name="habitat" value="commonly in sinkholes" constraint="in hammocks , disturbed marl sites , inland to coastal regions" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--50 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.; Central America; South America.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <discussion>These species frequently can be distinguished by the distribution of pinnae, the distribution of fertile pinnae, the shape of the costal areoles, and the structure of the paraphyses. In parts of Florida, their distributions are contiguous and abruptly separated by habitat. Acrosticum aureum is more frequently found in coastal shaded areas, in saline black-mangrove communities, and in the southern and southwestern parts of the state. Acrostichum danaeifolium grows vigorously in full sun and is common and widely distributed in Florida, where it has been collected in virtually every county throughout the southern two-thirds of the state. Hybrids have been produced in the laboratory, although these have not been analyzed cytologically. Hybrids are apparently rare in the field and have been reported only in the Dominican Republic (I. García de López 1978).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
