<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Chapman ex Engelmann) Sargent" date="1884">clausa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rep. For. N. America</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>199. 1884</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species clausa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Aiton" date="unknown">inops</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Chapman ex Engelmann" date="unknown">clausa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 125. 1877</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species inops;variety clausa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">clausa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="D.B. Ward" date="unknown">immuginata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species clausa;variety immuginata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 21m; trunk to 0.5m diam., straight and erect to leaning and crooked, much branched; crown mostly rounded or irregular.  Bark  gray to gray-brown, furrowed, with narrow, flat, irregular ridges, resin pockets absent, on upper sections of the trunk reddish to red-brown, platy becoming smooth distally.  Branches  spreading to ascending, poorly self-pruning; twigs slender, violet- to red-brown, rarely glaucous, aging gray, smooth.  Buds  cylindric, purple-brown, to 1cm; scale margins white-fringed.  Leaves  2 per fascicle, spreading-ascending, persisting 2--3 years, (3--)6--9(--10)cm × ca. 1mm, straight, slightly twisted, dark green, all surfaces with fine, inconspicuous stomatal lines, margins finely serrulate, apex short-conic; sheath 0.3--0.5(--0.7)cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid, ca. 10mm, brownish yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter or often long-serotinous, long-persistent, solitary or whorled, spreading, symmetric (rarely slightly asymmetric, reflexed), lanceoloid before opening, ovoid to broadly ovoid when open, 3--8cm, red-brown, sessile or on stalks to 1cm, scales with dark red-brown, purple, or purple-gray border distally on adaxial surface; apophyses thickened, shallowly and angulately raised, transversely rhombic, cross-keeled; umbo central, low-pyramidal, tapering to sharp tip or weak, often deciduous prickle.  Seeds  obovoid-oblique; body ca. 4mm, dark brown to nearly black; wing to 17mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Fire successional in sand dunes and white sandhills;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--60m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Fla.</description>
  <number>35</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sand pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Although Pinus clausa is too profusely branched to be important for saw timber, it is managed to produce a high volume of pulpwood in northern peninsular Florida.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
