<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="1803">serotina</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 205. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species serotina</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Miller" date="unknown">rigida</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="(Michaux) R.T. Clausen" date="unknown">serotina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species rigida;subspecies serotina;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">rigida</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Michaux) Hoopes" date="unknown">serotina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species rigida;variety serotina;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 21m; trunk to 0.6m diam., straight or more often crooked, commonly with adventitious sprouts; crown becoming ragged, thin, often broadly rounded or flat.  Bark  red-brown, irregularly furrowed and cross-checked into rectangular, flat, scaly plates.  Branches  spreading to ascending; twigs stout, orange- to yellow-orange, frequently glaucous, aging darker.  Buds  ovoid to narrowly ovoid, red-brown, 1--1.5(--2)cm, resinous.  Leaves  3 per fascicle (to 5 in adventitious or disturbed growth), spreading to ascending, persisting 2--3 years, (12--)15--20(--21)cm × 1.3--1.5(--2)mm, slightly twisted, tufted at twig tips, straight, yellow-green, all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins serrulate, apex acuminate; sheath 1--2cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  cylindric, to 30mm, yellow-brown.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, in some populations beginning to shed seeds then but more often variably serotinous, long-persistent, often whorled, symmetric, ovoid to lanceoloid before opening, broadly ovoid to nearly globose when open, 5--8cm, pale red-brown to creamy brown, sessile or on stalks to 1cm, scales with dark red-brown border on adaxial surface distally; apophyses slightly thickened, low, rhombic, low cross-keeled; umbo central, low-conic, with short, weak prickle, sometimes unarmed.  Seeds  ellipsoid, oblique at tip, somewhat compressed; body 5--6mm, pale brown, mottled darker or nearly black; wing to 20mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Flatwoods, flatwoods bogs, savannas, and barrens;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--200m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Del., Fla., Ga., Md., N.J., N.C., S.C., Va.</description>
  <number>22</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pond pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus serotina is fire successional and sprouts adventitiously after crown fires. It is part of a distinct forest type including Taxodium distichum (Linnaeus) Richard, Nyssa biflora Walter, Magnolia virginiana Linnaeus, Persea sp., and Ilex sp. Of good form when protected from fire, P . serotina then much resembles P . taeda , with which it hybridizes naturally. It is of increasing importance as pulpwood.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
