<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Gymnospermae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Gymnospermae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2</number>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves pinnately compound, leaflets linear; dioecious; stem below ground, or its leaf-bearing apex exposed; Florida and Georgia.</description>
      <determination>1 Zamiaceae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves simple, fan-shaped, needlelike, or scalelike; dioecious or monoecious; stem aboveground; widespread.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves deciduous, fan-shaped, dichotomously veined; ovules 2 at ends of long stalks, often only 1 maturing.</description>
      <determination>2 Ginkgoaceae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly evergreen (deciduous in Larix and usually in Taxodium, often ephemeral and not photosynthetic in Ephedra), needlelike or scalelike, not dichotomously veined; ovules (and seeds) 1--20 on cone scales or 1 on short stalks.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Longest internodes 2--10 cm (shorter at bases of branches); pollen cones compound, each sporangiophore subtended by a pair of bracteoles; seeds inserted on axis of seed cone, subtended by several pairs or whorls of papery, herbaceous, or fleshy bracts; shrubs (sometimes clambering), neither resinous nor fragrant; dry areas in w United States (se Texas to Oregon and California).</description>
      <determination>6 Ephedraceae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Longest internodes 0--1 cm; pollen cones simple, the individual sporophylls not bracteate (usually few sterile bracts at base of cone); seeds inserted on scales of seed cone, scales woody (fleshy and coalescent in Juniperus), or the seeds solitary and not enclosed by bracts or scales in Taxaceae; shrubs or trees, usually resinous and fragrant; widespread.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed 1, subtended by but not concealed by inconspicuous sterile bracts, with fleshy or juicy arils; leaves needlelike, spreading in 1 plane ("2-ranked") (except on erect shoots), without resin canals.</description>
      <determination>5 Taxaceae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seeds 1--400 in woody or fleshy cones, enclosed by conspicuous cone-scales, without arils (if cones fleshy then leaves not spreading in 1 plane); leaves needlelike or scalelike, spreading in 1 plane or not, with or without resin canals.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Foliage leaves needlelike, alternate or fascicled, individually abcising from branchlets when shed (except that fascicles in Pinus are shed as units); cone scales imbricate, seeds 2 per scale.</description>
      <determination>3 Pinaceae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Foliage leaves needlelike or scalelike, alternate, opposite, or whorled, persistent on branchlets (but most branchlets shed with age); cone scales valvate or imbricate (if imbricate then leaves opposite and scalelike), seeds 1--20 per scale.</description>
      <determination>4 Cupressaceae</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
