<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bernhardi" date="1806">cystopteris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Weatherby) Blasdell" date="1963">laurentiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21(4): 51. 1963</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus cystopteris;species laurentiana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cystopteris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Bernhardi" date="unknown">fragilis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Weatherby" date="unknown">laurentiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>28: 129. 1926</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cystopteris;species fragilis;variety laurentiana;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  creeping, not cordlike, internodes very short, less than 5 mm, heavily beset with old petiole bases, hairs absent; scales uniformly brown to ± clathrate, radial walls brown, luminae clear.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered at stem apex, to 45 cm, nearly all bearing sori.  Petiole  usually dark at base, grading to straw-colored distally, shorter than blade, sparsely scaly at base.  Blade  ovate to narrowly ovate, 2-pinnate to 2-pinnate-pinnatifid, widest above base, apex short-attenuate; rachis and costae usually sparsely invested with unicellular, gland-tipped hairs, occasionally with misshapen bulblets; axils of pinnae with occasional multicellular, gland-tipped hairs.  Pinnae  typically perpendicular to rachis, not curving toward blade apex, margins serrate; proximal pinnae pinnate-pinnatifid to pinnatifid, ± equilateral, basiscopic pinnules not enlarged, basal basiscopic pinnules sessile to short-stalked, base truncate to obtuse; distal pinnae ovate to oblong.  Veins  directed into teeth and notches.  Indusia  cup-shaped, apex truncate, typically sparsely invested with unicellular, gland-tipped hairs.  Spores  spiny, usually 49--60 µm. 2 n  = 252.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Cracks and ledges on cliffs, often on calcareous substrates;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="cracks" constraint="on cliffs , often on calcareous substrates" />
        <character name="habitat" value="ledges" constraint="on cliffs , often on calcareous substrates" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.B., Nfld., N.S., Ont., Que.; Conn., Ill., Iowa, Mass., Mich., Minn., Pa., Vt., Wis.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Laurentian bladder fern</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cystoptère laurentienne</other_name>
  <discussion>Cystopteris laurentiana is a sexual allohexaploid species with C . bulbifera as the diploid parent and C . fragilis as the tetraploid. Cystopteris laurentiana was previously thought to be common only in the Great Lakes region (R. F. Blasdell 1963); it is now known to occur frequently in the Driftless Area of the Midwest. Because C . laurentiana can be difficult to distinguish from C . fragilis , specimens with ovate leaves having unusually large spores and growing on moist cliffs should be checked carefully for occasional glandular hairs, the distinguishing feature of C . laurentiana . Sterile pentaploid hybrids between C . laurentiana and C . fragilis have been discovered where the two species are sympatric.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
