<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1806">cheilanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Davenport" date="1883">pringlei</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 61. 1883</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cheilanthes;species pringlei</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  long-creeping, 1--3 mm diam.; scales uniformly brown or with poorly defined, dark, central stripe, linear-lanceolate, straight to slightly contorted, loosely appressed, usually persistent.  Leaves  clustered to somewhat scattered, 4--15 cm; vernation noncircinate.  Petiole  dark brown, grooved distally on adaxial surface.  Blade  ovate-deltate, 3-pinnate-pinnatifid at base, 1.5--5 cm wide; rachis grooved adaxially, with scattered, lanceolate scales, not pubescent.  Pinnae  not articulate, dark color of stalk continuing into pinna base, basal pair conspicuously larger than adjacent pair, inequilateral, basiscopic pinnules enlarged, appearing glabrous adaxially.  Costae  green adaxially for most of length; abaxial scales multiseriate, lanceolate, truncate or subcordate at base, without overlapping basal lobes, conspicuous, the largest 0.4--0.8 mm wide, loosely imbricate, not concealing ultimate segments, erose, not ciliate.  Ultimate segments  spatulate, not especially beadlike, the largest usually 2--3 mm, abaxially glabrous or with a few small scales near base, adaxially glabrous.  False indusia  marginal, weakly differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  discontinuous, confined to apical or lateral lobes.  Sporangia  containing 64 spores. 2 n  = 60.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating late spring--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Rocky slopes and ledges, usually on igneous substrates;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="rocky slopes" />
        <character name="habitat" value="ledges" />
        <character name="habitat" value="igneous substrates" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">700--1200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.; n Mexico.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pringle's lip fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Cheilanthes pringlei is often confused with young, sterile plants of C . fendleri , but it is easily distinguished from the latter by having rachises that are grooved adaxially. This species appears to be restricted to the Sonoran Desert; records from Gila and Cochise counties, Arizona, and southern New Mexico are based on misidentifications.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
