<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Horianow" date="unknown">zamiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1762">Zamia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl., ed. 2</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 659. 1762</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family zamiaceae;genus Zamia</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Derivation equivocal, perhaps from misreading of Latin azania, a kind of pine cone, or from Latin zamia, loss, from the "sterile appearance" of the pollen cones]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  often branched, subterranean to aboveground.  Leaves  broadly oblong-elliptic; leaflets entire to coarsely dentate, without midribs, venation dichotomous but appearing parallel.  Cones  distinctly peduncled.  Pollen cones  more slender than seed cones.  x  = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">subtropics and tropics, North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 30 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Duncan, W. H. 1979.  Zamia  (Cycadaceae) new for Georgia. Sida 8: 115--116.</reference>
    <reference>Eckenwalder, J. E. 1980. Dispersal of the West Indian cycad  Zamia pumila  L. Biotropica 12: 79--80.</reference>
    <reference>Eckenwalder, J. E. 1980b. Taxonomy of the West Indian cycads. J. Arnold Arbor. 61: 701--722.</reference>
    <reference>Hardin, J. W. 1971. Studies of the southeastern United States flora. II. The gymnosperms. J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. 87: 43--50.</reference>
    <reference>Kral, R. 1983b. Cycadaceae: Zamia integrifolia Ait. In: R. Kral, ed. 1983. A Report on Some Rare, Threatened, or Endangered Forest-related Vascular Plants of the South. Washington. Pp. 20--23. [U.S.D.A., Techn. Publ. R8-TP 2.]</reference>
    <reference>Stevenson, D. W. 1987b. Comments on character distribution, taxonomy and nomenclature of the genus  Zamia  L. in the West Indies and Mexico. Encephalartos 9: 3--7.</reference>
    <reference>Ward, D. B., ed. N.d. Rare and Endangered Biota of Florida. Vol. 5. Plants. Gainesville. Pp. 122--124.</reference>
    <reference>Landry, G. P. 1980. The Ecology and Variation of Zamia pumila L. in Florida. M.S. thesis. Louisiana State University.</reference>
    <reference>Stevenson, D. W. 1987. Again the West Indian zamias. Fairchild Trop. Gard. Bull. 42(3): 23--27.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
