<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Warren H. Wagner Jr.  , Florence S. Wagner</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Agardh" date="unknown">ophioglossaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="C. Presl" date="1845">Cheiroglossa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Suppl. Tent. Pterid.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>56. 1845</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ophioglossaceae;genus Cheiroglossa</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek cheir, hand, and glossa, tongue; in reference to the palmately lobed trophophores and the linear sporophores]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic.  Roots  dichotomously divided at wide intervals, pale yellowish to brown, 1--1.5 mm diam., smooth, proliferous.  Stems  pendent, to 1.5 mm thick but appearing thicker because of persistent leaf bases, gemmae absent.  Trophophores  arching or pendent, blades stalked, palmately lobed, broadly fan-shaped, to 45 × 30 cm; margins entire; apex rounded to acute; veins anastomosing, major areoles very large, to 35 × 8 mm.  Sporophores  numerous, to 10, arising on each side of base of trophophore blade and apex of trophophore stalk.  Sporangial clusters  with sporangia in 2 rows embedded in compact, linear spike, apiculum absent.  Gametophytes  brown to white, cylindric, repeatedly branched, branches 2--20, 1--4 mm thick, and the whole ± stellate structure sometimes reaching 20 mm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">very scattered and local in tropics, North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hand fern</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">dwarf staghorn</other_name>
  <discussion>Cheiroglossa , which is sometimes treated as a subgenus of Ophioglossum , is widely divergent from Ophioglossum in many characteristics, including the epiphytic habit, dichotomous roots, hairy stem apex, pendent and very large trophophore, palmately lobed blade, extremely large areoles, sporophores multiple and arising from sides of blade base, and the much branched gametophytes.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
