<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker &amp; Greville" date="1829">scouleri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Icon. Filic.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 56. 1829</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus polypodium;species scouleri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  conspicuously whitish pruinose, stout, 3--12 mm diam., bland to slightly sweet-tasting; scales concolored to weakly bicolored, uniformly dark brown or with pale margins and base, lanceolate, symmetric, margins denticulate.  Leaves  to 85 cm.  Petiole  stout, to 3 mm diam.  Blade  ovate-lanceolate, pinnatifid, usually widest just above base, to 27 cm wide, stiff and leathery; rachis sparsely scaly to glabrescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially; scales bicolored, ovate-lanceolate, much more than 6 cells wide.  Segments  oblong to linear, usually more than 12 mm wide; margins entire to crenulate; apex rounded to rarely broadly acute; midrib glabrous adaxially.  Venation  anastomosing, usually forming 1 row of areoles.  Sori  crowded against midrib, usually more than 3 mm diam., circular when immature.  Sporangiasters  absent.  Spores  usually less than 52 µm, rugose, surface projections less than 3 µm tall. 2 n  = 74, 111.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating late fall--spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Cracks and ledges on cliffs, occasionally epiphytic, on a variety of substrates but preferring volcanic substrates in warmer, drier climates, rarely far from ocean;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="cracks" constraint="on cliffs , occasionally epiphytic , on a variety of substrates but preferring volcanic substrates in warmer , drier climates , rarely far from ocean" />
        <character name="habitat" value="ledges" constraint="on cliffs , occasionally epiphytic , on a variety of substrates but preferring volcanic substrates in warmer , drier climates , rarely far from ocean" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Calif., Oreg., Wash.; Mexico in Baja California.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Coast polypody</other_name>
  <discussion>The distinctive Polypodium scouleri has occasionally been assigned to the genus Goniophlebium because of its anastomosing venation and conspicuous areoles. Its venation pattern can be quite variable, however, and cannot be used as the sole feature distinguishing P . scouleri from P . californicum . Combining venation characteristics with others provided in the key distinguishes it clearly from its congeners in Polypodium . Some evidence suggests that P . scouleri hybridizes with P . californicum (S. A. Whitmore, unpubl.). I. Manton (1951) reported diploid and triploid cytotypes for P . scouleri , and variation in spore size suggests that the species may also include tetraploid populations.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
