<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David C. Michener</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Bartlett" date="unknown">cupressaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Spach" date="1841">Chamaecyparis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>11: 329. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cupressaceae;genus Chamaecyparis</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chamai, on the ground, or dwarf, and cyparissos, cypress]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  (rarely shrubs).  Branchlets  terete or rhombic in cross section, in fan-shaped or pinnately flattened sprays.  Leaves  opposite in 4 ranks.  Adult leaves  usually appressed, lateral and facial pairs similar, closely overlapping, scalelike, free portion of long-shoot leaves to ca. 7 mm; abaxial glands present or absent, circular to linear.  Pollen cones  with 2--3 pairs of sporophylls, each sporophyll with 2--4 pollen sacs.  Seed cones  maturing and opening in 1--2 years, nearly globose, glaucous, 4--12 mm; scales persistent, 2--5(--6) pairs, valvate, peltate or basifixed, thick and woody, terminal pair often fused.  Seeds  1--4 per cone scale, lenticular, equally 2-winged; cotyledons 2--3.  x  = 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, e Asia.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">White-cedar</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">false-cypress</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">faux-cypres</other_name>
  <discussion>Two Japanese species are widely cultivated and may become established locally. Chamaecyparis obtusa (Siebold &amp; Zuccarini) Endlicher (hinoki-cypress) has obtuse, glandless leaves and seed cones ca. 10--12 mm broad; C . pisifera (Siebold &amp; Zuccarini) Endlicher (sawara-cypress) has acuminate, obscurely glandular leaves and seed cones 6--8 mm broad. Cultivated juvenile forms of several species have been referred to by the superfluous Retinospora Siebold &amp; Zuccarini. Some authors include species of Chamaecyparis in the genus Cupressus .</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 6--7 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones 4-9 mm broad; leaves usually with circular abaxial glands; Atlantic and Gulf coasts.</description>
      <determination>1 Chamaecyparis thyoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones 8-12 mm broad; leaves with linear to circular abaxial glands or glands absent; Pacific Coast.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones with 5-9 scales, opening at end of first year, not notably resinous; leaves usually with linear glands; facial leaves of branchlets frequently separated from each other by paired bases of lateral leaves.</description>
      <determination>2 Chamaecyparis lawsoniana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones with 4-6 scales, sometimes remaining closed at end of first year, becoming resinous; leaves usually without glands, these circular when present; apices of facial leaves of branchlets often overlapping the base of next facial leaf.</description>
      <determination>3 Chamaecyparis nootkatensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
