<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Warren H. Wagner Jr. , Florence S. Wagner</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Agardh" date="unknown">Ophioglossaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Ophioglossaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  perennials, terrestrial or epiphytic.  Roots  lacking root hairs, unbranched or with a few narrow lateral branches, in 1 species dichotomously branched.  Stems  simple, unbranched, upright, with eustelic vascular tissue.  Leaf bases  dilated, clasping, forming sheath, open or fused, surrounding successive leaf primordia; primordia glabrous or with long, uniseriate hairs.  Leaves  1(--2) per stem, with common stalk divided into sterile, laminate, photosynthetic portion (trophophore) and fertile, spore-bearing portion (sporophore).  Trophophore blades  compound to simple, rarely absent, veins anastomosing or free, pinnate, or arranged like ribs of fan.  Indument  absent or of widely scattered, long, uniseriate hairs, especially on petioles and rachises.  Sporophores  pinnately branched or simple.  Sporangia  exposed or embedded, 0.5--1.5 mm diam., thick-walled, with thousands of spores.  Spores  all 1 kind, trilete, thick-walled, surface rugate, tuberculate, baculate (with projecting rods usually higher than wide), sometimes joined in delicate network, mostly with ± warty surface.  Gametophytes  not green, usually fleshy, round or linear, subterranean, mycorrhizal.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Adder's tongue Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Ophioglossaceae comprise two clearly defined subfamilies, Botrychioideae and Ophioglossoideae, which are sometimes recognized as distinct families. Ophioglossaceae may be only distantly related to the ferns and more closely related to Marattiales and certain seedplants, especially Cycadales, in such characteristics as stelar type, cork cambium, dilated leaf bases, conduplicate vernation, intercalary leaf growth, collateral leaf traces, circular-bordered pits, eusporangia, massive gametophytes, sunken archegonia, and presence in some species of endoscopic embryos.</discussion>
  <discussion>(Key to genera of Ophioglossaceae )</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera 5, species ca. 70--80 (3 genera, 38 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades mostly pinnately divided or lobed; veins free; margins entire to dentate to lacerate; sporangial clusters pinnately branched, sporangia sessile or terminating short stalks.</description>
      <determination>1 Botrychium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades undivided or palmately lobed; veins anastomosing; margins entire; sporangial clusters with sporangia embedded in compact linear spike.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades simple, unlobed, to 4.5 cm wide; main areoles mostly less than 6 mm wide; sporophore 1 per leaf at ground level or above ground level, or absent; plants terrestrial.</description>
      <determination>6 Ophioglossum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades palmately lobed, to 30 cm wide; main areoles large, mostly more than 30 mm; sporophores several to many per leaf at base of blade; plants epiphytic.</description>
      <determination>3 Cheiroglossa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
