<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown in Franklin" date="1823">cryptogramma</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. Brown in Franklin" date="1823">acrostichoides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Franklin,Narr. Journey Polar Sea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>754, 767. 1823</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cryptogramma;species acrostichoides</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cryptogramma</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) R. Brown ex Hooker" date="unknown">crispa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="(R. Brown) Hultén" date="unknown">acrostichoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cryptogramma;species crispa;subspecies acrostichoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cryptogramma</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">crispa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(R. Brown) C. B. Clarke" date="unknown">acrostichoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cryptogramma;species crispa;variety acrostichoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  decumbent to erect, much branched from base, stout, 10--20 mm diam. (including hardened, persistent leaf bases); scales bicolored, dense, broadly lanceolate to linear, to 6 × 2 mm.  Leaves  densely tufted, green over winter, persistent after withering; sterile leaves spreading, 3--17 cm; fertile leaves erect, 5--25 cm; hairs small, appressed, cylindric, scattered along grooves of petiole and along costae and costules of adaxial blade surface.  Petiole  green to straw-colored, dark brown on proximal 1/8 or less, 1--2 mm wide, firm and strawlike, not collapsed; scales bicolored or ± concolored, becoming sparse distally.  Blade  deltate to ovate-lanceolate, all 2--3-pinnate, somewhat leathery, opaque; hydathodes sunken below leaf surface.  Segments  of sterile leaves oblong to ovate-lanceolate, bases cuneate, distal 2/3--1/2 of segments crenate to dentate, often somewhat more deeply incised every 2d tooth; segments of fertile leaves horizontal to ascending, strongly differentiated from those of sterile leaves, linear, 3--12 × 1--2 mm; margins of fertile segments revolute, covering sporangia.  Sporangia  in sori that coalesce at maturity. 2 n  = 60.</description>
  <description type="habitat">New growth produced in spring, spores maturing in summer, sterile leaves green over winter, senescing 2d spring. Noncalcareous cliff crevices, rock outcrops, and talus, often in relatively dry habitats, typically montane but occurring in lowland to alpine habitats;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--3700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Man., N.W.T., Ont., Sask., Yukon; Alaska, Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mich., Mont., Minn., Nev., N.Mex., Oreg., Utah, Wash., Wyo.; reported from Mexico in Baja California; Asia.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">American parsley fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Cryptogramma acrostichoides has often been treated as a variety or subspecies of the strictly European Cryptogramma crispa (Linneaus) R. Brown, which has a chromosome number of 2 n = 120.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
