<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1841">pellaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Windham" date="1993">gastonyi</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>19: 36. 1993</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus pellaea;species gastonyi</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales uniformly reddish brown, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, thin, margins entire to denticulate.  Leaves  somewhat dimorphic, sterile leaves shorter than fertile leaves, clustered on stem, 8--25 cm; croziers villous.  Petiole  reddish purple to dark brown, lustrous, rounded adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  elongate-deltate to lanceolate, 2-pinnate proximally, 3--6 cm wide; rachis purple or brown throughout, straight, rounded adaxially, sparsely villous with long, divergent hairs.  Pinnae  ascending or perpendicular to rachis, not decurrent on rachis or obscurely so, usually with 3--7 ultimate segments; costae straight, 2--30 mm, usually shorter than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  oblong-lanceolate, 7--30 mm, leathery, sparsely villous abaxially near midrib; margins usually recurved on fertile segments, covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, crenulate; apex obtuse to slightly mucronate.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  long-stalked, containing 32 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Calcareous cliffs and ledges, usually on limestone;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="calcareous cliffs" />
        <character name="habitat" value="ledges" />
        <character name="habitat" value="limestone" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">100--1500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Sask.; Mo., S.Dak., Wyo.</description>
  <number>15</number>
  <discussion>Pellaea gastonyi is an apogamous tetraploid that has originated through repeated hybridization between P . atropurpurea and P . glabella . Isozyme studies (G. J. Gastony 1988) indicate that P . glabella subsp. missouriensis was the diploid parent of plants found in Missouri, whereas diploid P . glabella subsp. occidentalis was involved in the origin of P . gastonyi populations occurring in western North America. Pellaea gastonyi is most often confused with P . atropurpurea , from which it differs in having sparsely villous rachises, smaller ultimate segments, and spores averaging more than 62 µm in diameter.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
