<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">lycopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">lycopodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">annotinum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1103. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family lycopodiaceae;genus lycopodium;species annotinum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Horizontal stems  on substrate surface.  Upright shoots  clustered, mainly unbranched or sparsely branching mainly at base, 1.2--1.6 cm diam.; annual bud constrictions abrupt and conspicuous.  Lateral branchlets  few and like upright shoots but annual bud constrictions absent.  Leaves  spreading to reflexed, dark green, linear-lanceolate, (2.5--)5--8 X 0.6--1.2 mm; margins closely and shallowly dentate mainly in distal 1/2; apex sharply pointed, lacking hair tip.  Strobili  solitary, sessile on shoots, 15--30 X 3.5--4.5 mm.  Sporophylls  (1.5--)3.5 X 0.7(--2) mm, abruptly narrowed to pointed tip. 2 n  = 68.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Swampy or moist coniferous forests, mountain forests, and exposed grassy or rocky sites;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="swampy" />
        <character name="habitat" value="moist coniferous forests" />
        <character name="habitat" value="mountain forests" />
        <character name="habitat" value="and exposed grassy or rocky sites" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1850 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; St. Pierre and Miquelon; Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld., N.W.T., N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask., Yukon; Alaska, Ariz., Colo., Conn., Idaho, Ky., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Mont., N.H., N.J., N.Mex., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Oreg., Pa., R.I., Tenn., Utah, Vt., Va., Wash., Wis., Wyo.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Bristly club-moss</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">lycopode interrompu</other_name>
  <discussion>This widespread and common club-moss has been divided into various forms or varieties, some of which have been treated as species. Present evidence supports the hypothesis that these are environmentally induced forms, the most distinctive of which has been called Lycopodium annotinum var. alpestre C. Hartman, with leaves only 2.5--6 mm, very leathery, entire-margined, and appressed. Plants intermediate between this and L . annotinum var. annotinum are a form that has been called var. pungens (Bachelot de la Pylaie) Desvaux, an invalid name. Both are found in cold, bleak, northern or high elevation habitats. The species should be studied in detail to determine whether it contains any groups that should be recognized taxonomically.</discussion>
  <discussion>Lycopodium clavatum group</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
