<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown" date="1810">woodsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Windham" date="1993">cochisensis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>19: 54. 1993</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus woodsia;species cochisensis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact, erect to ascending, with a few persistent petiole bases of unequal lengths; scales often uniformly brown but at least some bicolored with dark central stripe and pale brown margins, narrowly lanceolate.  Leaves  5--25 × 1.5--6 cm.  Petiole  light brown or straw-colored throughout when mature, occasionally darker at very base, not articulate above base, relatively brittle and easily shattered.  Blade  narrowly lanceolate to ovate, pinnate-pinnatifid to 2-pinnate proximally, sparsely to moderately glandular, never viscid; glandular hairs with thin stalks and slightly expanded tips; rachis with glandular hairs and occasional hairlike scales.  Pinnae  ovate-deltate to elliptic, longer than wide, abruptly tapered to a rounded or broadly acute apex, occasionally attenuate; largest pinnae with 4--9 pairs of pinnules; abaxial and adaxial surfaces glandular, lacking nonglandular hairs or scales.  Pinnules  dentate, often shallowly lobed; margins lustrous adaxially, usually thickened, lacking cilia but sparsely glandular, with occasional 1--2-celled translucent projections. Vein tips enlarged to form whitish hydathodes visible adaxially. Indusia of relatively broad segments; segments multiseriate most of length, usually divided and uniseriate distally, composed of ± isodiametric cells, often surpassing mature sporangia.  Spores  averaging 43--49 µm. 2 n  = 152.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating late spring--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shaded ledges and alcoves near springs and seeps, usually on granitic or volcanic substrates;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1000--2200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex.; n Mexico.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Cochise cliff fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Woodsia cochisensis traditionally has been identified as W . plummerae or (rarely) W . mexicana Fée. It is readily separated from W . plummerae by the characteristics given in the key, and from North American members of the mexicana group ( W . phillipsii and W . neomexicana ) by having indusial segments that are broad and nonfilamentous at the base. Woodsia cochisensis is less glandular than typical W . mexicana from northeastern Mexico and is further distinguished from that species by the thickened, lustrous pinnule margins and well-developed hydathodes. Isozyme and chromosome studies suggest that W . cochisensis is an allotetraploid that may have originated through hybridization between W . phillipsii and an undescribed Mexican diploid (M. D. Windham 1993). It crosses with the former species to produce sterile triploids of intermediate morphology.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
