<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Donald R. Farrar</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martius" date="unknown">hymenophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Trichomanes</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1097. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5, 485, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hymenophyllaceae;genus Trichomanes</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek thrix, hair, and manes, cup, alluding to the hairlike receptacle extending from the cuplike involucre]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic or on rock.  Stems  long-creeping or short and erect, clothed in masses of dark brown hairs of 2 or more types, including multicellular gland-tipped hairs and elongate, sometimes branched and often multicellular, rhizoidlike hairs.  Roots  sparse or absent on creeping stems, numerous and wiry on erect stems.  Leaves  entire, lobed, or compound, 0.5--20 × 0.2--5 cm.  Petiole  short, wiry, often partially or wholly winged.  Blade  glabrous or with scattered, multicellular, gland-tipped hairs on veins; margins entire or minutely lobed, sometimes bearing dark stellate hairs (or orbicular scales,  Trichomanes membranaceum ).  Soral involucres  conic.  Sporangia  sessile, formed at base of exserted bristle and carried outward by intercalary growth of bristle base.  Gametophytes  persistent, entirely filamentous or with proximal filamentous net producing aerial blades with gemmiferous apices.  Gametophyte gemmae  uniseriate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, mostly tropical, a few temperate.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Bristle fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Trichomanes occurs primarily in tropical lowland and montane rainforests, a few species occurring in continuously moist, deeply sheltered habitats in temperate latitudes. Species outside the flora display a wide range of morphologies and habits. Some are terrestrial, some attain considerably larger size, and some have dimorphic fertile and sterile leaves.</discussion>
  <discussion>Filamentous gametophytes of Trichomanes can be distinguished from algae and from moss protonemata by their short cells with numerous discoid chloroplasts, by the presence of short, brown, unicellular rhizoids, and by their production of specialized gemmifer cells and gemmae.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 320 (8 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Farrar, D. R., J. C. Parks, and B. W. McAlpin. 1982. The fern genera Vittaria and Trichomanes in the northeastern United States. Rhodora 85: 83--92. Wessels</reference>
    <reference>Boer, J. G. 1962. The New World species of Trichomanes sect. Didymoglossum and Microgonium . Acta Bot. Neerl. 11: 277--330.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants entirely filamentous; on rock in temperate uplands of e U.S.</description>
      <determination>8 Trichomanes intricatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves entire to irregularly palmately lobed with veins repeatedly forking from base to weakly pinnate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 2-4 cm, bearing dark, large, branched hairs on margins between lobes.</description>
      <determination>3 Trichomanes krausii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 4-20 cm, without hairs on margins.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 1-2-pinnate-pinnatifid, widely spaced on long-creeping stems.</description>
      <determination>1 Trichomanes boschianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves pinnatifid, clustered on short erect stems.</description>
      <determination>2 Trichomanes holopterum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins fringed with paired disclike scales.</description>
      <determination>7 Trichomanes membranaceum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins fringed with dark stellate hairs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Soral involucres 1 per leaf; involucral lips not dark-edged; venation weakly pinnate.</description>
      <determination>4 Trichomanes petersii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Soral involucres 1-6 per leaf; involucral lips dark-edged; veins repeatedly forking from base.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 5-10 cm; soral involucres flaring at mouth.</description>
      <determination>5a subsp. floridanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 1-3 cm; soral involucres not flaring at mouth.</description>
      <determination>6 Trichomanes lineolatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
