<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert P. Adams</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Bartlett" date="unknown">cupressaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Juniperus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1038. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5, 461, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cupressaceae;genus Juniperus</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin juniperus, name for juniper]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees  evergreen.  Branchlets  terete, 3--6 angled, variously oriented, but not in flattened sprays.  Leaves  opposite in 4 ranks or in whorls of 3.  Adult leaves  closely appressed to divergent, scalelike to subulate, free portion to ca. 10 mm (to ca. 15 mm in  Juniperus communis ); abaxial gland visible or not, elongate to hemispheric ( J .  ashei ), sometimes exuding white crystalline deposit.  Pollen cones  with 3--7 pairs or trios of sporophylls, each sporophyll with 2--8 pollen sacs.  Seed cones  maturing in 1 or 2 years, globose to ovoid and berrylike, 3--20 mm, remaining closed, usually glaucous; scales persistent, 1--3 pairs, peltate, tightly coalesced, thick and fleshy or fibrous to obscurely woody.  Seeds  1--3 per scale, round to faceted, wingless; cotyledons 2--6.  x  = 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">primarily Northern Hemisphere, 1 in e Africa.</description>
  <number>8</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Juniper</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cedar</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">redcedar</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cedro</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sabino</other_name>
  <discussion>Juniperus is the only dioecious (sometimes monoecious) genus of Cupressaceae in the flora. Cones, generally terminal, are axillary in J . communis .</discussion>
  <discussion>Numerous cultivars of Juniperus species are widely used for landscaping. Mutants, or "sports," affecting plant habit and foliage are present in all species and are likely related to single-gene mutations. Many have been given formal names or incorrectly ascribed to hybridization. Gymnocarpy (bare seeds protruding from the cone), caused by insect larvae (T. A. Zanoni 1978), is occasionally found in most junipers, particularly in the southwestern United States. Specimens with such aberrations may be almost impossible to identify without chemical data.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 60 (13 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Adams, R. P. 1969. Chemosystematic and Numerical Studies in Natural Populations of Juniperus . Ph.D. thesis. University of Texas.</reference>
    <reference>Adams, R. P. and T. A. Zanoni. 1979. The distribution, synonymy, and taxonomy of three junipers of the southwest United States and northern Mexico. SouthW. Naturalist 24: 323--330.</reference>
    <reference>Fassett, N. C. 1945.  Juniperus virginiana ,  J .  horizontalis , and  J .  scopulorum . V. Taxonomic treatment. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 72: 480--482.</reference>
    <reference>Hall, M. T. 1952. Variation and hybridization in Juniperus . Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 39: 1--64. Van</reference>
    <reference>Vasek, F. C. 1966. The distribution and taxonomy of three western junipers. Brittonia 18: 350--372.</reference>
    <reference>Zanoni, T. A. 1978. The American junipers of the section  Sabina  ( Juniperus , Cupressaceae)---A century later. Phytologia 38: 433--454.</reference>
    <reference>Zanoni, T. A. and R. P. Adams. 1979. The genus  Juniperus  (Cupressaceae) in Mexico and Guatemala: Synonymy, key, and distributions of the taxa. Bol. Soc. Bot. México 38: 83--131.</reference>
    <reference>Adams, R. P., E. von Rudloff, and L. Hogge. 1983. Chemosystematic studies of the western North American junipers based on their volatile oils. Biochem. Syst. &amp; Ecol. 11: 85--89.</reference>
    <reference>Haverbeke, D. F. 1968. A population study of Juniperus in the Missouri River basin. Univ. Nebraska Stud., n. s. 38: 1--82.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves of 1 kind, subulate, with basal abscission zone, spreading; cones axillary (Juniperus sect. Juniperus). ..</description>
      <determination>1 Juniperus communis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves of 2 kinds, whip (subulate, without basal abscission zone) and scalelike; cones terminal (Juniperus sect. Sabina Spach).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of leaves entire (at 20×) or, if with irregular teeth (at 40×), then scalelike leaves acuminate at apex.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of leaves denticulate (at 20×), scalelike leaves usually obtuse to acute at apex (sometimes mucronate in Juniperus deppeana or acuminate in J. monosperma).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of leaves with irregular teeth (at 40×), scalelike leaves acuminate at apex; seed cones with 4-13 seeds, tan-brown to brownish purple when mature; branches as well as branchlets flaccid. .</description>
      <determination>2a var. flaccida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of leaves entire (at 20× and 40×), scalelike leaves obtuse to acute or apiculate at apex; seed cones with 1-3 seeds, blue-black to brownish blue when mature; branches not drooping, but branchlets often flaccid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Prostrate to decumbent shrubs; scalelike leaves apiculate at apex; peduncles generally curved.</description>
      <determination>3 Juniperus horizontalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Upright trees; scalelike leaves obtuse to acute at apex; peduncles generally straight.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scalelike leaves not overlapping, or, if so, by not more than 1/5 their length, apex obtuse to acute; bark of larger branchlets exfoliating in plates; seed cones maturing in 2 years, of 2 distinct sizes.</description>
      <determination>4 Juniperus scopulorum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scalelike leaves overlapping by more than 1/4 their length, apex acute (to bluntly obtuse in var. silicicola, se United States); bark of larger branchlets usually exfoliating in strips; seed cones maturing in 1 year, of 1 size.</description>
      <determination>5 Juniperus virginiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones with 3-6 seeds, fibrous to obscurely woody; bark exfoliating in rectangular plates, branchlets erect (rarely bark exfoliating in thin strips, branchlets then flaccid).</description>
      <determination>6a var. deppeana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones with 1-3 seeds, fleshy or resinous to fibrous; bark exfoliating in thin strips, branchlets erect.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves with raised hemispheric glands (particularly obvious on whip leaves).</description>
      <determination>7 Juniperus ashei</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves with ovate, elliptic, elongate, or inconspicuous glands (or glands round on scalelike leaves only).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones blue to blue-black, with 2(-3) seeds, maturing in 2 years; bark of branchlets greater than 10 mm diam. exfoliating in scales or flakes; single-stemmed trees to 20(-30) m.</description>
      <determination>8 Juniperus occidentalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones variously colored, but with brownish or reddish hue, even when some blue is present, with 1(-2) seeds, usually maturing in 1 year; bark of branchlets greater than 10 mm diam. usually exfoliating in strips or smooth; usually multistemmed shrubs or trees to 12 m.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Abaxial glands inconspicuous because embedded in leaf; monoecious.</description>
      <determination>9 Juniperus osteosperma</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Abaxial glands conspicuous; dioecious (very rarely monoecious).</description>
      <next_statement_id>10</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones mostly 9-10 mm diam., bluish brown, glaucous; branchlets about as wide as length of scalelike leaves; scalelike leaves closely appressed, abaxial surface generally flattened; branchlets terete.</description>
      <determination>10 Juniperus californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones mostly 6-8 mm diam., reddish blue to brownish blue, rose to pinkish, or copper to copper-red, glaucous or not; branchlets ca. 2/3 as wide as length of scalelike leaves; scalelike leaves with apex spreading, abaxial surface raised; branchlets generally 3-4(-6)-sided.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones reddish blue to brownish blue; fewer than 1/5 of whip-leaf glands with evident white exudate.</description>
      <determination>11 Juniperus monosperma</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones rose to pinkish or copper to copper-red; 1/4 or more of whip-leaf glands with evident white exudate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones rose to pinkish, glaucous; adaxial surface of leaves glaucous.</description>
      <determination>12 Juniperus coahuilensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed cones copper to copper-red, not glaucous; adaxial surface of leaves not glaucous.</description>
      <determination>13 Juniperus pinchotii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
