<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1806">cheilanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kunze" date="1839">kaulfussii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 145. 1839</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cheilanthes;species kaulfussii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  short-creeping, usually 4--8 mm diam.; scales uniformly black or with narrow brown margins, linear-subulate, straight to slightly contorted, strongly appressed, persistent.  Leaves  clustered, 8--35 cm; vernation circinate.  Petiole  dark brown, flattened or slightly grooved distally on adaxial surface.  Blade  elongate-pentagonal, 3-pinnate-pinnatifid to 4-pinnate at base, 3--10 cm wide; rachis grooved adaxially, lacking scales, with monomorphic pubescence.  Pinnae  not articulate, dark color of stalk continuing into pinna base, basal pair larger than adjacent pair, strongly inequilateral, proximal basiscopic pinnules greatly enlarged, appearing glandular-pubescent adaxially.  Costae  green or straw-colored adaxially for most of length; abaxial scales absent.  Ultimate segments  linear-oblong, not especially beadlike, largest 3--8 mm, abaxially and adaxially glandular pubescent with short, sticky, capitate glands.  False indusia  marginal, weakly differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  usually discontinuous, concentrated on apical and lateral lobes.  Sporangia  containing 32 spores.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rocky slopes and ledges, usually on igneous substrates;</description>
  <description type="elevation">300--2500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.; Mexico; Central America; South America.</description>
  <number>21</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Glandular lip fern</other_name>
  <discussion>The few populations of Cheilanthes kaulfussii known in the flora produce 32 spores per sporangium and reproduce apogamously (D. M. Benham 1982). Although the chromosome number of North American specimens has not been established with certainty, the specimens appear to be polyploids that may have been derived from 64-spored Mexican populations through autopolyploidy. The species is quite distinctive and should not be confused with any other member of the flora.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
