<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1806">cheilanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Link" date="1833">tomentosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hort. Berol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 42. 1833</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cheilanthes;species tomentosa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Myriopteris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Link) J. Smith" date="unknown">tomentosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Myriopteris;species tomentosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact, usually 4--8 mm diam.; scales mostly bicolored, with broad, well-defined, dark, central stripe and narrow, light brown margins, linear-lanceolate, straight to slightly contorted, loosely appressed, persistent.  Leaves  clustered, 8--45 cm; vernation noncircinate.  Petiole  usually dark brown, rounded adaxially.  Blade  oblong-lanceolate, usually 4-pinnate at base, 1.5--8 cm wide; rachis rounded abaxially, with scattered linear scales and monomorphic pubescence.  Pinnae  not articulate, dark color of stalk continuing into pinna base, basal pair not conspicuously larger than adjacent pair, usually equilateral, appearing tomentose adaxially.  Costae  green adaxially for most of length; abaxial scales multiseriate, linear, truncate at base, inconspicuous, the largest 0.1--0.4 mm wide, loosely imbricate, not concealing ultimate segments, usually entire, not ciliate.  Ultimate segments  oval or rarely oblong, beadlike, the largest 1--2 mm, abaxially densely tomentose, adaxially pubescent with fine, unbranched hairs.  False indusia  marginal to obscurely inframarginal, somewhat differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  ± continuous around segment margins.  Sporangia  containing 32 spores.  n  = 2 n  = 90, apogamous.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rocky slopes and ledges, on a variety of substrates including limestone and granite;</description>
  <description type="elevation">200--2400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Ariz., Ark., Ga., Kans., Mo., N.Mex., N.C., Okla., Pa., S.C., Tenn., Tex., Va., W.Va.; Mexico.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Woolly lip fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Cheilanthes tomentosa is an apogamous triploid of unknown parentage. It is closely related to C . eatonii , but it is distinguished by having narrower, less prominent costal scales. Natural hybrids between these two species have been reported (D. S. Correll 1956), but such hybrids are unlikely because both species are apogamous in the supposed region of hybridization.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
