<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Reichenbach" date="unknown">isoëtaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">isoëtes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Gay &amp; Durieu" date="unknown">melanopoda</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Bot. France</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 102. 1864</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family isoëtaceae;genus isoëtes;species melanopoda</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants terrestrial or becoming so. Rootstock nearly globose, 2-lobed. Leaves deciduous, bright green, pale to lustrous black toward base, spirally arranged, to 40 cm, pliant, tapering gradually to tip. Velum covering less than 3/4 sporangium. Sporangium wall brown-streaked. Megaspores white, 280--440 μm diam., obscurely rugulate with low ridges, rarely tuberculate or reticulate; girdle obscure. Microspores gray in mass, 20--30 μm, spinulose. 2n = 22.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Spores mature in late spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Noncalcareous soil, meadows, fields, ditches, soil pockets on rock outcrops;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ark., Ga., Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., La., Minn., Miss., Mo., Nebr., N.J., N.C., Okla., S.C., S. Dak., Tenn., Tex., Utah, Va.</description>
  <other_name type="common_name">Black-footed quillwort</other_name>
  <discussion>Population of Isoëtes melanopoda in New Jersey, North Carolina, South Carolina, Utah, and Virginia are disjunct.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of Isoëtes melanopoda with black leaf bases are typical. Plants without black leaf bases have been called I. melanopoda f. pallida (Engelmann) Fernald. Variation also occurs in megaspore morphology. A collection from Dallas County, Texas, has lustrous black leaf bases and boldly rugulate spores with ridges that occasionally anastomose. In many respects, I. melanopoda is similar to I. howellii.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
