<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Newman" date="unknown">aspleniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">asplenium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">trichomanes</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1080. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family aspleniaceae;genus asplenium;species trichomanes</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots  not proliferous.  Stems  short-creeping, often branched; scales black throughout or with brown borders, lanceolate, 2--5 × 0.2--0.5 mm, margins entire to denticulate.  Leaves  monomorphic.  Petiole  reddish brown or blackish brown throughout, lustrous, 1--4(--7) cm, 1/6--1/4 length of blade; indument absent or of black, linear-lanceolate or filiform scales at base.  Blade  linear, 1-pinnate, 3--22 × 0.5--1.5 cm, thin, glabrous or sparsely pubescent; base gradually tapered; apex narrowly acute, not rooting.  Rachis  reddish brown throughout, lustrous, glabrous or nearly so.  Pinnae  in 15--35 pairs, oblong to oval; medial pinnae 2.5--8 × 2.5--4 mm; base broadly cuneate, with or without low, rounded acroscopic auricle; margins shallowly crenate to serrate or ± entire; apex obtuse.  Veins  free, evident.  Sori  2--4 pairs per pinna, on both basiscopic and acroscopic sides.  Spores  64 per sporangium. 2 n  = 72, 144.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide.</description>
  <number>19</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Maidenhair spleenwort</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">doradille chevelue</other_name>
  <discussion>In North America, as in Europe, Asplenium trichomanes consists of diploid and tetraploid cytotypes, treated here as subspecies. Asplenium trichomanes subsp. trichomanes , the diploid, is found on noncalcareous rocks. In the southwestern United States it occurs at high elevations. Asplenium trichomanes subsp. quadrivalens , the tetraploid, grows on calcareous substrates and has a more northern distribution (R. C. Moran 1982). Triploid hybrids are known between the diploids and tetraploids (R. C. Moran 1982; W. H. Wagner Jr. and F. S. Wagner 1966).</discussion>
  <discussion>Subspecies 4 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spores 27-32 µm; on acidic substrates.</description>
      <determination>19a subsp. trichomanes</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spores 37-43 µm; on limestone. .</description>
      <determination>19b subsp. quadrivalens</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
