<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Jermy" date="1986">tetragonostachys</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Maxon" date="1920">standleyi</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Misc. Collect.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>72: 9. 1920</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus tetragonostachys;species standleyi</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">densa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Maxon) R. M. Tryon" date="unknown">standleyi</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Selaginella;species densa;variety standleyi;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial or on rock, forming cushionlike or rather short, loose mats.  Stems  decumbent to short-creeping, not readily fragmenting, irregularly forked, without budlike arrested branches, tips straight; main stem upperside and underside structurally slightly different, inconspicuously indeterminate, lateral branches radially symmetric, determinate, strongly ascending, 1-forked.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems throughout stem length, 0.2--0.35 mm diam.  Leaves  monomorphic, in poorly defined pseudowhorls of 5 or 6, tightly appressed, ascending, green, linear, linear-oblong or linear-lanceolate, (2.5--)3--4.5 mm (smaller on upperside leaves and in ascending buds); abaxial ridges present; base decurrent, oblique, glabrous or rarely pubescent; margins short-ciliate to denticulate, cilia transparent, scattered, spreading to ascending, 0.05--0.07(--0.1) mm; apex keeled, obtuse, rather abruptly bristled; bristle usually yellowish or transparent to opaque, slightly puberulent or smooth, (0.4--)0.7--1.25 mm.  Strobili  solitary, 0.5--1(--2.3) cm; sporophylls deltate-ovate, rarely ovate-lanceolate, abaxial ridges well defined, base glabrous, margins short-ciliate to denticulate on distal 3/4, apex keeled, strongly truncate in profile, abruptly bristled.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rock crevices, granitic outcrops, gravelly soil, bare soil, or alpine meadows;</description>
  <description type="elevation">2000--3700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C.; Alaska, Colo., Mont., Wyo.</description>
  <number>28</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Standley's spike-moss</other_name>
  <discussion>R. M. Tryon (1955) reported an elevation range of 1500--4660 m for Selaginella standleyi . I have not seen specimens from these lower and higher elevations.</discussion>
  <discussion>Selaginella standleyi is a member of the S . densa complex. It has sometimes been confused with S . watsonii and S . sibirica ; it is, however, rather easy to distinguish by leaf and strobilus characters.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
