<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>William H. Parker</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">Larix</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict. Abr., ed. 4</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>vol. 2. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus Larix</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin larix, name for larch]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  deciduous; crown sparse, open.  Bark  silver-gray to gray-brown on young trees, becoming reddish brown to brown, smooth initially, scaly to thickened and furrowed with age.  Branches  whorled; short (spur) shoots prominent on twigs 2 years or more old, each bearing leaves (needles), and often pollen cone, or seed cone; lateral long shoots (sylleptic branches) sometimes produced by current-year growth increments; leaf scars many.  Buds  rounded.  Leaves  in tufts of 10--60 on short (spur) shoots or borne singly on 1st-year long shoots, deciduous, ± flattened, with abaxial keel, sessile, base decurrent, sheath absent, apex pointed or rounded; resin canals 2.  Pollen cones  solitary, ovoid-cylindric, yellowish.  Seed cones  maturing in 1 season, persisting several years, erect, globose to ovoid, usually terminal on short shoots and thus appearing stalked, sometimes sessile on 1-year-old long shoots; scales persistent, circular to oblong-obovate, thin, lacking apophysis and umbo; bracts included or exserted.  Seeds  winged; cotyledons 4--6.  x =12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">boreal and cold north temperate areas, North America, Eurasia.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Larch</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">mélèze</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">mélèze laricin</other_name>
  <discussion>Species of Larix are present in most boreal regions; they often form only a minor component of the vegetation. Some are important for their hard, heavy, and decay-resistant wood. Only a few have received any horticultural attention; some cultivars exist for the most commonly cultivated Old World larches, L . decidua Miller and L . kaempferi (Lambert) Carrière, but almost none for the North American species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 10 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Arno, S.F. and J.R. Habeck. 1972. Ecology of alpine larch ( Larix lyallii  Parl.) in the Pacific Northwest. Ecol. Monogr. 42: 417--450.</reference>
    <reference>Bakowsky, O.A. 1989. Phenotypic Variation in  Larix lyallii  and Relationships in the Larch Genus. M.Sc.F. thesis. Lakehead University.</reference>
    <reference>Carlson,C. 1965. Interspecific Hybridization of  Larix occidentalis  and  Larix lyallii . M.Sc.F. thesis. University of Montana.</reference>
    <reference>Dickinson, T.A., W.H. Parker, and R.E. Strauss. 1987. Another approach to leaf shape comparisons. Taxon 36: 1--20.</reference>
    <reference>Knudsen, G.M. 1968. Chemotaxonomic Investigation of Hybridization between  Larix occidentalis  and  Larix lyallii . M.Sc.F. thesis. University of Montana.</reference>
    <reference>Owens, J.N. and S.Simpson. 1986. Pollen from conifers native to British Columbia. Canad. J. Forest Res. 16: 955--967.</reference>
    <reference>Parker, W.H. and T.A. Dickinson. 1990. Range-wide morphological and anatomical variation in  Larix laricina . Canad. J. Bot. 68: 832--840.</reference>
    <reference>Powell, G. R. 1987. Syllepsis in  Larix laricina : Analysis of tree leaders with and without sylleptic long shoots. Canad. J. Forest Res. 17: 490--498.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Twigs glabrous; seed cones 1-2 cm, scales 10-30, surpassing bracts at maturity; short-shoot leaves 1-2 cm, thickness 0.3-0.5 mm; pollen 53-65 um diam.</description>
      <determination>1 Larix laricina</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Twigs initially pubescent, becoming glabrous, or strongly tomentose for 2-3 years; seed cones 2-5 cm, scales 45-55, shorter than awn-tipped bracts at maturity; short-shoot leaves 2-5 cm, thickness 0.4-0.6 mm; pollen 71-93 um diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Twigs initially pubescent (but not tomentose), becoming glabrous or very sparsely pubescent during first year; seed cones 2-3 cm, scale margins entire, cone stalk 3.5-5 mm diam.; width-to-thickness ratio of short-shoot leaves 1.3-1.7, adaxial surface with shallow convex midrib; resin canals 20-50 um from margins, each surrounded by 5-7 epithelial cells.</description>
      <determination>2 Larix occidentalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Twigs strongly tomentose; seed cones 2.5-4(-5) cm, scale margins erose, cone stalk 2.5-4 mm diam.; width-to-thickness ratio of short-shoot leaves 1.2-1.4, adaxial surface 2-angled; resin canals 40-80 um from margins, each surrounded by 6-10 epithelial cells.</description>
      <determination>3 Larix lyallii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
