<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1806">cheilanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="D. C. Eaton in Emory" date="1859">gracillima</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Emory,Rep. U.S. Mex. Bound.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 234. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cheilanthes;species gracillima</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Myriopteris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(D. C. Eaton) J. Smith" date="unknown">gracillima</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Myriopteris;species gracillima;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  short-creeping, 4--8 mm diam.; scales uniformly brown or with poorly defined, dark, central stripe, linear-lanceolate, straight to slightly contorted, loosely appressed, persistent.  Leaves  clustered, 5--25 cm; vernation noncircinate.  Petiole  dark brown, rounded adaxially.  Blade  linear-oblong, 2--3-pinnate at base, 1--2.5 cm wide; rachis rounded adaxially, with scattered linear scales, not pubescent.  Pinnae  not articulate, dark color of stalk continuing into pinna base, basal pair not conspicuously larger than adjacent pair, usually equilateral, appearing sparsely pubescent or glabrous adaxially.  Costae  green adaxially for most of length; abaxial scales multiseriate, linear, truncate at base, inconspicuous, the largest 0.1--0.4 mm wide, loosely imbricate, not concealing ultimate segments, long-ciliate, cilia usually confined to base.  Ultimate segments  oblong or rarely oval, beadlike, the largest 1.5--3 mm, abaxially densely covered with branched hairs and small, ciliate scales, adaxially with scattered, branched hairs or glabrescent.  False indusia  marginal, slightly differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  ± continuous around segment margins.  Sporangia  containing 64 spores.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cliffs and rocky slopes, usually on igneous substrates;</description>
  <description type="elevation">800--3000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C.; Calif., Idaho, Mont., Nev., Oreg., Utah, Wash.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Lace fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Cheilanthes gracillima is a well-marked species, but it apparently hybridizes with C . intertexta (see reticulogram) to produce plants of intermediate morphology with malformed spores that have been called C . gracillima var. aberrans M. E. Jones (A. R. Smith 1974).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
