<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">adiantum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Swartz" date="1788">tenerum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>135. 1788</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus adiantum;species tenerum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  short-creeping; scales bicolored, centers dark reddish brown, margins pale tan, erose-ciliate. Leaves arching or sometimes pendent, closely spaced, 20--110 cm.  Petiole  1--3 mm diam., glabrous, occasionally glaucous. Blade trowel-shaped, pinnate, 12--60 × 12--60 cm, gradually reduced distally, glabrous; proximal pinnae 3-pinnate; rachis straight, glabrous, not glaucous.  Segment  stalks 1--5 mm, with dark color ending abruptly at segment base, terminating in cupulelike swelling at base of segment   (unlike any other species of  Adiantum  in the flora).  Ultimate segments  fan-shaped or rhombic, about as long as broad; base cuneate; apex rounded or acute, lobed, lobes separated by narrow incisions 0.5 mm wide.  Indusia  transversely oblong to crescent-shaped, 0.5--2 mm, glabrous.  Spores  mostly 40--58 µm diam. 2 n  = 60.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating throughout the year.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Restricted to moist, shaded, limestone ledges, sink walls, and grottoes in the flora;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--50 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.; e,s Mexico; Central America in Guatemala, Honduras, Nicaragua, Costa Rica; South America in Venezuela.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Brittle maidenhair</other_name>
  <discussion>Adiantum tenerum is readily distinguished from other species in the flora by the ultimate segments conspicuously articulate to the stalks.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
