<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1841">pellaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker" date="1858">bridgesii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Fil.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 238, plate 142b. 1858</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus pellaea;species bridgesii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales mostly weakly bicolored, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, centers dark brown, thin, margins lighter, thin, denticulate to entire.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered on stem, 7--30 cm; croziers nearly glabrous.  Petiole  dark brown, lustrous, rounded adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  linear, 1-pinnate, 1.5--4 cm wide; rachis brown throughout, straight, rounded adaxially, glabrous.  Pinnae  perpendicular to slightly ascending, usually not decurrent on rachis, simple and unlobed; costae absent.  Ultimate segments  broadly ovate to elliptic, 7--20 mm, leathery, glabrous; margins plane, not recurved, not covering abaxial surface, borders whitish, entire; apex obtuse to rounded.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  sessile or subsessile, containing 64 spores, intermixed with abundant farina-producing glands. 2 n  = 58.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rocky slopes and cliffs, on granitic substrates;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1200--3600 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif., Idaho, Nev., Oreg.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <discussion>The morphology of Pellaea bridgesii is so distinctive that its sectional (and even generic) placement in Pellaea has long been a source of contention. W. H. Wagner Jr. et al. (1983) documented the existence of sterile diploid hybrids (called P . × glaciogena ) between P . bridgesii and P . mucronata (see reticulogram), suggesting that P . bridgesii is most closely related to members of sect. Pellaea . In addition to the more obvious characters mentioned above, P . bridgesii is distinguished from other North American species (except P . ternifolia ) by its anastomosing veins.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
