<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>George Yatskievych</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="C. Presl" date="1836">Phanerophlebia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Tent. Pterid.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>84. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Phanerophlebia</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek phaneros, free, and phlebium, vein, for the nonanastomosing venation found in the type species, P. nobilis ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial, less commonly on rock.  Stems  short-creeping to erect, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, evergreen.  Petiole  shorter than or ± equaling length of blade, base not swollen; vascular bundles more than 3, arranged in an arc, ± round in cross section.  Blade  ovate-lanceolate, 1-pinnate, with a ± similar apical pinna, papery.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins serrulate to spinulose; proximal pinnae largest or nearly so, short-petiolulate, ± equilateral or inequilateral with acroscopic lobe; costae adaxially grooved, grooves continuous from rachis to costae; indument of filiform scales on costae and veins abaxially, ± glabrous adaxially.  Veins  free [anastomosing], forked.  Sori  in 2 or more rows between midrib and margin, round; indusia persistent or caducous [absent].  Spores  brown, with inflated folds or wings. x = 41.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, Central America, n South America, West Indies in Hispaniola.</description>
  <number>14</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Mexican holly fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Phanerophlebia has sometimes been included in Cyrtomium , which it resembles superficially. As with that genus, Phanerophlebia might better be considered a subgenus of Polystichum , from which it is poorly differentiated morphologically. Elsewhere, some species have bicolored stem scales, netted venation, and/or lack indusia.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 8 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Maxon, W. R. 1912. Notes on the North American species of  Phanerophlebia . Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 39: 23--28.</reference>
    <reference>Underwood, L. M. 1899. North American ferns---II. The genus  Phanerophlebia . Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 26: 205--216.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae, at least some on each plant, with basal, acroscopic lobe; indusia flat to concave centrally, not umbonate, shriveled at maturity.</description>
      <determination>1 Phanerophlebia auriculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae lacking basal, acroscopic lobe; indusia with raised, central umbo, not shriveled at maturity.</description>
      <determination>2 Phanerophlebia umbonata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
