<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas" date="1827">lambertiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London, Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 500. 1827</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species lambertiana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 75m; trunk to 3.3m diam., massive, straight; crown narrowly conic, becoming rounded.  Bark  cinnamon- to gray-brown, deeply furrowed, plates long, scaly.  Branches  spreading, distal branches ascending; twigs gray-green to red-tan, aging gray, mostly puberulent.  Buds  cylindro-ovoid, red-brown, to 0.8cm, resinous.  Leaves  5 per fascicle, spreading to ascending, persisting 2--4 years, 5--10cm × (0.9--)1--1.5(--2)mm, straight, slightly twisted, pliant, blue-green, abaxial surface with only a few lines evident, adaxial surfaces with evident white stomatal lines, margins finely serrulate, apex acuminate; sheath (1--)1.5--2cm, shed early.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid-cylindric, to 15mm, yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds and falling soon thereafter, often clustered, pendent, symmetric, cylindric before opening, lance-cylindric to ellipsoid-cylindric when open, 25--50cm, yellow-brown, stalks 6--15cm; apophyses somewhat thickened; umbo terminal, depressed, resinous, slightly excurved.  Seeds  obovoid, oblique apically; body 1--2cm, deep brown; wing broad, 2--3cm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Montane dry to moist forests;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="montane dry to moist forests" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">330--3200m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif., Nev., Oreg.; Mexico in n Baja California.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sugar pine</other_name>
  <discussion>The largest species of the genus, Pinus lambertiana also has the longest seed cone in the genus. It is an important timber tree with harvest far exceeding regrowth. It is easily distinguished from P . monticola and P . strobus by its larger cones and thicker cone scales with larger seeds; it is somewhat less reliably distinguished by its leaves, which are slightly wider and more tapering-tipped and have some stomatal lines evident on the abaxial surfaces (the lines not evident in P . monticola and P . strobus ). A "sugary" resin high in cyclitols exudes from the sweet-scented fresh-cut wood.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
