<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Michael D. Windham</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1841">Pellaea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fil. Spec.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>59. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus Pellaea</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pellos, dark, possibly referring to bluish gray leaves]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  usually on rock.  Stems  compact to long-creeping, ascending to horizontal, usually branched; scales brown to tan or often bicolored with dark, central stripe and lighter margins, linear-subulate to lanceolate (rarely ovate), margins dentate, erose, or entire.  Leaves  monomorphic to somewhat dimorphic, clustered to widely scattered, 2--100 cm.  Petiole  brown, black, straw-colored, or gray, rounded, flattened or with single longitudinal groove adaxially, glabrous or pubescent, usually with a few scales at base, with single vascular bundle.  Blade  linear to ovate-deltate, 1--4-pinnate proximally, leathery or rarely somewhat herbaceous, abaxially glabrous, pubescent, or with hairlike scales scattered along costae, adaxially usually glabrous, dull, not striate; rachis straight or flexuous.  Ultimate segments  of blade usually stalked and free from costae, elliptic, lanceolate to linear, usually more than 4 mm wide; base rounded, truncate, or cordate; stalks often lustrous and dark colored; segment margins reflexed to form confluent, poorly defined, false indusia extending entire length of segment.  Veins  of ultimate segments free or rarely anastomosing, usually obscure, pinnately branched and divergent distally.  False indusia  greenish to whitish, narrow, clearly marginal, often concealing the sporangia.  Sporangia  scattered along veins near segment margins, containing 32 or 64 spores, often intermixed with glands, farina-producing.  Spores  brown to tan (rarely yellow), tetrahedral-globose, rugose or cristate, lacking prominent equatorial ridge.  x  = 29.</description>
  <description type="distribution">most in the Western Hemisphere, a small number in Asia, Africa, the Pacific Islands, and Australia.</description>
  <number>13</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Cliff-brake</other_name>
  <discussion>Pellaea in the broad sense is a diverse, poorly defined assemblage of xeric-adapted ferns (A. R. Smith 1981). Relationships among the North American, neotropical, and Eastern Hemisphere species are unclear, and it seems likely that the genus, as broadly construed by E. B. Copeland (1947) and R. M. Tryon and A. F. Tryon (1982), is polyphyletic. The species included here in Pellaea belong to a closely knit alliance that is usually recognized as a distinct section (sect. Pellaea ). Although the inclusion of P . bridgesii in this group has been questioned (A. F. Tryon 1957), W. H. Wagner Jr. et al. (1983) have shown that the aberrant morphology of this species is simply an extreme expression of evolutionary trends commonly encountered in sect. Pellaea .</discussion>
  <discussion>Among Western Hemisphere cheilanthoid ferns, species of Pellaea show clear morphologic, chromosomal, and biochemical affinities to Argyrochosma and members of the Cheilanthes alabamensis complex. In fact, the glabrous species of Argyrochosma ( A . jonesii and A . microphylla ) are commonly misidentified as Pellaea . These species are easily recognizable, however, because they have a combination of concolored stem scales and small ultimate segments (less than 4 mm wide).</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 40 (15 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Gastony, G. J. 1988. The  Pellaea glabella  complex: Electrophoretic evidence for the derivations of the agamosporous taxa and a revised taxonomy. Amer. Fern J. 78: 44--67.</reference>
    <reference>Tryon, A. F. 1957. A revision of the fern genus  Pellaea  section  Pellaea . Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 44: 125--193.</reference>
    <reference>Tryon, A. F. 1968. Comparisons of sexual and apogamous races in the fern genus  Pellaea . Rhodora 70: 1--24.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles and rachises straw-colored, tan, or gray, rarely lustrous; stem scales narrowly lanceolate to ovate, largest more than 0.3 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles and rachises dark brown to black, usually lustrous; stem scales linear-subulate, less than 0.3 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachises and costae strongly flexuous; pinnae retrorse, projecting downward toward base of leaf.</description>
      <determination>1 Pellaea ovata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachises and costae straight or slightly flexuous; pinnae perpendicular to rachis or ascending.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems stout and compact, more than 5 mm diam.; stem scales uniformly orange-brown and thin; ultimate segments rotund-cordate to deltate-cordate.</description>
      <determination>2 Pellaea cordifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems slender and long-creeping, less than 5 mm diam.; stem scales mostly bicolored, with black, thick center and brown, thin margins; ultimate segments elliptic to ovate-deltate, not deeply cordate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments leathery, veins obscure abaxially; croziers only slightly scaly; blades usually 2-pinnate at base.</description>
      <determination>3 Pellaea intermedia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments somewhat herbaceous, veins visible abaxially; croziers densely scaly; blades usually 3-pinnate at base.</description>
      <determination>4 Pellaea andromedifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Some stem scales bicolored, with dark central region and lighter, brown margin.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem scales uniformly reddish brown or tan.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades linear, 1-pinnate throughout, pinnae entire; fertile ultimate segments with rounded apices; segment margins not recurved, not concealing sporangia.</description>
      <determination>5 Pellaea bridgesii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades linear-oblong to deltate, pinnate-pinnatifid to 3-pinnate, at least some pinnae lobed or divided; fertile ultimate segments with mucronate apices; segment margins recurved, usually concealing sporangia.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades deeply pinnate-pinnatifid at base, basal pinnae ternately lobed; petioles dark purple or black; sporangia not intermixed with farina-producing glands.</description>
      <determination>6 Pellaea ternifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 2–3-pinnate at base, basal pinnae fully pinnate (occasionally appearing ternate but with terminal segment on short, dark stalk); petioles chestnut brown to dark reddish brown; sporangia intermixed with glands producing yellowish farina (sparse in Pellaea wrightiana).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinna costae usually shorter than or equal to ultimate segments; largest pinnae divided into 3–11 segments; blades linear-oblong, usually less than 4.5 cm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinna costae much longer than ultimate segments; largest pinnae divided into 11 or more segments; blades ovate-deltate to lanceolate, usually more than 4.5 cm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments linear, with greenish, strongly recurved margins covering more than 1/2 abaxial surface; sporangia with short stalks; pinnae strongly ascending.</description>
      <determination>7 Pellaea brachyptera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments narrowly oblong, with white-bordered, recurved margins usually covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface; sporangia with long stalks; pinnae perpendicular to rachis or slightly ascending.</description>
      <determination>8 Pellaea wrightiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades usually 2-pinnate proximally, pinnae perpendicular to rachis or slightly ascending; margins of ultimate segments with whitish borders; sporangia with long stalks.</description>
      <determination>9 Pellaea truncata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades 3-pinnate proximally or, if 2-pinnate, pinnae strongly ascending; margins of ultimate segments with greenish borders; sporangia with short stalks.</description>
      <determination>10 Pellaea mucronata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments glabrous abaxially or with isolated hairlike scales on a few segments or, if sparsely villous, then rachises nearly glabrous; pinnae or costae slightly decurrent on rachis; blades linear-oblong to lanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments sparsely villous on abaxial costae; rachises variously pubescent; pinnae or costae not decurrent on rachis (obscurely so in Pellaea gastonyi); blades lanceolate, ovate, or deltate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal pinnae usually bilobed and mitten-shaped; petioles with prominent articulation lines near base; rachises of mature leaves green in distal portion of blade; sporangia sessile or subsessile.</description>
      <determination>11 Pellaea breweri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal pinnae deeply divided into 3–7 lobes or segments (occasionally simple); petioles lacking articulation lines or, if present, then rachises of mature leaves brown to terminal pinna; some sporangia long-stalked.</description>
      <determination>12 Pellaea glabella</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial surface of rachis densely covered with short, curly, appressed hairs; largest ultimate segments (excluding terminal pinnae) usually more than 30 mm.</description>
      <determination>13 Pellaea atropurpurea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial surface of rachis with sparse, long, divergent hairs; largest ultimate segments (excluding terminal pinnae) usually less than 30 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal pinnae divided into 7–15 ultimate segments, segments shorter than longest pinna costae; fertile leaves usually more than 6 cm wide.</description>
      <determination>14 Pellaea lyngholmii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal pinnae divided into 3–7 ultimate segments, some segments longer than longest pinna costae; fertile leaves usually less than 6 cm wide.</description>
      <determination>15 Pellaea gastonyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
