<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="E. James" date="1823">flexilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Account Exped. Pittsburgh</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 27, 35. 1823</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species flexilis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Apinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(E.James) Rydberg" date="unknown">flexilis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Apinus;species flexilis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 26m; trunk to 2m diam., straight to contorted; crown conic, becoming rounded.  Bark  gray, nearly smooth, cross-checked in age into scaly plates and ridges.  Branches  spreading to ascending, often persistent to trunk base; twigs pale red-brown, puberulous (rarely glabrous), slightly resinous, aging gray, smooth.  Buds  ovoid, light red-brown, 0.9--1cm, resinous; lower scales ciliolate along margins.  Leaves  5 per fascicle, spreading to upcurved and ascending, persisting 5--6 years, 3--7cm × 1--1.5mm, pliant, dark green, abaxial surface with less conspicuous stomatal bands than adaxial surfaces, adaxial surfaces with strong, pale stomatal bands, margins finely serrulate, apex conic-acute to acuminate; sheath 1--1.5(--2)cm, shed early.  Pollen cones  broadly ellipsoid-cylindric, ca. 15mm, pale red or yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds and falling soon thereafter, spreading, symmetric, lance-ovoid before opening, cylindro-ovoid when open, 7--15cm, straw-colored, resinous, sessile to short-stalked, apophyses much thickened, strongly cross-keeled, umbo terminal, depressed.  Seeds  irregularly obovoid; body 10--15mm, brown, sometimes mottled darker, wingless or nearly so. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>High montane forests, often at timberline;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="high montane forests , at timberline ;" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">(1000--)1500--3600m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C.; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., Nebr., Nev., N.Mex., N.Dak., Oreg., S.Dak., Utah, Wyo.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Limber pine</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">pin blanc de l'ouest</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus flexilis , much branched with a strongly tapering trunk, is little utilized because of its form and relative inaccessibility. It reportedly forms intermediates with P . strobiformis where the two overlap. The fresh-cut wood has the odor of turpentine.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
