<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Clifton E. Nauman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(R. Brown) J. Smith" date="1841">Phlebodium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Hooker)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 58. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus Phlebodium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek phlebos, vein, referring to the prominent venation]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">Phlebodium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. J. Bennett et al., Pl. Jav. Rar.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 4. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polypodium;section Phlebodium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic.  Stems  creeping, branched, not whitish pruinose, 8--30 mm diam.; scales concolored, lanceolate, not clathrate, glabrous, margins dentate.  Leaves  monomorphic, widely spaced, not conspicuously narrowed at tip, to 130 cm.  Petiole  articulate to stem, dark brown, round in cross section, with 2 adaxial grooves.  Blade  ovate to elliptic, not pectinate, pinnatisect with broadly winged rachises and rounded sinuses, with fewer than 20 pairs of segments, glaucous, usually glabrous, scales absent; rachis glabrous.  Segments  linear to lanceolate, margins entire, apex rounded.  Veins  free near margins, well developed near costae, highly reticulate, usually with 1 row of costal areoles extending from vein to vein without included veinlets, and with a series of elongate, polygonal areoles with 1--3 excurrent included veinlets meeting at apices, and similar areoles closer to margin of segment mostly without included veinlets.  Sori  on veins, transverse, 2 in each major areole on included veinlets, circular to oblong; indument absent.  Spores  tuberculate.  x  = 37.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical regions, North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Golden polypodies</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2--4 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Duncan, W. H. 1954.  Polypodium aureum  in Florida and Georgia. Amer. Fern J. 44: 155--158.</reference>
    <reference>Lellinger, D. B. 1987. Nomenclatural notes on some ferns of Costa Rica, Panama, and Colombia. III. Amer. Fern J. 77: 101--102.</reference>
    <reference>Proctor, G. R. 1985. Ferns of Jamaica. London.</reference>
    <reference>Snyder, L. H. Jr. and J. G. Bruce. 1986. Field Guide to the Ferns and Other Pteridophytes of Georgia. Athens, Ga.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
