<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>George Yatskievych</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="C. Presl" date="1836">Cyrtomium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Tent. Pterid.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>86. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Cyrtomium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek cyrtoma, arch, for the arched veins]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants terrestrial or on rock. Stems erect or ascending, stolons absent. Leaves monomorphic, evergreen. Petiole ± 1/2--3/4 length of blade, base not swollen; vascular bundles more than 3, arranged in arc, ± round in cross section. Blade oblong-lanceolate, 1-pinnate with pinnae not lobed, distal pinnae only slightly smaller, blade ending in basally lobed pinna ± similar to lateral pinnae, papery or somewhat leathery. Pinnae not articulate to rachis, segment margins crenate to spinulose, sometimes also coarsely dentate; proximal pinnae not reduced, petiolulate, equilateral or somewhat inequilateral with acroscopic base more developed; costae adaxially grooved, grooves continuous from rachis to costae; indument of filiform scales abaxially, absent adaxially. Veins elaborately anastomosing, areoles formed with 1--3 included veinlets. Sori in 2 or more rows between midrib and margin, round. Indusia peltate, persistent or caducous. Spores brown, with inflated folds or wings. x = 41.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Asia, Africa including Madagascar, Pacific Islands in Hawaii.</description>
  <number>13</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Asiatic holly fern</other_name>
  <discussion>This difficult genus requires further systematic study. Estimates of species numbers have ranged from 9 (C. Christensen 1930) to 59 (Shing K. H. 1965). The group might better be considered a subgenus of Polystichum , from which it is poorly differentiated morphologically.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 15 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Christensen, C. 1930. The genus  Cyrtomium . Amer. Fern J. 20: 41--52.</reference>
    <reference>Ching, R. C. 1936. On the genus  Cyrtomium  Presl. Bull. Chin. Bot. Soc. 2: 85--106.</reference>
    <reference>Shing, K. H. 1965. A taxonomical study of the genus  Cyrtomium  Presl. Acta Phytotax. Sin., Addit. 1: 1--48.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae 4-10(-12) pairs, leathery, shiny adaxially, margins sometimes undulate or coarsely dentate, but not minutely crenulate or denticulate.</description>
      <determination>1 Cyrtomium falcatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae (8-)10-25 pairs, papery, not shiny adaxially, margins minutely crenulate-denticulate.</description>
      <determination>2a var. fortunei</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
