<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Elisabeth G. Andrews , Michael D. Windham</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Humboldt &amp; Bonpland ex Willdenow" date="1810">Pleopeltis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5(1): 211. 1810</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus Pleopeltis</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pleos, many, and pelte, shield, in reference to the peltate scales covering immature sori]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic, on rock, or rarely terrestrial.  Stems  often long-creeping, usually branched, 1--2.5 mm diam., not whitish pruinose; scales bicolored with dark central region, round to ovate-lanceolate or subulate, clathrate toward center, glabrous or pubescent with reddish brown hairs, margins transparent, erose-denticulate to fringed-ciliate.  Leaves  monomorphic, widely spaced, not conspicuously narrowed at tip, to 25 cm.  Petiole  green to dark brown or black, flattened to terete, often grooved proximally and winged distally.  Blade  oblong-linear to deltate, simple and entire or deeply pinnatifid, not pectinate, with fewer than 25 pairs of segments, not glaucous, with conspicuous peltate scales on abaxial surface; rachis sparsely to densely scaly abaxially, glabrous to sparsely scaly adaxially; scales ovate-lanceolate to spheric, peltate, clathrate toward center.  Segments  (when present) linear to oblong; margins entire to crenulate; apex rounded.  Venation  mostly free or complexly anastomosing, with 1--several included veinlets in fertile areoles.  Sori  often confined to distal 1/2 of leaf, discrete or confluent, circular to oval when immature, borne at ends of single veins or at junction of several veinlets, in 1 row on either side of midrib; indument of ephemeral, peltate scales covering immature sori.  Spores  smooth with scattered spheric deposits or slightly papillate or verrucose.  x  = 34, 35, 37.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical regions, North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Africa, Asia in India.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Shielded-sorus ferns</other_name>
  <discussion>Pleopeltis is a neotropical genus of mostly epiphytic ferns. Its center of diversity is in southern Mexico and Central America. The genus is currently under revision, and preliminary data indicate that certain scaly-leaved species traditionally placed in the genus Polypodium are actually more closely related to Pleopeltis than they are to Polypodium . The two North American species of this scaly Polypodium group recently have been transferred to Pleopeltis (M. D. Windham 1993) and are similarly treated here.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Wendt, T. 1980. Notes on some  Pleopeltis  and  Polypodium  species of the Chihuahuan Desert Region. Amer. Fern J. 70: 5--11.</reference>
    <reference>Windham, M. D. 1993. New taxa and nomenclatural changes in the North American fern flora. Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 19: 31--61. 1993.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades simple.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades deeply pinnatifid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales on abaxial blade surface scattered, less than 0.5 mm wide, mostly roundish and deeply fringed (appearing stellate); petioles conspicuously flattened in cross section; sori oval to oblong, often confluent; stem scales mostly round, with numerous reddish brown hairs.</description>
      <determination>1 Pleopeltis astrolepis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales on abaxial blade surface dense and overlapping, 0.5–1 mm wide, broadly ovate-lanceolate with fringed-ciliate margins; petioles round in cross section; sori round to oval, discrete; stem scales lanceolate-attenuate, with only occasional hairs.</description>
      <determination>2a var. erythrolepis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mature blade scales distinctly bicolored with dark brown centers and broad tan to silvery gray transparent margins, clathrate only near point of attachment; petiole scales often overlapping, margins ± entire; sori deeply embossed, forming bumps on adaxial blade surface; stems usually 1–2 mm diam.</description>
      <determination>3a var. michauxiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mature blade scales not bicolored or occasionally with very narrow transparent margin, dark reddish brown, clathrate throughout with cell luminae large and clear; petiole scales rarely overlapping, margins denticulate to ciliate; sori not embossed, rarely visible on adaxial blade surface; stems usually 2–3 mm diam.</description>
      <determination>4 Pleopeltis riograndensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
