<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1806">cheilanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker" date="1858">wrightii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Fil.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 87, plate 110, fig. A. 1858</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cheilanthes;species wrightii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  long-creeping, 1--3 mm diam.; scales uniformly brown or slightly darker at base, linear-lanceolate, straight to slightly contorted, loosely appressed, often deciduous on older portions of stem.  Leaves  clustered to somewhat scattered, 4--25 cm; vernation circinate.  Petiole  brown, grooved adaxially.  Blade  lanceolate to ovate-deltate, 2-pinnate-pinnatifid at base, 1--4 cm wide; rachis grooved adaxially, not scaly or pubescent.  Pinnae  not articulate, dark color of stalk continuing into pinna base, basal pair often slightly larger than adjacent pair, ± equilateral, appearing glabrous adaxially.  Costae  green adaxially for most of length; abaxial scales absent.  Ultimate segments  oblong to linear, not beadlike, the largest 3--7 mm, abaxially and adaxially glabrous.  False indusia  marginal, slightly differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  discontinuous, concentrated on interrupted lateral lobes.  Sporangia  containing 64 spores. 2 n  = 60.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Rocky slopes and ledges usually on igneous substrates;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="rocky slopes and ledges on igneous substrates" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">300--2000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex., Tex.; n Mexico.</description>
  <number>15</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Wright's lip fern</other_name>
  <discussion>The glabrous Cheilanthes wrightii is occasionally confused with C . alabamensis and certain species of Pellaea . Cheilanthes wrightii is easily separated from C . alabamensis by its glabrous rachis, which is grooved on the adaxial surface. It is distinguished from all local members of Pellaea by having both a grooved rachis and a thin, long-creeping stem.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
