<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Jermy" date="1986">tetragonostachys</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Maxon" date="1921">scopulorum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 36. 1921</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus tetragonostachys;species scopulorum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">densa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Maxon) R. M. Tryon" date="unknown">scopulorum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Selaginella;species densa;variety scopulorum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hieronymus" date="unknown">engelmannii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Maxon) C. F. Reed" date="unknown">scopulorum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Selaginella;species engelmannii;variety scopulorum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial or on rock, forming cushionlike or rather loose mats.  Stems  decumbent or creeping, not readily fragmenting, irregularly forked, without budlike arrested branches, tips straight; main stem upperside and underside structurally slightly different, conspicuously or inconspicuously indeterminate, lateral branches radially symmetric, conspicuously determinate, strongly ascending, 1--2-forked.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems, throughout stem length, 0.25--0.45 mm diam.  Leaves  monomorphic, in poorly defined pseudowhorls of 4 or 6, tightly appressed, ascending, green, linear-lanceolate to linear, in lateral ranks sometimes falcate, 2.5--4(--4.3) X 0.5--0.75 mm (upperside leaves smaller than underside, smaller also on ascending buds); abaxial ridges present; base (on main stem) decurrent, oblique, and glabrous on underside leaves, slightly decurrent to adnate, oblique, and glabrous or rarely puberulent on upperside leaves; margins usually short-ciliate, cilia transparent, spreading or ascending at base, denticulate and ascending on distal 2/3, 0.02--0.07(--0.15) mm; apex plane or sometimes slightly keeled, obtuse to attenuate, abruptly bristled; bristle whitish, transparent to opaque, with few teeth or smooth, 0.5--1.1 mm.  Strobili  solitary, (0.5--)1--3(--4.5) cm; sporophylls ovate-lanceolate, lanceolate, or seldom ovate, usually tapering toward apex, abaxial ridges well defined, base glabrous, margins proximally short-ciliate to denticulate, lacking cilia apically, apex usually attenuate or slightly keeled, short-bristled.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rocky alpine tundra, subalpine meadows, dry cliffs, rocky slopes, rock crevices, granitic outcrops and ledges, sandstone outcrops, in soil pockets among rocks, or sandy or granitic soil;</description>
  <description type="elevation">700--3700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C.; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., N.Mex., Oreg., Utah, Wash., Wyo.</description>
  <number>27</number>
  <discussion>Selaginella scopulorum is a member of the S . densa</discussion>
  <discussion>complex, in which there is a clear need for more systematic studies. Some specimens of S . scopulorum from Montana, Wyoming, and Colorado have more conspicuous whitish bristles than those elsewhere and are difficult to distinguish from S . densa .</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
