<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Jermy" date="1986">tetragonostachys</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="L. Underwood" date="1898">rupincola</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>25: 129. 1898</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus tetragonostachys;species rupincola</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  on rock or terrestrial, forming loose clumps.  Stems  radially symmetric, underground (rhizomatous) and aerial, not readily fragmenting, irregularly forked; both rhizomatous and aerial stems often with 1 branch arrested, budlike, tips straight; rhizomatous stems hard to distinguish on wholly creeping plants; aerial stems erect or ascending, sometimes decumbent to slightly creeping, budlike arrested branches restricted mostly near stem base.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems, restricted to lower stems or throughout stem length, 0.3--0.5 mm diam.  Leaves  dimorphic, not clearly ranked.  Rhizomatous stem leaves  persistent or deciduous, tightly appressed, scalelike.  Aerial stem leaves  appressed, ascending, green, linear-lanceolate, 3--4.7 X 0.45--0.65 mm; abaxial ridges present; base abruptly adnate, rounded, pubescent; margins long-ciliate, cilia white to whitish, spreading, 0.1--0.2 mm; apex not keeled to slightly keeled; bristle white to whitish or yellowish to greenish near base, puberulent, 0.65--1.85 mm (1/3--1/2 length of leaves).  Strobili  solitary, 0.5--2.5(--3.5) cm; sporophylls lanceolate, strongly tapering toward tip, abaxial ridges prominent, base glabrous, margins short-ciliate, apex long-bristled.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Exposed ledges and rock, steep slopes, rock crevices or gravelly soil;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1000--2000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex., Tex.; Mexico.</description>
  <number>8</number>
  <discussion>Selaginella rupincola is allied to S . bigelovii . It is one of the presumed parents of S . × neomexicana (see discussion). In addition to characteristics given, it can be separated from S . bigelovii in having hairs often running along the ridges of the abaxial groove, whereas S . bigelovii has nonhairy ridges on the abaxial groove.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
