<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Warren H. Wagner Jr. , Florence S. Wagner</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Agardh" date="unknown">ophioglossaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Ophioglossum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1062. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5, 484, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ophioglossaceae;genus Ophioglossum</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin ophis, snakelike, and glossa, tongue, in reference to the sporophore tip]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Roots  unbranched, whitish yellow to black, 0.1-1.5 mm diam., smooth, commonly proliferous and forming clones.  Stems  upright, forming caudex, to 1.6cm thick (cormlike in  O .  crotalophoroides ); gemmae absent.  Trophophores  erect to prostrate, blades nearly sessile or stalked, lanceolate to cordate, simple, 0.4-100 mm × 0.3-45 mm; margins entire; apex rounded, acute, or apiculate; veins anastomosing, main areoles to 15 × 4mm, but mostly less than 5 × 3 mm.  Sporophores  1 per leaf, simple, stalked, borne from ground level to well above ground at base of trophophore but commonly absent, leaf made up of only trophophyll.  Sporangial clusters  with sporangia in 2 rows, deeply sunken in simple, linear or oblong fleshy sporophore tip, tip usually ± apiculate.  Gametophytes  brown to white, narrowly linear, unbranched, 2-20 × 1-3mm diam.  x =30.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, mainly tropical and subtropical.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Adder's-tongue</other_name>
  <discussion>Ophioglossum occurs mostly in disturbed, open, grassy habitats. It is often overlooked because of superficial resemblance to seedlings of monocotyledonous plants. The intensive and careful field studies of R.D. Thomas (W. H. Wagner Jr., C. M. Allen, and G. P. Landry 1984) have greatly extended our knowledge of adder's-tongue distributions in North America. The chromosome numbers of Ophioglossum are the highest known in all vascular plants; numbers as high as 2 n =1200+ have been reported (A.Löve et al. 1977).</discussion>
  <discussion>(Key to species of Ophioglossum )</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 25-30 (7 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems spheric, cormlike, fleshy, 3--12 mm diam.; leaves arising from deep cavity in top of stem; trophophore blades usually lying flat on ground, deltate to cordate.</description>
      <determination>2 Ophioglossum crotalophoroides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems upright, 1--5 mm diam., seldom more; leaves arising at top of stem; trophophore blades erect to spreading, mostly ovate to lanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore veins in larger leaves forming small areoles within larger areoles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore veins forming only branching or nonbranching, free, included veinlets within larger areoles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades commonly folded when alive, ovate to ovate-lanceolate, to 10 × 4.5 cm; roots 0.5--1.5 mm diam.; sporophores 1.3--2.5 times length of trophophore; dried blades uniformly green without pale central band.</description>
      <determination>3 Ophioglossum engelmannii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades plane when alive, ovate to lanceolate, to 4.5 × 1.7 cm; roots 0.2--0.8 mm diam.; sporophores 2--6 times length of trophophore; dried blades commonly with pale central band.</description>
      <determination>4 Ophioglossum nudicaule</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades rounded at apex, apiculum absent, ovate-lanceolate, oblanceolate, ovate, to trowel-shaped, to 10 × 3.5 cm; adult leaves usually 1 per stem, appearing in a single flush once per year.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades acute at apex, with ± developed apiculum or apiculum absent, ovate-oblong, ovate-deltate, or ovate-lanceolate, to 4.5 × 1 cm (6 × 3 mm occasionally in O. petiolatum); adult leaves commonly 2--3 per stem, appearing in 1 or more flushes per year, depending on rains.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades dark green, somewhat shiny (alive), ovate to trowel-shaped, firm, base abruptly tapering; damp forest habitats; se United States, Mexican highlands.</description>
      <determination>7 Ophioglossum vulgatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades pale green, dull (alive), obovate to oblanceolate or ovate, herbaceous, base gradually tapering; open pastures, meadows, marshes, ditches; n North America.</description>
      <determination>6 Ophioglossum pusillum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots dark brown, usually fewer than 8 per shoot, major roots generally straight, 0.8--1.3 mm diam.; blade apiculum mostly absent; venation usually coarse.</description>
      <determination>5 Ophioglossum petiolatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots yellowish to pale brown, usually more than 12 per shoot, 0.2--1 mm diam.; blade apiculum absent or present; venation usually fine, intricate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots 0.5--1 mm diam.; sporophores 1--2.5 times length of trophophore; trophophores 0.4--4.3 × 0.3--1 cm, commonly folded when alive; blades thick, herbaceous; California.</description>
      <determination>1 Ophioglossum californicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots 0.2--0.8 mm diam.; sporophores 2--6 times length of trophophore; trophophores as small as 0.4 × 0.3 cm, usually plane when alive; blades thin, herbaceous; se United States.</description>
      <determination>4 Ophioglossum nudicaule</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
