<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert M. Lloyd</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Acrostichum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1067. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5, 484, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus Acrostichum</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek acros, at the end, tip, and stichos, row, referring to the distal spore-bearing pinnae]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial in fresh- or saltwater habitats.  Stems  erect or creeping, branched; scales dark brown, concolored, linear-lanceolate, margins entire.  Leaves  slightly dimorphic, clustered, 1--5 m.  Petiole  brown, with a single groove adaxially, glabrous, smooth or with scale scars, with several abaxial vascular bundles and 2 adaxial vascular bundles.  Blade  lanceolate, pinnate, leathery, abaxially glabrous or hispid, adaxially dull, not striate, glabrous; rachis straight.  Pinnae  stalked, free from rachis, narrowly oblong to lanceolate, 2--5 cm wide; base cuneate; stalk green; margins plane; fertile leaves bearing sporangia on most pinnae or on only more distal pinnae (fertile pinnae may be slightly smaller than sterile ones).  Veins  of pinnae conspicuous, strongly anastomosing.  False indusia  absent.  Sporangia  spread over abaxial surface, mixed with paraphyses (sori acrostichoid), containing 64 spores.  Spores  yellow, tetrahedral, minutely tuberculate or roughened, equatorial flange absent.  x  = 30.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide, warm and tropical regions.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Leather fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3, possibly more (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Adams, D. C. and P. B. Tomlinson. 1979.  Acrostichum  in Florida. Amer. Fern J. 69: 42--46. García de López, I. 1978. Revisión del género  Acrostichum  en la República Dominicana. Moscosoa 1: 64--70.</reference>
    <reference>Lloyd, R. M. 1980. Reproductive biology and gametophyte morphology of New World populations of  Acrostichum aureum . Amer. Fern J. 70: 99--110.</reference>
    <reference>Small, J. K. 1938. Ferns of the Southeastern States. Lancaster, Pa. [Facsimile edition 1964, New York and London.]</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fertile leaves with only most distal pinnae fertile; pinnae often distant and not overlapping; costal areoles usually narrow, 3 or more times longer than wide; paraphyses terminating in isodiametric, irregularly lobed cell.</description>
      <determination>1 Acrostichum aureum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fertile leaves with most pinnae fertile; pinnae distant to closely spaced and ± overlapping; costal areoles usually broad, less than 3 times longer than wide; paraphyses terminating in horizontally extended, smooth or lobed cell.</description>
      <determination>2 Acrostichum danaeifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
