<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">lycopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Holub" date="1975">Diphasiastrum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Preslia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>47: 104. 1975</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family lycopodiaceae;genus Diphasiastrum</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[ Diphasium, a generic name, and -astrum, incomplete resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial, mainly trailing on ground with erect shoots.  Roots  emerging immediately on underside of main stems.  Horizontal stems  on substrate surface to subterranean, long-creeping.  Upright shoots  quadrate to flattened (except in  D .  sitchense ), 2--6 mm diam., usually with 2--5 lateral branchlets on main erect stem; lateral branchlets leafy, ± flat in cross section.  Leaves  on horizontal stems somewhat distant, appressed, linear to lanceolate, thin, scalelike; leaves on ultimate branchlets appressed to divergent, linear-lanceolate to nearly filiform, usually almost scalelike and mostly imbricate, in 4 ranks, leaves of lateral ranks larger, more spreading than those of upperside and underside ranks (except in  Diphasiastrum sitchense  with 5 ranks of uniform nonimbricate leaves).  Gemmiferous branchlets and gemmae  absent.  Strobili  solitary and sessile or multiple and stalked, apex blunt, acute, or with sterile apical projection; peduncle conspicuously leafy; sporophylls shorter than peduncle leaves.  Sporangia  reniform.  Spores  reticulate, sides at equator convex, angles acute.  Gametophytes  nonphotosynthetic, mycorrhizal, carrot-shaped, paraphyses absent; ring meristem present.  x  = 23.</description>
  <description type="distribution">mainly north temperate and subarctic.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">False Diphasium</other_name>
  <discussion>Diphasiastrum is remarkable in North America for its ability to form numerous homoploid, apparently fertile interspecific hybrids, some of which are frequent to common and must be reckoned with in floristic studies. Field and laboratory studies of these hybrids and their parents are needed for determination of the population dynamics of Diphasiastrum and to answer questions as to why the parental species retain their genetic identities.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 15--20 (11 taxa in the flora, including 5 species and 6 fertile hybrids):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Beitel, J. M. 1979. The clubmosses  Lycopodium sitchense  and  L .  sabinaefolium  in the upper Great Lakes area. Michigan Bot. 18: 3--13.</reference>
    <reference>Holub, J. 1975.  Diphasiastrum , a new genus in Lycopodiaceae. Preslia 14: 97--100.</reference>
    <reference>Wilce, J. H. 1965. Section  Complanata  of the genus  Lycopodium . Beih. Nova Hedwigia 19: i--ix, 1--233, plate 40.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Upright shoots to 18 cm, mostly less than 12 cm including base; strobili mostly sessile.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Upright shoots, 8--50 cm, mostly more than 12 cm, including base; strobili stalked.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate branchlets approximately square in cross section; leaves 4-ranked, strongly overlapping.</description>
      <determination>1 Diphasiastrum alpinum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate branchlets round in cross section; leaves 5-ranked, not overlapping.</description>
      <determination>4 Diphasiastrum sitchense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate branchlets cordlike, nearly square in cross section, usually bluish glaucous; underside leaves approximately equal in size to lateral and upperside leaves.</description>
      <determination>5 Diphasiastrum tristachyum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate branchlets narrowly bladelike, flat in cross section, usually green; underside leaves much smaller than lateral and upperside leaves.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branchlets irregular, with conspicuous annual bud constrictions; peduncles, if present, regularly forked; strobili mostly 15--25 mm, lacking sterile tips.</description>
      <determination>2 Diphasiastrum complanatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branchlets very regularly fan-shaped, lacking conspicuous annual bud constrictions; peduncles mostly branching abruptly at base to produce false whorl of strobili; strobili mostly 20--35 mm, many with sterile tips.</description>
      <determination>3 Diphasiastrum digitatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
