<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Masahiro Kato</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Roth" date="1799">Athyrium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Tent. Fl. Germ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(1,1): 31, 58. 1799</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Athyrium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek athyros, doorless; the sporangia only tardily push back the outer edge of the indusium]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  generally terrestrial.  Stems  short-creeping or ascending, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, usually dying back in winter.  Petiole  ± 0.5 times length of blade or less, base swollen and dentate, persisting as trophopod over winter or not; vascular bundles 2, lateral, lunate in cross section.  Blade  lanceolate to elliptic or oblanceolate, 1--3-pinnate-pinnatifid, gradually reduced distally to confluent, pinnatifid apex, herbaceous.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins serrulate or crenate; proximal pinnae often reduced, sessile to short-petiolulate, ± equilateral; costae adaxially grooved, grooves continuous from rachis to costae to costules; indument absent or of linear to lanceolate scales or 1-celled glands abaxially.  Veins  free, simple or forked.  Sori  in 1 row between midrib and margin, round to elongate, straight or hooked at distal end, or horseshoe-shaped; indusia shaped like sori, persistent, attached laterally or with narrow sinus, or indusia absent.  Spores  brownish, rugose.  x  = 40.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Lady fern</other_name>
  <discussion>In species outside the flora stems are sometimes long-creeping to erect, with leaves radially or dorsiventrally arranged.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species about 180 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Johnson, D. M. 1986b. Trophopods in North American species of  Athyrium  (Aspleniaceae). Syst. Bot. 11: 26--31.</reference>
    <reference>Kato, M. 1977. Classification of  Athyrium  and allied genera of Japan. Bot. Mag. (Tokyo) 90: 23--40.</reference>
    <reference>Liew, F. S. 1972. Numerical taxonomic studies on North American lady ferns and their allies. Taiwania 17: 190--221.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sori round, submarginal; indusia much reduced or usually absent.</description>
      <determination>1 Athyrium alpestre var. americanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sori elongate or hooked, medial; indusia well developed.</description>
      <determination>2 Athyrium filix-femina</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
