<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1841">pellaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Mettenius ex Kuhn" date="1869">intermedia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>38: 84. 1869</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus pellaea;species intermedia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pellaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">intermedia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Mettenius ex Kuhn" date="unknown">pubescens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pellaea;species intermedia;variety pubescens;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  creeping, horizontal, slender, 2--4 mm diam.; scales mostly bicolored, narrowly lanceolate, largest scales 0.3--0.8 mm wide, centers black, thick, margins brown, thin, irregularly dentate.  Leaves  monomorphic, widely scattered along stem, 12--50 cm; croziers pubescent and bearing a few scales.  Petiole  straw-colored, tan, or gray, not lustrous, rounded or slightly flattened adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  ovate to elongate-deltate, usually 2-pinnate proximally, 4--20 cm wide; rachis tan throughout, straight to slightly flexuous, rounded or flattened adaxially, ± pubescent.  Pinnae  perpendicular to rachis or slightly ascending, not decurrent on rachis, usually with 7--21 ultimate segments; costae straight to slightly flexuous, 20--100 mm, longer than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  ovate to elliptic, 5--15 mm, leathery, glabrous or usually puberulent abaxially; margins recurved on fertile segments, usually covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, nearly entire; apex obtuse to slightly mucronate.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  short-stalked, containing 32 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands.  n  = 2 n  = 87, 116, apogamous.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Rocky slopes and ledges, on a variety of substrates, including limestone and granite;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="rocky slopes and ledges , on a variety of substrates , including limestone and granite" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">300--2400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex., Tex.; n Mexico.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <discussion>Plants of Pellaea intermedia in the flora are apogamous triploids and tetraploids; a sexual diploid cytotype has been found near Saltillo, Mexico (A. F. Tryon 1968). Given the high degree of morphologic similarity among the three cytotypes, the North American polyploids probably were derived from the Mexican diploid through autopolyploidy.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
