<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robbin C. Moran</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cavanilles" date="1799">Tectaria</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Anales Hist. Nat.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(2): 115. 1799</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Tectaria</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin tectum, roof, and aria, a substantive suffix, alluding to the rooflike indusium of some species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial or on rock.  Stems  short-creeping to erect, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, evergreen.  Petiole  3/4--3 times length of blade, base not swollen; vascular bundles more than 3, arranged in an arc, ± round in cross section.  Blade  lanceolate to deltate or pentagonal, entire to 1-pinnate-pinnatifid [3-pinnate-pinnatifid], reduced distally to shallowly lobed or hastate apex, herbaceous to papery.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins entire to sinuate or shallowly lobed; proximal pinnae not or only slightly reduced, sessile to short-petiolulate, base equilateral or often inequilateral with prominent basiscopic lobe(s); costae adaxially rounded or shallowly grooved, grooves not continuous from rachis to costae; indument lacking or of multicellular hairs on costae abaxially, of multicellular hairs on costae adaxially.  Veins  reticulate, areoles with or without included veinlets.  Sori  in 1--several rows between midrib and margin, round; indusia peltate to round-reniform and with narrow sinus, persistent or caducous.  Spores  brownish, with inflated folds or wings.  x  = 40.</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly tropical.</description>
  <number>16</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Halberd fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 200 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Morton, C. V. 1966. The Mexican species of  Tectaria . Amer. Fern J. 56: 120--137.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades 15-50 cm; areoles with included veinlets.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades 5-15 cm; areoles rarely with included veinlets.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Indusia peltate, attached centrally; pinnae cordate at base; rachises and costae glabrous abaxially.</description>
      <determination>1 Tectaria heracleifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Indusia round-reniform, attached at sinus; pinnae oblique at base; rachises and costae puberulent abaxially.</description>
      <determination>2 Tectaria incisa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae 1-8 pairs, often with proliferous buds in axils; petiole shorter than or rarely equaling blade, pubescent on both surfaces; indusia round-reniform, attached at sinus.</description>
      <determination>3 Tectaria coriandrifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae absent or 1(-2) pair, without proliferous buds in axils; petiole 1-3 times length of blade, pubescent adaxially, lacking hairs abaxially; indusia peltate, attached centrally.</description>
      <determination>4 Tectaria fimbriata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
