<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Newman" date="unknown">aspleniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">asplenium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="E. P. St. John ex Small" date="1938">plenum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ferns S. E. States</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>173. 1938</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family aspleniaceae;genus asplenium;species plenum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots  proliferous.  Stems  erect, unbranched; scales blackish throughout, narrowly deltate, 0.4--1.1 × 0.3--0.7 mm, margins entire to denticulate.  Leaves  monomorphic.  Petiole  blackish throughout, dull, 2--6(--10) cm, 1/4--2/5 length of blade; indument absent.  Blade  lanceolate, 1--2-pinnate, (4--)8--12(--15) × 1.5--5 cm, thin, glabrous; base not tapered; apex gradually narrowing.  Rachis  mostly green except occasionally blackish at base, dull, glabrous.  Pinnae  in (5--)10--20(--25) pairs, oblong-deltate, 1--3.5 × 0.5--1.8 cm; base excavate on basiscopic side; apex pointed.  Pinnules  linear to oblong, 4--10 mm; apex mostly notched.  Veins  free, not conspicuous.  Sori  mostly 1 per segment, 1--3 mm.  Spores  mostly abortive, some viable. 2 n  = 144.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Limestone rocks in shaded forests;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="limestone rocks" constraint="in shaded forests" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--50 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <number>29</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Ruffled spleenwort</other_name>
  <discussion>Asplenium plenum occurs with its parents on limestone rocks in shaded forests and is known only from Florida, although it could occur in the Antilles, Central America, and South America (D. B. Lellinger 1981). It is noteworthy for constituting one of the first known examples of backcrossing and formation of a new taxon by unreduced spores from a sterile hybrid. According to V. M. Morzenti (1967) and G. J. Gastony (1986), hybridization between A . abscissum and A . verecundum produced A . × curtissii . An unreduced spore of the hybrid gave rise to a 3 x gametophyte. This gametophyte produced a 3 x sperm that backcrossed with an x egg of A . abscissum producing the 4 x allotetraploid, A . plenum , that is not only capable of propagation by minute root proliferations like those of the parents but also to some extent by spores. This complex hypothesis was confirmed by electrophoretic comparisons of the plants involved (G. J. Gastony 1986).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
