<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Clifton E. Nauman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="C. Presl" date="unknown">lygodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1801">Lygodium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(2): 7, 106. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family lygodiaceae;genus Lygodium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek lygodes, flexible, in reference to the twining rachis]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Stems  branched, slender.  Leaves  often more than several meters, 2-pinnate or more divided, climbing by means of twining rachis; fertile pinnae borne toward apex of fertile leaves.  Blades  of short, alternate primary pinnae.  Pinnules  ± entire to palmately or pinnately lobed; fertile and sterile pinnae similar or fertile pinnae greatly contracted.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, mostly tropical regions, a few species in temperate regions, North America, Asia in Japan, s Africa, Pacific Islands in New Zealand.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Climbing ferns</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 40 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Beckner, J. 1968. Lygodium microphyllum , another fern escaped in Florida. Amer. Fern J. 58: 93-94.</reference>
    <reference>Nauman, C. E. 1987. Schizaeaceae in Florida. Sida 12: 69-74.</reference>
    <reference>Nauman, C. E. and D. F. Austin. 1978. Spread of the exotic fern Lygodium microphyllum in Florida. Amer. Fern J. 68: 65-66.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnules palmately lobed, sterile tissue nearly absent on fertile lobes; petioles borne 1--4 cm apart.</description>
      <determination>1 Lygodium palmatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnules 1-pinnate to palmately lobed, sterile tissue present on fertile lobes; petioles borne less than 1 cm apart.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnules usually 1-pinnate, primary divisions mostly undivided, usually without basal lobes; lobes absent or rounded, auriculate, not directed toward leaf apex; ultimate segments articulate to petiolules, leaving wiry stalks when detached; blade tissue glabrous abaxially.</description>
      <determination>2 Lygodium microphyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnules usually more than 1-pinnate, primary divisions pinnately to palmately lobed or divided, or if undivided with distinct basal lobes; lobes directed toward leaf apex; ultimate segments not articulate to petiolules, not leaving wiry stalks when detached; blade tissue sparsely to moderately pubescent abaxially.</description>
      <determination>3 Lygodium japonicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
