<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="D. Don" date="1836">coulteri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London, Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 440. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species coulteri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 24m; trunk to 1m diam., straight to contorted; crown broad, thin, irregular.  Bark  dark gray-brown to near black, deeply furrowed, with long, scaly, irregularly anastomosing, rounded ridges.  Branches  often ascending; twigs stout to moderately slender, violet-brown, often glaucous, aging gray-brown, rough.  Buds  ovoid, deep red-brown, 1.5(--3)cm, resinous; scale margins white-fringed, apex cuspidate.  Leaves  3 per fascicle, slightly spreading, not drooping, mostly ascending in a brush, persisting 3--4 years, 15--30cm × ca. 2mm, slightly curved or straight, twisted, dusty gray-green, all surfaces with pale, fine stomatal lines, margins serrulate, apex abruptly subulate; sheath 2--4cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  ovoid to cylindric, to 25mm, light purple-brown, aging orange-brown.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, gradually shedding seeds thereafter and moderately persistent, massive, heavy, drooping, asymmetric at base, narrowly ovoid before opening, ovoid-cylindric when open, 20--35cm, pale yellow-brown, resinous, stalks to 3cm; apophyses transverse-rhombic, strongly and sharply cross-keeled, elongate, curved, continuous with umbos to form long, upcurved claws 2.5--3cm.  Seeds  obovoid; body 15--22mm, dark brown; wing to 25mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Dry rocky slopes, flats, ridges, and chaparral, transitional to oak-pine woodland;</description>
  <description type="elevation">300--2100m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.; Mexico in Baja California.</description>
  <number>30</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Coulter pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus coulteri is the heaviest-coned pine; one who seeks its shade should wear a hardhat.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
