<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David M. Johnson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Onoclea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1062. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5, 484, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Onoclea</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek onos, vessel, and kleiein, to close, in reference to the sori, which are enclosed by the revolute fertile leaf margins]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Stems  creeping, stolons absent.  Leaves  strongly dimorphic, fertile leaves usually shorter, greatly contracted, persistent 2--3 years, sterile leaves dying back in winter.  Petiole  of sterile leaf ca. 1--1.5 times length of blade, petiole of fertile leaf 2--6 times length of blade, bases swollen and persisting as trophopods over winter; vascular bundles 2, lateral, lunate in cross section.  Blade  of sterile leaf deltate, pinnatifid to pinnate-pinnatifid proximally, reduced and shallowly pinnatifid distally, herbaceous to papery, blade of fertile leaf linear-oblong, 2-pinnate, leathery.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins of sterile blades entire to sinuate or shallowly lobed, margins of fertile pinnules strongly revolute and forming hardened beadlike structures; proximal pinnae largest or nearly so, sessile or adnate, equilateral; costae adaxially flat; indument on both sides of linear to lanceolate scales and/or multicellular hairs on rachis and costae. Veins reticulate with areoles lacking included veinlets in sterile leaves, veins free in fertile leaves.  Sori  covered by strongly revolute margins of pinnae, ± round; indusia vestigial, triangular, persistent but not easily seen in mature leaves.  Spores  greenish, with a few low folds and numerous, minute, echinate-cristate elements.  x  = 37.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate regions in Northern Hemisphere, Asia.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sensitive fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Onoclea is one of several genera known to store starch grains in long-persistent petiole bases (trophopods) (W. H. Wagner Jr. and D. M. Johnson 1983).</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
