<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">pteris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Swartz" date="1801">tripartita</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(2): 67. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus pteris;species tripartita</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Litobrochia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Swartz) C. Presl" date="unknown">tripartita</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Litobrochia;species tripartita;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  stout, short-creeping, densely and conspicuously scaly; scales pale brown.  Leaves  clustered, 1--2 m.  Petiole  straw-colored to brownish red, to more than 1 m, scaly proximally, otherwise glabrous at maturity.  Blade  deltate to pentagonal, pedate, ultimate divisions pinnately divided, 1--2 × 1--2 m; rachis not winged.  Pinnae  few, closely spaced, remaining green through winter, not decurrent on rachis, not articulate to rachis, oblong-lanceolate, 1--3-forked, to 7 × 6 dm; base asymmetrical, acute; apex acute; rachis and costae glabrate or with minute hairs, especially near axils of proximal pinnae; penultimate pinnules linear to linear-lanceolate, pinnatifid, separated, not remaining green through winter, not articulate to rachis.  Ultimate segments  of blade numerous, linear-oblong to linear-lanceolate, to 19 × 6 mm, margins entire or serrulate, apex obtuse and rounded to acute; terminal segments 3--4 cm longer and more tapering than lateral segments.  Veins  anastomosing near costae and costules, becoming forked and free near margins of ultimate segments.  Sori  narrow, blade tissue exposed abaxially.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Terrestrial in cypress, pond-apple, and other swamps or forested wet habitats, on constantly moist, circumneutral soils;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="terrestrial in cypress , pond-apple , and other swamps or forested wet habitats , on moist , circumneutral soils ;" modifier="constantly" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--50 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced, naturalized in scattered locations; Fla.; West Indies; Central America; South America; native to tropical Asia.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Giant brake</other_name>
</bio:treatment>
