<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Clifton E. Nauman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="C. Presl" date="1836">Campyloneurum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Tent. Pterid.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>189. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus Campyloneurum</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek kampylos, curved, and neuron, nerve, in reference to the venation]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic.  Stems  short- to long-creeping, branched, 2--10 mm diam., sometimes whitish pruinose; scales brown, ovate, often clathrate, entire.  Leaves  monomorphic, tufted, conspicuously narrowed to tip, to 150 cm.  Petiole  absent or present, articulate to stem.  Blade  linear to lanceolate or elliptic, simple, glabrous, sparsely scaly, margins entire; scales clathrate, basifixed.  Primary veins  connected by 1--several secondary veins (cross veins), forming 1--several areoles between each pair of primary veins, areoles with 1--4 excurrent veinlets, sometimes these excurrent veinlets dividing areoles completely.  Sori  in 1--10 rows between midrib and margin, terminal on included veinlets, discrete, round; indument absent.  Spores  verrucose to nearly psilate.  x  = 37.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical, North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Strap ferns</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 25--50 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Eaton, A. A. 1906. Pteridophytes observed during three excursions into southern Florida. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 33: 455--486.</reference>
    <reference>Lellinger, D. B. 1988. Some new species of  Campyloneurum  and a provisional key to the genus. Amer. Fern J. 78: 14--34.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Primary veins obscure and slightly to strongly curved; blades generally less than 6 cm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Primary veins conspicuous and straight to slightly curved; blades generally more than 6 cm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades more than 2 cm wide, margins shallowly sinuate to undulate, not revolute; areoles in 4–8 series between costa and margin; petioles always present.</description>
      <determination>1 Campyloneurum costatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades less than 2 cm wide, margins revolute, not shallowly sinuate to undulate; areoles in 1–4 series between costa and margin; petioles present or absent.</description>
      <determination>2 Campyloneurum angustifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles absent to ca. 9 cm; blades yellow-green, margins entire and plane to lightly undulate.</description>
      <determination>3 Campyloneurum phyllitidis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles 5–18 cm; blades dark green, margins undulate.</description>
      <determination>4 Campyloneurum latum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
