<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Alan R. Smith</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">Polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Polypodiaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  perennial, terrestrial, on rock, or often epiphytic, erect, arching, or occasionally pendent.  Stems  long- to short-creeping, branched or not, bearing scales and few to numerous roots, usually dictyostelic.  Leaves  monomorphic to dimorphic, circinate in bud.  Petiole  usually articulate at base [rarely nonarticulate, as in  Loxogramme ], lacking scales or sometimes scaly, with usually 3 vascular bundles. Blade simple to often pinnatifid, pinnatisect, or pinnate, infrequently more divided; rachis grooved or not adaxially. Veins free (and simple to several times forked) to often anastomosing in complex systems, areoles with or without included veinlets. Indument on blade absent, or petiole, rachis, costae, and sometimes blade tissue usually bearing hairs (these often septate and with reddish crosswalls) and/or scales. Sori borne abaxially on veins, round to oblong, occasionally elongate, rarely marginal, rarely covering surface; paraphyses present or absent; sporangia with stalk of 2 or 3 rows of cells; indusia absent. Spores usually transparent or yellowish (rarely greenish), all 1 kind, bilateral, monolete [rarely trilete, as in some Loxogramme], surface most often smooth, tuberculate, verrucose, or granulate, occasionally spiny, 64 per sporangium (spores globose and 32 per sporangium in apogamous spp.). Gametophytes green, aboveground, cordate or elliptic, glabrous or sometimes glandular; archegonia and antheridia borne on lower surface, antheridia 3-celled.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide, especially tropics and subtropics.</description>
  <number>22</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Polypody Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Phymatosorus scolopendria (Burman f.) Pichi-Sermolli, native to the Old World, is a rare escape in southern Florida.</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera in this family are variously circumscribed, and the New World species historically were placed in the single genus Polypodium . Many of the segregates recognized here are still placed in Polypodium in recent floristic accounts. Limits of genera in both Old World and New World are controversial and are currently under study by several workers.</discussion>
  <discussion>(Key to genera of Polypodiaceae)</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 40, species perhaps 500 (7 genera, 25 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades simple, undivided.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades pinnatifid or pinnatisect, rarely 1-pinnate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporangia confined to marginal or nearly marginal bands in distal 1/2 of blade.</description>
      <determination>7 Neurodium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporangia in discrete, round to oblong or slightly elongate sori on abaxial surface, not in marginal bands.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades abaxially with peltate scales.</description>
      <determination>4 Pleopeltis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades abaxially glabrous, except for scattered scales on midrib.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 2-10 mm diam.; sori in 1-10 or more rows between midrib and margin; petioles clustered, proximate; main lateral veins often prominent, ±parallel.</description>
      <determination>5 Campyloneurum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 0.5-1.5 mm wide; sori in 1 row between midrib and margin; petioles well separated, often 1-2 cm apart; main lateral veins obscure, not parallel.</description>
      <determination>6 Microgramma</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades with numerous peltate or ovate scales abaxially.</description>
      <determination>4 Pleopeltis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades lacking scales abaxially except along midrib.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades pectinate, usually with more than (20-)25 pairs of segments; segments narrow, linear, 1.5-5(-8) mm wide; veins free; stems short-creeping; Florida.</description>
      <determination>1 Pecluma</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades pinnatifid, rarely 1-pinnate, with fewer than 20(-25) pairs of segments; segments broad, generally (3-)5-20(-30) mm wide; veins free or anastomosing; stems moderately to widely creeping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades 1-pinnate; Florida.</description>
      <determination>2 Polypodium triseriale</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades pinnatifid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Venation free or with 1 row of areoles between costa and margin; sori at end of 1 included veinlet or on forked free vein; widespread but not Florida. .</description>
      <determination>2 Polypodium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Venation highly reticulate, with 3-4 rows of areoles between costa and margin; sori at end of usually 2 included veinlets; Florida.</description>
      <determination>3 Phlebodium</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
