<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Alan R. Smith</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Blume" date="1828">Arachniodes</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl. Javae</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 241. 1828</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Arachniodes</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek arachnion, spider's web, and -odes, having the form or nature of; it has been suggested that Blume saw fungal hyphae or spider webs on his original material]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Stems  moderately long- to short-creeping, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, evergreen. Petiole ± as long as blade, base not swollen; vascular bundles more than 3, arranged in an arc, ± round in cross section.  Blade  broadly deltate or pentagonal, 2--3-pinnate-pinnatifid, gradually to abruptly reduced distally to pinnate or pinnatifid apex, papery to somewhat leathery.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins and especially apex spinulose; proximal pinnae largest, petiolulate, inequilateral with basal basiscopic pinnule much larger and more elongate than more distal pinnules; costae adaxially grooved, grooves continuous from rachis to costae to costules; indument of hairlike scales abaxially, absent adaxially.  Veins  free, forked.  Sori  in 1 row between midrib and margin, round; indusia round-reniform, attached at narrow sinus, persistent.  Spores  brownish, rugate or tuberculate, sometimes spiny.  x  = 41.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropics and subtropics, mostly in e Asia and Pacific Islands, a few in Africa, ca. 4 in Mexico, Central America, South America.</description>
  <number>10</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">East Indian holly fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (1 in the flora naturalized from Asia):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ching, R. C. 1934. A revision of the compound leaved Polysticha and other related species in the continental Asia including Japan and Formosa. Sinensia 5: 23--91.</reference>
    <reference>Gordon, J. E. 1981.  Arachniodes simplicior  new to South Carolina and the United States. Amer. Fern J. 71: 65--68.</reference>
    <reference>Tindale, M. D. 1960. Pteridophyta of south eastern Australia. Contr. New South Wales Natl. Herb., Fl. Ser. 211: 47--78.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
