<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ronald J. Taylor</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Endlicher) Carrière" date="unknown">Tsuga</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>185. 1855- Hemlock, pruche [Japanese  tsuga , nampan]</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus Tsuga</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Japanese tsuga, name for native hemlocks of Japan]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Endlicher" date="unknown">Tsuga</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Conif.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>83. 1847</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;section Tsuga;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  evergreen; crown conic; leading shoot usually drooping.  Bark  gray to brown, scaly, often deeply furrowed.  Branches  horizontal, often tending to be arranged in flattened "sprays" and arched downward; short (spur) shoots absent; young twigs and distal portions of stem flexuous and pendent, roughened by peglike projections persisting after leaves fall.  Buds  mostly rounded at apex, not resinous.  Leaves  borne singly, persisting several years, ± 2-ranked or radiating in all directions, flattened to somewhat angular; abruptly narrowed to a petiolelike base, set on peglike projections, these angled, projected forward, sheath absent; apex rounded or notched; resin canals 1.  Cones  borne on year-old twigs.  Pollen cones  solitary, globose, brown.  Seed cones  maturing in 1 year, shedding seeds and falling soon thereafter or persisting for several years, pendent, ovoid, oblong, or oblong-cylindric, sessile or nearly so; scales persistent, shape various, thin, leathery, lacking apophysis and umbo; bracts small, included.  Seeds  winged; cotyledons 4--6.  x =12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Northern Hemisphere.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hemlock</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">pruche</other_name>
  <discussion>Species of Tsuga are found naturally in areas of relatively moist climates where water stresses are minimal. Most are conspicuous, if not dominant, members of the communities in which they occur.</discussion>
  <discussion>Hemlock wood is moderately strong and pliable and lacks resin ducts. With the decline of associated species considered superior in commercial value, hemlocks have become important in the timber industry, especially for pulp. Hemlocks are also widely used for horticultural purposes; numerous cultivars have been developed.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 10 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly spreading in all directions from twigs, bearing stomates on both surfaces or on abaxial surface only; seed cones ovoid, oblong, or oblong-cylindric, 2.5-6 cm; scales oblong, 8-18 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly appearing 2-ranked, bearing stomates on abaxial surface only; seed cones ovoid, (1-)1.5-2.5(-3) cm; scales ovate to cuneate, 8-15 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves bearing stomates on both surfaces, thicker along midline; seed cones 3-6 cm, half as wide; montane tree of w North America.</description>
      <determination>2 Tsuga mertensiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves bearing stomates on abaxial surface only, flat, not notably thicker along midline, but slightly revolute; seed cones 2.5-4 cm, more than half as wide; montane tree of se United States.</description>
      <determination>1 Tsuga caroliniana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Buds 2.5-3.5 mm; crown narrowly conic; tree of w North America.</description>
      <determination>4 Tsuga heterophylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Buds 1.5-2.5 mm; crown broadly conic; tree of e North America.</description>
      <determination>3 Tsuga canadensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
