<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Raymond B. Cranfill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="C. Presl" date="unknown">Blechnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Blechnaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  perennial, mostly terrestrial, occasionally on rock or epiphytic.  Stems  creeping to suberect or ascending, sometimes climbing [rarely arborescent], slender to stout, dictyostelic, scaly.  Leaves  monomorphic or dimorphic, large and coarse, generally greater than 30 cm, often exceeding 1 m.  Petiole  not articulate, generally more than 2 vascular bundles arranged in arc, generally scaly at least at base.  Blade  often anthocyanic (reddish) when young, pinnatifid [rarely simple] to pinnate-pinnatifid or 2-pinnate [rarely decompound], glabrous or occasionally bearing scales or capitate glands.  Rachis  frequently grooved adaxially.  Veins  of sterile leaves generally free, rarely anastomosing, veins of fertile leaves united to form sorus-bearing secondary vein parallel to costa or costule (vascular commisure), sometimes anastomosing further.  Sori  elongate along secondary vein; indusia present [rarely absent], opening along costal side of fertile vein, frequently hidden by dehisced sporangia; sporangial stalk of 3 rows of cells.  Spores  monolete, reniform; perine present, variously ornamented.  Gametophytes  green, cordate, sometimes bearing capitate hairs, antheridia and archegonia borne on lower surface.</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly tropical and south temperate (except Woodwardia , which is north temperate).</description>
  <number>18</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Chain Fern Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Circumscription of genera is controversial, especially as to placement of those species now included in Blechnum . Characteristics holding the family together include the anastomoses of veins along the axes of the blade to form a series of areoles or a single continuous vein along which the sorus is borne, elongate sori with indusia opening toward midvein, bilateral spores, and chromosome base numbers of generally x = 28--36. Relationships of the family with both dryopteroid and athyrioid ferns have been suggested.</discussion>
  <discussion>Stenochlaena tenuifolia (Desvaux) T. Moore, native to the Old World, was reported as escaped from cultivation in the 1930s in southern Florida; it has not been collected there recently. It is distinguished by having climbing stems and by having contracted, 2-pinnate fertile leaves with sporangia covering the abaxial surface.</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 10, species ca. 250 (2 genera, 6 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sori continuous along length of costa or costule; veins of sterile leaves free.</description>
      <determination>1 Blechnum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sori distinct, in chainlike rows along costa or costule; veins of sterile leaves anastomosing at least along costae and costules.</description>
      <determination>2 Woodwardia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
