<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>George Yatskievych , Michael D. Windham</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1833">Pityrogramma</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Handbuch</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 19. 1833</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus Pityrogramma</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pityros, bran, and gramma, lines (as in written characters), referring to the farina covering the abaxial leaf blade surface]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial [or on rock].  Stems  erect or nearly so, unbranched; scales brown, concolored or nearly so, lanceolate, margins entire.  Leaves  monomorphic, closely spaced, 25--150 cm.  Petiole  black to purplish black or reddish brown, longitudinally grooved adaxially, glabrous, with 2(--3) vascular bundles.  Blade  linear-lanceolate to ovate or elongate-triangular, 1--4-pinnate, herbaceous to leathery, abaxially usually farinose, farina white or yellow, sometimes partially or completely replaced by trichomes, adaxially glabrous, dull, not striate; rachis straight.  Ultimate segments  stalked or sessile, free from costa or partially adnate to it, narrowly triangular to linear, entire or lobed; base narrowly cuneate, stalks when present green, not lustrous; margins not recurved to form false indusia.  Veins  of ultimate segments free, obscure, pinnately branched and divergent distally.  False indusia  absent.  Sporangia  scattered along veins, containing 32 or 64 spores, intermixed with farina-producing glands.  Spores  tan with dark brown ridges, tetrahedral-globose, perispore usually reticulate, with equatorial flange (except in  Pityrogramma trifoliata ).  Gametophytes  glabrous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">primarily neotropical, some in Africa, introduced elsewhere in Eastern Hemisphere.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Silverback fern</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">goldback fern</other_name>
  <discussion>The name Nesoris bicolor Rafinesque was based on a yellow-farinose plant from Florida and presumably represents a species of Pityrogramma . A type has not been located, and C. S. Rafinesque's (1836[--1838]b, part 4) description is not precise enough to permit equation of this name with modern nomenclature. No yellow-farinose Pityrogramma has since been reported from Florida.</discussion>
  <discussion>Pentagramma has been segregated from Pityrogramma (G. Yatskievych et al. 1990) and comprises what was the Pityrogramma triangularis (Kaulfuss) Maxon complex.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 15 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Tryon, R. M. 1962. Taxonomic fern notes. II.  Pityrogramma  (including  Trismeria ) and  Anogramma . Contr. Gray Herb. 189: 52--76.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal pinnae pinnately lobed or divided, narrowly triangular.</description>
      <determination>1a var. calomelanos</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal pinnae entire or serrulate, linear to narrowly lanceolate.</description>
      <determination>2 Pityrogramma trifoliata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
