<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Edward R. Alverson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown in Franklin" date="1823">Cryptogramma</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Franklin,Narr. Journey Polar Sea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>767. 1823</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus Cryptogramma</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek cryptos, hidden, and gramme, line, referring to the ± marginal soral bands hidden by revolute margins]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  on rock.  Stems  decumbent to erect, or creeping, few to many branched; scales colorless or brownish, concolored or bicolored, ovate, lanceolate or linear, margins entire.  Leaves  dimorphic, scattered or densely tufted; fertile leaves 5--25 cm; sterile leaves 3--20 cm, shorter than fertile leaves.  Petiole  dark brown proximally, light brown to green distally, with single longitudinal groove adaxially, scaly, with single vascular bundle.  Blade  deltate, lanceolate to elliptic, 2--4-pinnate, somewhat leathery or herbaceous to membranaceous, abaxially glabrous, adaxially glabrous or sparsely pubescent, dull to somewhat lustrous, not striate; rachis straight.  Ultimate segments  of blade short-stalked or sessile, free or adnate to midrib; stalks dull, green; segments of sterile leaves ovate, elliptic, obovate, or fan-shaped, usually less than 4 mm wide, margins plane, dentate or shallowly to deeply cut; fertile segments strongly differentiated from sterile segments, lanceolate to linear, usually less than 2 mm wide, margins reflexed to form false indusia extending over entire length of segments, at first covering young sporangia, often becoming plane at maturity.  Veins  of ultimate segments usually obscure, free, pinnately branched and divergent distally.  False indusia  greenish to brown, broad, clearly marginal, usually concealing sporangia.  Sporangia  scattered along veins on abaxial leaf surface, often intermixed with farina-producing glands, containing 64 spores.  Spores  yellow, tetrahedral, trilete, verrucose, equatorial flange absent.  Gametophytes  glabrous.  x  = 30.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate regions, North America, South America, Eurasia.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Parsley fern</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">rock-brake</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cliff-brake</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cryptogramme</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 8--11 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Alverson, E. R. 1989.  Cryptogramma cascadensis , a new parsley fern from western North America. Amer. Fern J. 79: 95--102.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 1–1.5 mm diam., creeping, few-branched; leaves scattered along stems, delicate and ephemeral; petioles mostly dark brown in proximal 1/2–2/3, greenish distally; often in calcareous habits.</description>
      <determination>1 Cryptogramma stelleri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 4–20 mm diam., decumbent to erect, many branched from base; leaves strongly tufted, herbaceous to somewhat leathery, present throughout growing season; petioles dark brown in proximal 1/8 or less; mostly of noncalcareous habitats.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades herbaceous, thin, translucent when dried, shed in autumn, not persistent; hydathodes on dried leaves superficial; hairs absent from adaxial leaf surface.</description>
      <determination>2 Cryptogramma cascadensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades somewhat leathery, opaque when dried, green and persistent over winter; hydathodes on dried leaves sunken below surface; hairs small, appressed, cylindric, present in grooves of petiole, costae, and costules of adaxial leaf surface.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Segments oblong to ovate-lanceolate, with 6–12 or more teeth or shallow lobes; sterile leaves 2–3-pinnate.</description>
      <determination>3 Cryptogramma acrostichoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Segments obovate, with 2–6 deep lobes; at least some sterile leaves 3–4-pinnate.</description>
      <determination>4 Cryptogramma sitchensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
