<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Warren H. Wagner Jr. , Florence S. Wagner</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Agardh" date="unknown">ophioglossaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1801">Botrychium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(2): 8, 110. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ophioglossaceae;genus Botrychium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin botry, bunch (of grapes), and - oides, like; in reference to the sporangial clusters]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Roots  occasionally branching laterally, yellowish to black, 0.5--2 mm diam., smooth or with corky ridges, not proliferous.  Stems  upright, forming caudex to 5 mm thick; gemmae absent or minute, spheric.  Trophophores  ascending to perpendicular to stem, sessile or stalked; blades linear, oblong, or deltate, simple to 5-pinnate, 4--25 × 1--35 cm.  Pinnae  (reduced to segments in many species) spreading to ascending, fan-shaped to lanceolate to linear; margins entire to dentate to lacerate, apex rounded or acute; veins free, arranged like ribs of fan or pinnate.  Sporophores  normally 1 per leaf, 1--3-pinnate, long-stalked, borne at ground level to high on common stalk.  Sporangial clusters  with sporangia sessile to short-stalked, almost completely exposed, borne in 2 rows on pinnate (except in very small plants) sporophore branches.  Gametophytes  broadly ovate, unbranched, 1--3 × 1--10 mm.  x =44, 45, 92.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Grapefern</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">moonwort</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">botryche</other_name>
  <discussion>The greatest diversity in Botrychium is at high latitudes and high elevations, mostly in disturbed meadows and woods. Extensive field and laboratory research has revealed unexpected diversity in North America, especially in subg. Botrychium . For accurate identification, a substantial number of carefully spread and pressed leaves are usually needed because of the large amount of variation found in most species. Taking many samples will have little effect on the population as long as the underground shoots and roots are left intact. Approximately a dozen sterile hybrid combinations have been encountered, but they are very infrequent.</discussion>
  <discussion>The range maps south of Canada reflect mostly local occurrences at high elevations (1000--3700 m) in the mountains. The ranges for many of the species are probably more extensive and continuous than indicated by our present knowledge.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 50--60 (30 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Clausen, R.T. 1938. A monograph of the Ophioglossaceae. Mem. Torrey Bot. Club. 19(2): 1--177.</reference>
    <reference>Wagner, F. S. 1993. Chromosomes of North American grapeferns and moonworts (Ophioglossaceae:  Botrychium ). Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 19: 83--92.</reference>
    <reference>Wagner, W.H. Jr. and F.S. Wagner. 1983. Genus communities as a systematic tool in the study of New World  Botrychium  (Ophioglossaceae). Taxon 32: 51--63.</reference>
    <reference>Wagner, W.H. Jr. and F.S. Wagner. 1990. Moonworts ( Botrychium  subg.  Botrychium ) of the upper Great Lakes region. Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 17: 313--325.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades deltate, mostly 5--25 cm, commonly sterile, sporophores absent or misshapen; plants mostly over 12 cm; leaf sheaths open or closed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades mainly oblong to linear, mostly 2--4 cm, all fertile, sporophores always present; plants to 15 cm, mostly less than 10 cm; leaf sheaths closed (subg. Botrychium).</description>
      <next_statement_id>9</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blade thin, herbaceous; leaf sheaths open; sporophores, when present, arising from base of trophophore blade high on common stalk; leaves absent during winter (subg. Osmundopteris).</description>
      <determination>1 Botrychium virginianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades herbaceous or thick-papery to leathery; leaf sheaths closed; sporophores, when present, arising near ground from basal portion of common stalk; leaves present during winter (subg. Sceptridium).</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores prostrate, blades commonly 2 per plant; roots yellowish, to 30 per plant; sporophore stalks and midrib broadly flattened, fleshy; leaves dying in early spring, new leaves appearing in late fall (sect. Hiemobotrychium).</description>
      <determination>2 Botrychium lunarioides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores erect or ascending, blades commonly 1 per plant; roots blackish, to 15 per plant; sporophore stalks and midrib only slightly flattened, not fleshy; leaves appearing in late spring and lasting until following spring (subg. Sceptridium sect. Sceptridium).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal pinnae mostly long-stalked and remotely alternate; pinnule venation nearly like ribs of fan but with short midrib; blades dull gray-green.</description>
      <determination>5 Botrychium jenmanii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal pinnae short-stalked and mostly subopposite; pinnule venation pinnate, with strong midrib; blades bluish green or green to dark green.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Terminal pinnules larger than lateral pinnules; pinnae undivided except in proximal 1/2--3/4.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Terminal pinnules similar to or only slightly larger than lateral pinnules; pinnae divided to tip.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades usually 2--3-pinnate, terminal pinnae elongate and nearly parallel-sided; leaves mostly remaining green during winter.</description>
      <determination>3 Botrychium biternatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades usually 2--4-pinnate, pinnules trowel-shaped or ovate (rarely linear), apex rounded to acute; leaves green or bronze during winter.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnules obliquely ovate, margins finely denticulate to crenulate, apex rounded to acute; trophophore blades green in winter.</description>
      <determination>7 Botrychium oneidense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnules obliquely trowel-shaped or linear, margins denticulate to lacerate or coarsely cut, apex acute; trophophore blades bronze in winter if exposed.</description>
      <determination>4 Botrychium dissectum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Segments of blades rounded, nearly entire, plane; texture leathery; n North America.</description>
      <determination>6 Botrychium multifidum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Segments of blades angular, ± dentate, somewhat channeled and concave abaxially; texture semiherbaceous; Great Lakes and St. Lawrence Seaway region.</description>
      <determination>8 Botrychium rugulosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores linear to linear-oblong, simple to lobed, lobes rounded to square and angular, stalks usually 1/3--2/3 length of trophophore; plants in deep shade under shrubs and trees.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores linear to deltate (narrowly oblong in Botrychium minganese), pinnate, rarely simple, lobes, if present, of various shapes, stalk usually less than 1/4 length of trophophore; plants usually in exposed sites.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Segments rounded; plants herbaceous.</description>
      <determination>29 Botrychium simplex</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Segments angular; plants succulent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Surfaces shiny yellow-green (alive); blade apex undissected or with 2--3 lobes, cutting fairly regular; trophophore stalks very succulent; Great Lakes region.</description>
      <determination>21 Botrychium mormo</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Surfaces dull gray-green (alive); blade apex dissected with 3--5 lobes or projections, cutting somewhat irregular; trophophore stalks somewhat succulent; far w North American mountains.</description>
      <determination>20 Botrychium montanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distance between 1st and 2d pinna pairs greater than that between 2d and 3d pairs; segments asymmetric, enlarged on acroscopic side.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distance between 1st and 2d pinna pairs same or slightly more than between 2d and 3d pairs; segments asymmetric to symmetric.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Apex of blade undivided or coarsely divided; pinnae ovate--fan-shaped, margins shallowly sinuate; small leaves frequently simple or nearly so; large mature blades subternate to ternate; sporophores 1-pinnate; nearly circumboreal.</description>
      <determination>29 Botrychium simplex</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Apex of blade always finely divided; pinnae fan-shaped to narrowly spatulate, margins crenate to dentate or jagged; small leaves always deeply lobed or pinnate; large mature blades oblong-linear; sporophores 2--3-pinnate; w Minnesota prairie.</description>
      <determination>14 Botrychium gallicomontanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores present; basal pinnae or segments with venation like ribs of fan, midrib absent; basal pinnae fan-shaped to spatulate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores present or replaced by sporophore; if present, basal pinnae or segment venation pinnate, midrib present, oblanceolate to linear to lanceolate to ovate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades ovate to deltate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades oblong to oblong-lanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporophores 3--5 times length of trophophores, arising at or just above leaf sheath; blades bright green, pinnae remote or approximate, fan-shaped, papery; widespread, w North America.</description>
      <determination>29 Botrychium simplex</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporophores 1--1.5 times length of trophophores, arising high on common stalk; blades dull whitish green, pinnae overlapping, cuneate, leathery; sw Oregon.</description>
      <determination>28 Botrychium pumicola</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal pinnae broadly fan-shaped.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal pinnae narrowly fan-shaped, or cuneate to lanceolate or linear.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants herbaceous; trophophores on most plants less than 4 × 1.5 cm; pinnae 2--5 pairs, well separated; margins commonly crenate to dentate; sporophores 1.3--3 times length of trophophore; damp sites; w North America.</description>
      <determination>12 Botrychium crenulatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants fleshy; trophophores on most plants more than 5 × 2 cm; pinnae 4--9 pairs, approximate to overlapping; margins usually entire to undulate, rarely dentate; sporophores 0.8--2 times length of trophophore; dry sites; widespread.</description>
      <determination>17 Botrychium lunaria</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae strongly ascending; margins conspicuously dentate-lacerate.</description>
      <determination>10 Botrychium ascendens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae spreading or only moderately ascending; outer margins entire to crenate or rarely dentate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores ± folded longitudinally when alive, usually to 4 × 1 cm; pinnae to 5 pairs, most proximal pinnae 2-lobed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophores flat or folded only at base when alive, usually to 10 × 2.5 cm; pinnae to 10 pairs, basal pinnae unlobed or if lobed, not usually 2-cleft.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades very fleshy; sporophores usually less than 1.5 times length of trophophores; pinnae mostly linear; basal pinna lobes usually ± equal; appearing in spring.</description>
      <determination>11 Botrychium campestre</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades herbaceous; sporophores usually 1.5--4 times length of trophophores; pinnae asymmetrically fan-shaped; basal pinna lobes unequal; appearing in late spring.</description>
      <determination>22 Botrychium pallidum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades narrowly oblong, firm to herbaceous; pinnae nearly spheric to fan-shaped; margins shallowly crenate; proximal sporophore branches 1-pinnate.</description>
      <determination>19 Botrychium minganense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades narrowly deltate, leathery; pinnae spatulate to linear-spatulate; margins entire to very coarsely and irregularly dentate; most proximal sporophore branches usually 2-pinnate.</description>
      <determination>30 Botrychium spathulatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore replaced by sporophore, yielding 2 sporophores.</description>
      <determination>23 Botrychium paradoxum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore present, fully distinct from sporophore.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades deltate; sporophores divided proximally into several equally long branches.</description>
      <determination>16 Botrychium lanceolatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore blades ovate to oblong (nearly deltate in Botrychium hesperium, deltate-oblong in B. pinnatum); sporophores with single midrib or 1 dominant midrib and 2 smaller ribs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore stalk long, equal to length of trophophore rachis; blade mostly ovate-oblong to deltate-oblong; basal pinnae ovate-rhombic; nw North America.</description>
      <determination>24 Botrychium pedunculosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trophophore stalk short to nearly absent, to 1/4 length of trophophore rachis; blade mainly oblong-lanceolate to triangular; most basal pinnae elongate, oblanceolate to oblong to linear or linear-lanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Large trophophore blades nearly deltate, basal pinna pair elongate; pinnae distal to basal pair approximate to overlapping; segments and lobes rounded at apex.</description>
      <determination>15 Botrychium hesperium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Large trophophore blades mostly oblong-deltate to ovate-oblong; basal pinna pair not elongate; pinnae distal to basal pair remote to approximate; segments and lobes truncate, rounded, or acute at apex.</description>
      <next_statement_id>27</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporophores long, 1--3 times length of trophophore; blades dull, blue to green.</description>
      <next_statement_id>28</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporophores short, only 1--2 times length of trophophore; blades shiny, bright green.</description>
      <next_statement_id>29</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae ovate to lanceolate, blunt, shallowly to deeply lobed.</description>
      <determination>18 Botrychium matricariifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae oblanceolate to linear-lanceolate, acuminate, entire to shallowly lobed.</description>
      <determination>9 Botrychium acuminatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae acute, oblanceolate to narrowly spatulate, rarely more than 2-lobed; pinnae well separated.</description>
      <determination>13 Botrychium echo</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae mostly with rounded apex, ovate to broadly spatulate, to 6-lobed; pinnae approximate to overlapping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>30</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of mature trophophores nearly as wide as long, with slightly pointed tips, costa rudimentary, veins otherwise ± like ribs of fan; basal pinnae with only shallow, narrow sinuses and 1--3 lobes.</description>
      <determination>26 Botrychium boreale</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of mature trophophores considerably longer than wide, mostly with blunt tips, veins mainly pinnate; basal pinnae with deep, ± wide sinuses and 3--8 lobes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>31</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae ascending, usually somewhat overlapping; trophophore blades leathery, somewhat shiny; Lake Superior region.</description>
      <determination>27 Botrychium pseudopinnatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae ± ascending to ± horizontal, usually approximate to somewhat remote; trophophore blades papery, shiny; nw North America.</description>
      <determination>25 Botrychium pinnatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
