<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Haufler &amp; Windham" date="1991">appalachianum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>81: 18. 1991</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus polypodium;species appalachianum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  often whitish pruinose, slender, to 6 mm diam., acrid-tasting; scales concolored to weakly bicolored, uniformly golden brown or slightly darker near apex, lanceolate, contorted distally, margins denticulate.  Leaves  to 40 cm.  Petiole  slender, ± 1.5 mm diam.  Blade  elongate-deltate, rarely oblong, pinnatifid, usually widest at or near base, to 9 cm wide, herbaceous to somewhat leathery; rachis sparsely scaly to glabrescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially; scales lanceolate-ovate, usually more than 6 cells wide.  Segments  linear to oblong, less than 8 mm wide, margins entire to crenulate; apex acute to narrowly rounded; midrib glabrous adaxially.  Venation  free.  Sori  midway between margin and midrib to nearly marginal, less than 3 mm diam., circular when immature.  Sporangiasters  present, usually more than 40 per sorus, heads densely covered with glandular hairs.  Spores  less than 52 µm, verrucose, projections less than 3 µm tall. 2 n  = 74.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Cliffs and rocky slopes, on a variety of substrates;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="cliffs and rocky slopes , on a variety of substrates ;" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.B., Nfld., N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que.; Ala., Conn., Del., D.C., Ga., Ky., Maine, Md., Mass., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., R.I., S.C., Tenn., Vt., Va., W.Va.</description>
  <number>7</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Appalachian polypody</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">polypode des Appalaches</other_name>
  <discussion>Polypodium appalachianum is a newly recognized species traditionally identified as the diploid cytotype of P . virginianum (A. M. Evans 1971; I. Manton and M. Shivas 1953). Because the tetraploid cytotype is an allopolyploid (C. H. Haufler and Wang Z. R. 1991), and the type specimen of P . virginianum is tetraploid (R. Cranfill and D. M. Britton 1983), the diploid is recognized here as a distinct species, P . appalachianum . Some collections of P . appalachianum can be difficult to distinguish from P . virginianum , but the latter species has spores averaging more than 52 µm, and P . appalachianum has spores less than 52 µm. Frequent hybridization between P . appalachianum and P . virginianum forms morphologically intermediate, triploid individuals with misshapen spores. Particularly confusing is the frequent occurrence of the triploid sympatric with only one parent or with neither parent nearby.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
