<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Presl &amp; C. Presl" date="unknown">polypodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Suksdorf" date="1927">amorphum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Werdenda</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 16. 1927</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polypodiaceae;genus polypodium;species amorphum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="F. A. Lang" date="unknown">montense</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polypodium;species montense;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  often whitish pruinose, slender, to 6 mm diam., acrid-tasting; scales weakly bicolored, lanceolate, contorted distally, bases and margins light brown, sometimes with dark central stripe, margins often coarsely dentate.  Leaves  to 30 cm.  Petiole  slender, to 1.5 mm diam.  Blade  oblong to rarely deltate, pinnatifid, usually widest near middle, occasionally at or near base, to 4 cm wide, somewhat leathery; rachis sparsely scaly to glabrescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially; scales lanceolate-ovate, usually more than 6 cells wide.  Segments  oblong, less than 12 mm wide; margins entire to crenulate; apex rounded to broadly acute; midrib glabrous adaxially.  Venation  free.  Sori  midway between margin and midrib to nearly marginal, less than 3 mm diam., circular when immature.  Sporangiasters  present, usually less than 40 per sorus, heads covered with glandular hairs.  Spores  more than 58 µm, rugose to verrucose, surface projections less than 3 µm tall. 2 n  = 74.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Cliffs and rocky slopes, usually on igneous substrates;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="cliffs and rocky slopes , on igneous substrates ;" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Oreg., Wash.</description>
  <number>10</number>
  <discussion>The diploid Polypodium amorphum is one of the progenitors of allotetraploid P . hesperium , and these two species are occasionally sympatric. Although P . amorphum can be mistaken for P . hesperium , consistent differences exist for separating these two species (see comments under P . hesperium ). Hybridization between P . amorphum and P . hesperium results in triploid individuals with misshapen spores (F. A. Lang 1971).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
