<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">lycopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Holub" date="1964">Phlegmariurus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Preslia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 17, 21. 1964</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family lycopodiaceae;genus Phlegmariurus</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[based on epithet of Lycopodium phlegmaria ; Greek phlegma, flame, and oura, tail; in reference to the tasslelike fertile portions of the plant]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic or terrestrial, pendent [erect].  Roots  produced in distal parts of shoots, migrating downward in cortex to emerge in substrate.  Horizontal stems  absent [present].  Shoots  clustered, round in cross section, dichotomously branching, 1.5--5 mm diam.  Leaves  not in distinct ranks [ranked], imbricate or not, monomorphic (or sporophylls sometimes differentiated), appressed, ascending to spreading, linear to subulate, margins mostly entire [denticulate].  Gemmiferous branchlets and gemmae  absent.  Sporangia  reniform, borne individually in axils of undifferentiated or slightly differentiated sporophylls [differentiated sporophylls in strobili].  Spores  pitted to small-grooved, sides at equator convex and angles acute.  Gametophytes  nonphotosynthetic, mycorrhizal, mainly growing buried in humus on trees, branched, paraphysate with uniseriate hairs; ring meristem absent.  x  = 68.</description>
  <description type="distribution">in tropical areas worldwide.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hanging fir-moss</other_name>
  <discussion>As construed here, Phlegmariurus is very large and diverse. Many groups have been tentatively suggested in this genus (B. Øllgaard 1987). Some of these ultimately may be recognized as subgenera or even genera.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species over 300 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
