<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">marsileaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">marsilea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Engelmann ex A. Braun in Kunze" date="1848">macropoda</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in Kunze,Amer. J. Sci. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>ser. 2, 6: 88. 1848</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family marsileaceae;genus marsilea;species macropoda</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  forming dense clones.  Roots  arising at nodes.  Petioles  5--39 cm, hairy.  Pinnae  9--35 × 8--39 mm, conspicuously white hairy abaxially, hairy adaxially; hairs often exceeding margin to make pinnae appear white margined from above.  Sporocarp stalks  erect, frequently branched, attached 2--4.5 mm above base of petiole; unbranched stalks or ultimate branches of stalks 8--17 mm; common trunk of branched stalks 1--5 mm (rarely 2--3 unbranched stalks attached separately to same petiole).  Sporocarps  strongly ascending, 6--9 × 4.5--5.5 mm, 2 mm thick, elliptic or quadrate in lateral view, covered with matted or twisted hairs; raphe 1.6--2.4 mm, proximal tooth 0.4--0.5 mm, blunt, distal tooth absent or present as slightly raised area.  Sori  19--23.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporocarps produced nearly year-round (Feb--Nov).</description>
  <description type="habitat">On mud and in shallow water, locally abundant in clay soils of ditches, ponds, marshes;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., La., Tex.; Mexico.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <discussion>Marsilea macropoda is introduced in Alabama and Louisiana.</discussion>
  <discussion>Marsilea macropoda , with its tall, hairy leaves and branched sporocarp stalks, is a striking and distinctive species, worthy of cultivation. It is sympatric with M . vestita over much of its range, and individuals that appear to be hybrids have been collected in Blanco, Brazos, and Kleberg counties in Texas. These plants combine the large hairy leaves of M . macropoda with the shorter-stalked sporocarps bearing a superior tooth found in M . vestita .</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
