<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Garrie P. Landry</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Horianow" date="unknown">zamiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family zamiaceae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  superficially palmlike or fernlike, perennial, evergreen, dioecious.  Stems  subterranean with exposed apex or aboveground, fleshy, stout, cylindric, simple or irregularly branched.  Roots  with small secondary roots; coral-like roots developing at base of stem at or below soil surface.  Leaves  pinnately compound, spirally clustered at stem apex, leathery, petiole and rachis unarmed [with stout spines]; leaflets entire or dentate [spinose], venation dichotomous [netted]; resin canals absent.  Cones  axillary, appearing terminal, short-peduncled [sessile], disintegrating at maturity; sporophylls densely crowded, spirally arranged, often covered with indument.  Pollen cones  soon shed, generally smaller and more numerous than seed cones; sporophylls bearing many crowded, small microsporangia (pollen sacs) adaxially; pollen spheric, not winged.  Seed cones  persistent for a year or more, 1(--2) per plant, nearly globose to ovoid, tapering sharply or blunt at apex; sporophylls peltate, thickened and laterally expanded distally, bearing 2(--3) ovules.  Seeds  angular, inner coat hardened, outer coat fleshy, often brightly colored; cotyledons 2.</description>
  <description type="distribution">primarily tropical to warm temperate regions, North Americ, Central America, South America, Africa, Australia.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sago-palm Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 9, species ca. 100 (1 genus, 1 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Candolle, A. L. P. de. 1868. Cycadaceae. In: A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. de Candolle, eds. 1823--1873. Prodromus Systematis Naturalis Regni Vegetabilis.... Paris etc. Vol. 16, part 2, pp. 522--547.</reference>
    <reference>Johnson, L. A. S. 1959. The families of cycads and the Zamiaceae of Australia. Proc. Linn. Soc. New South Wales 84: 64--117.</reference>
    <reference>Schuster, J. 1932. Cycadaceae. In: H. G. A. Engler, ed. 1900--1953. Das Pflanzenreich.... Berlin. Vol. 99[IV,1], pp. l--168.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
