<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Warren H. Wagner Jr.</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Kaulfuss" date="unknown">Schizaeaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Schizaeaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial or epiphytic.  Roots  numerous.  Stems  mainly erect, covered with many stiff hairs 1--3 cells long, with simple siphonostele (hollow vascular cylinder).  Leaves  tufted, monomorphic or dimorphic.  Petioles  much longer than blades, blades reduced to tiny apical fistlike or radiating groups of rudimentary fertile pinnae ("digits").  Petioles  sometimes repeatedly dichotomous, in some species webbed between branches to form fan-shaped false blades.  Sporangia  arranged in 1--4 ranks on abaxial surface of digits with revolute margins.  Annulus  subapical, composed of 1--(2--3) layer(s) of thickened cells.  Gametophytes  subterranean and not green or borne aboveground and green, tuberlike or flattened, cordate or filamentous.  Spores  bilateral, monolete.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, mainly in tropical areas.</description>
  <number>9</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Curly Grass Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 2--3, species 30 (2 genera, 2 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bierhorst, D. W. 1971. Morphology of Vascular Plants. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Nauman, C. E. 1987. Schizaeaceae in Florida. Sida 12: 69--74.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fertile blades pinnate, segments arising along rachis on distal 3--10 mm; sterile leaves curling.</description>
      <determination>1 Schizaea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fertile blades falsely digitate, segments appearing to arise at single point; sterile leaves absent.</description>
      <determination>2 Actinostachys</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
