<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Jermy" date="1986">tetragonostachys</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. A. Eaton" date="1899">cinerascens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fern Bull.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 33. 1899</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus tetragonostachys;species cinerascens</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial, forming loose to compact mats.  Stems  creeping, not readily fragmenting, upperside and underside structurally slightly different, irregularly forked, without budlike arrested branches, tips straight; main stem indeterminate, lateral branches determinate, ascending, 1--2-forked.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems, throughout stem length, (0.17--)0.2--0.3 mm diam.  Leaves  monomorphic, not in defined pseudowhorls, loosely appressed, ascending, green, linear-lanceolate, (1--)2.5--3 X (0.25--)0.4--0.6 mm (leaves in secondary and tertiary branches smaller); abaxial ridges inconspicuous; base rounded and adnate or cuneate and slightly decurrent, glabrous, seldom pubescent; margins short-ciliate, cilia transparent, scattered, ascending, 0.02--0.75 mm; apex plane, blunt, acute to slightly acuminate (not distinctly bristled).  Strobili  solitary, 2--4 mm; sporophylls deltate-ovate to lanceolate-ovate, abaxial ridges not prominent, base glabrous, margins short-ciliate, apex not keeled, acute.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Dry open places of clay soil, clayey-sandy soil, or in shade under shrubs and trees;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="dry open places" constraint="of clay soil , clayey-sandy soil , or in shade under shrubs and trees" />
        <character name="habitat" value="clay soil" />
        <character name="habitat" value="clayey-sandy soil" />
        <character name="habitat" value="shade" />
        <character name="habitat" value="shrubs" />
        <character name="habitat" value="trees" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.; Mexico in Baja California.</description>
  <number>18</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Gray spike-moss</other_name>
  <discussion>The light brown and grayish mats, short lateral branches, narrow stem, and short strobili distinguish Selaginella cinerascens from all other species in the flora, in which it has no close relatives. R. M. Tryon (1955) related S . cinerascens to S . arsenei Weatherby from Mexico. Selaginella cinerascens also closely resembles S . nivea Alston from Madagascar. In California S . cinerascens is known only from San Diego County.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
