<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1806">cheilanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker" date="1852">lindheimeri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Fil.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 101, plate 107a. 1852</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cheilanthes;species lindheimeri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Myriopteris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hooker) J. Smith" date="unknown">lindheimeri</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Myriopteris;species lindheimeri;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  long-creeping, 0.7--3 mm diam.; scales uniformly brown, ovate-lanceolate, straight to slightly contorted, loosely appressed, often deciduous on older portions of stem.  Leaves  scattered, 7--30 cm; vernation noncircinate.  Petiole  usually dark brown, rounded adaxially.  Blade  oblong-lanceolate to ovate-deltate, 4-pinnate at base, 2--5 cm wide; rachis rounded adaxially, with scattered linear-lanceolate scales and sparse monomorphic pubescence.  Pinnae  not articulate, dark color of stalk continuing into pinna base, basal pair not conspicuously larger than adjacent pair, usually equilateral, appearing densely tomentose adaxially.  Costae  green adaxially for most of length; abaxial scales multiseriate, lanceolate-ovate, truncate to cordate at base, usually without overlapping basal lobes, conspicuous, the largest 0.4--1 mm wide, strongly imbricate, often concealing ultimate segments, long-ciliate throughout, cilia fine, curly, forming entangled mass.  Ultimate segments  round to slightly oblong, beadlike, the largest 0.7--1 mm, abaxially nearly glabrous, often with a few small scales or branched hairs, adaxially appearing tomentose but actually nearly glabrous.  False indusia  marginal, weakly differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  ± continuous around segment margins.  Sporangia  containing 32 spores.  n  = 2 n  = 90, apogamous.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Rocky slopes and ledges, on a variety of acidic to mildly basic substrates;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="rocky slopes" constraint="on a variety of acidic to mildly basic substrates" />
        <character name="habitat" value="ledges" constraint="on a variety of acidic to mildly basic substrates" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">200--2500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex., Tex.; Mexico.</description>
  <number>11</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Fairy swords</other_name>
  <discussion>Cheilanthes lindheimeri is an apogamous triploid of unknown parentage. It is occasionally misidentified as C . wootonii (actually the element here recognized as C . yavapensis ); most specimens can be placed using the characteristics given in the key. The adaxial blade surface appears to be densely gray tomentose, but this is an illusion created by the fine, curly cilia of the abaxial costal scales that overtop the minute ultimate segments and form an entangled mass that prevents the easy removal of individual costal scales.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
