<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Jermy" date="1986">tetragonostachys</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Maxon" date="1920">leucobryoides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Misc. Collect.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>75: 8. 1920</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus tetragonostachys;species leucobryoides</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  on rock, forming rounded cushionlike mats.  Stems  decumbent to short-creeping, dry stems readily fragmenting; irregularly forked, without budlike arrested branches, tips straight; main stem upperside and underside structurally slightly different, inconspicuously indeterminate, lateral branches radially symmetric, determinate, strongly ascending, 1-forked.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems, throughout stem length, 0.2--0.35 mm diam.  Leaves  monomorphic, ± in alternate pseudowhorls of 4, tightly appressed, ascending, green, linear-oblong to linear-lanceolate, sometimes falcate on lateral rows (on main stem), 2--4.5 X 0.5--0.65 mm (usually smaller on young ascending branches); abaxial ridges present; base cuneate and decurrent (rounded and adnate on young branches), glabrous; margins short-ciliate, cilia transparent, scattered, spreading at base to ascending and dentiform toward apex, 0.07--0.15 mm; apex slightly attenuate and bristled or obtuse and abruptly bristled; bristle whitish or transparent, puberulent, 0.2--0.6 mm.  Strobili  solitary, 0.4--1.5 cm; sporophylls deltate-ovate or lanceolate, abaxial ridges moderately defined, base glabrous, margins short-ciliate to denticulate, apex acuminate with very short bristle.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>In rock crevices or on exposed rock;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="in rock crevices on exposed rock ;" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">800--2800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., Calif., Nev.</description>
  <number>24</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Mojave spike-moss</other_name>
  <discussion>Selaginella leucobryoides has very tightly intertwined stems that readily fragment, a characteristic shared with S . utahensis and S . asprella . Selaginella leucobryoides is very closely related to, and difficult to separate from, S . utahensis (see discussion).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
