<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">lycopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Holub" date="1983">Pseudolycopodiella</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Folia Geobot. Phytotax.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 441. 1983</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family lycopodiaceae;genus Pseudolycopodiella</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Green pseudo-, false, and Latin -ella, diminutive, meaning false little Lycopodium, because of its resemblance to Lycopodiella ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  creeping on wet substrates.  Roots  emerging immediately on underside of stems.  Horizontal stems  on substrate surface, short-creeping.  Upright shoots  not branched, forming sparsely leafy peduncles scattered along horizontal stem, nearly naked, 9--11 mm diam.  Leaves  of horizontal stems not in distinct ranks, not imbricate, dimorphic, margins entire; lateral leaves narrowly linear, nearly subulate, median leaves 1/2--2/3 shorter than lateral leaves, ascending.  Gemmiferous branchlets and gemmae  absent.  Strobili  solitary, not conspicuously differentiated from peduncle, tip blunt; peduncle nearly naked with scattered minute leaves, 0.9--3 mm diam.; sporophylls much shorter than peduncle leaves.  Sporangia  reniform.  Spores  rugulate, sides at equator convex, angles acute.  Gametophytes  photosynthetic, on substrate surface, tuber-shaped and lobed; ring meristem absent.  x  = 35.</description>
  <description type="distribution">widespread.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <discussion>Species 12 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bruce, J. G. 1976. Comparative studies of  Lycopodium carolinianum . Amer. Fern J. 66: 125--137.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
