<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">abies</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Miller" date="1768">balsamea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict., ed. 8</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>Abies no. 3. 1768</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus abies;species balsamea</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">balsamea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1002. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species balsamea;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 23m; trunk to 0.6m diam.; crown spirelike.  Bark  gray, thin, smooth, in age often becoming broken into irregular brownish scales.  Branches  diverging from trunk at right angles, the lower often spreading and drooping; twigs mostly opposite, greenish brown, pubescence sparse.  Buds  hidden by leaves or exposed, brown, conic, small, resinous, apex acute; basal scales short, broad, nearly equilaterally triangular, glabrous, resinous, margins entire, apex sharp-pointed.  Leaves  1.2--2.5cm × 1.5--2mm, 1-ranked (particularly on lower branches) to spiraled, flexible; cross section flat, grooved adaxially; odor pinelike (copious ß-pinene); abaxial surface with (4--)6--7(--8) stomatal rows on each side of midrib; adaxial surface dark green, slightly or not glaucous, with 0--3 stomatal rows at midleaf, these more numerous toward leaf apex; apex slightly notched to rounded; resin canals large, ± median, away from margins, midway between abaxial and adaxial epidermal layers.  Pollen cones  at pollination red, purplish, bluish, greenish, or orange.  Seed cones  cylindric, 4--7 × 1.5--3cm, gray-purple, turning brown before scale shed, sessile, apex round to obtuse; scales ca. 1--l.5 × 0.7--1.7cm (relationship reversed in more western collections), pubescent; bracts included or exserted and reflexed over scales.  Seeds  3--6 × 2--3mm, body brown; wing about twice as long as body, brown-purple; cotyledons ca. 4. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Boreal and northern forests;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="boreal forests" />
        <character name="habitat" value="northern forests" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1700m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">St. Pierre and Miquelon; Alta., Man., N.B., Nfld., N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask.; Conn., Iowa, Maine, Mass., Mich., Minn., N.H., N.Y., Pa., Vt., Va., W.Va., Wis.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Balsam fir</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sapin baumler</other_name>
  <discussion>Balsam fir is frequently segregated into two varieties (e.g., H.J. Scoggan 1978--1979) based on whether the bracts are included (var. balsamea ) or exserted (var. phanerolepis Fernald), the latter considered by Liu T. S. (1971) to be a hybrid between Abies balsamea and A . fraseri . D.T. Lester (1968) demonstrated, however, that bract length may vary within a cone, annually, and from tree to tree. Nevertheless, a tendency exists for the exserted variety to be found most commonly from Newfoundland south through New England (R.C. Hosie 1969; B.F. Jacobs et al. 1984); it is not found west of Ontario. Western populations lack 3-carene and have other minor chemical differences separating them from eastern balsam fir (E.Zavarin and K.Snajberk 1972; R.S. Hunt and E.von Rudloff 1974). Morphologic variation in balsam fir has been studied mainly east of Ontario; the populations to the west have been ignored for the most part, although they may yield stronger evidence for species subdivision.</discussion>
  <discussion>In Alberta, populations intermediate between western Abies balsamea and A . bifolia (E.H. Moss 1953; R.S. Hunt and E.von Rudloff 1974, 1979) may be classified as A . balsamea × bifolia . In West Virginia and Virginia, populations of balsam fir tend to be more similar to A . fraseri than are more northern populations (B.F. Jacobs et al. 1984).</discussion>
  <discussion>Balsam fir ( Abies balsamea ) is the provincial tree of New Brunswick.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Lester, D.T. 1968. Variation in cone morphology of balsam fir,  Abies balsamea . Rhodora 70: 83--94.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
