<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown" date="1810">woodsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Sprengel) Torrey" date="1840">obtusa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>New York State, Rep. Geol. Surv.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>195. 1840</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus woodsia;species obtusa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Sprengel" date="unknown">obtusum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Anleit. Kenntn. Gew.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 93. 1804</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polypodium;species obtusum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Woodsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Sprengel) Hooker &amp; Greville" date="unknown">perriniana</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Woodsia;species perriniana;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact to creeping, erect to horizontal, with few to many persistent petiole bases of unequal lengths; scales often uniformly brown but at least some bicolored with dark central stripe and pale brown margins, narrowly lanceolate.  Leaves  8--60 × 2.5--12 cm.  Petiole  light brown or straw-colored when mature, occasionally darker at very base, not articulate above base, relatively brittle and easily shattered.  Blade  lanceolate to ovate, 2-pinnate to 2-pinnate-pinnatifid proximally, moderately glandular, rarely somewhat viscid; many glandular hairs with thick stalks and distinctly bulbous tips; rachis with glandular hairs and scattered, often hairlike scales.  Pinnae  ovate-deltate to elliptic, longer than wide, abruptly tapered to a rounded or broadly acute apex, occasionally attenuate; largest pinnae with 5--14 pairs of pinnules; abaxial and adaxial surfaces glandular, lacking nonglandular hairs or scales.  Pinnules  dentate, sometimes deeply lobed; margins nonlustrous, thin, with occasional glands, lacking cilia or translucent projections.  Vein tips  usually enlarged to form whitish hydathodes visible adaxially.  Indusia  of relatively broad, nonfilamentous segments, these multiseriate throughout, composed of ± isodiametric cells, entire or glandular along distal edge, concealed by or slightly surpassing mature sporangia.  Spores  averaging 35--47 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">only in the flora.</description>
  <number>7</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Blunt-lobed cliff fern</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">woodsie à lobes arrondis</other_name>
  <discussion>Woodsia obtusa comprises two cytotypes that are treated here as subspecies because they show subtle morphologic and ecological distinctions and tend to have different distributions. Tetraploid populations (subsp. obtusa ) are found throughout the eastern flora, commonly occurring on limestone. The diploid (subsp. occidentalis ) is found near the western edge of the species range, usually on sandstone and granitic substrates. Isozyme studies suggest that subsp. obtusa may have been derived from subsp. occidentalis through autopolyploidy (M. D. Windham 1993). The westernmost collections of Woodsia obtusa (all subsp. occidentalis ) come from the Wichita Mountains of Oklahoma and the Edwards Plateau of Texas. Reports of this species from the trans-Pecos region of western Texas are apparently based on misidentifications.</discussion>
  <discussion>Subspecies 2:</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spores averaging 42-47 µm; proximal pinnules of lower pinnae usually shallowly lobed or merely dentate; blades coarsely cut and evidently 2-pinnate; stems compact to short-creeping, individual branches usually 5-10 mm diam.</description>
      <determination>7a subsp. obtusa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spores averaging 35-42 µm; proximal pinnules of lower pinnae usually deeply lobed or pinnatifid; blades finely cut, 2-pinnate-pinnatifid; stems short- to long-creeping, individual branches 3-5 mm diam.</description>
      <determination>7b subsp. occidentalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
