<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Kathleen M. Pryer</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Newman" date="1851">Gymnocarpium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 371. 1851</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Gymnocarpium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek gymnos, naked, and karpos, fruit, referring to the absence of indusia]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Stems  long-creeping, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, dying back in winter.  Petiole  ca. 1.5--3 times length of blade, base not swollen; vascular bundles 2, lateral, ± oblong in cross section.  Blade  broadly deltate, ternate, or ovate, 2--3-pinnate-pinnatifid, reduced distally to pinnatifid apex, herbaceous.  Pinnae  weakly articulate to rachis but persistent, segment margins entire to crenate; proximal pinnae longest, petiolulate, usually ± inequilateral with pinnules on basiscopic side longer than those on acroscopic side; costae adaxially grooved, grooves not continuous from rachis to costae; indument lacking or of minute (0.1 mm) glands abaxially and sometimes along costae adaxially.  Veins  free, simple or forked.  Sori  in 1 row between midrib and margin, ± round; indusia absent.  Spores  brownish, rugose.  x  = 40.</description>
  <description type="distribution">north temperate regions, North America, Eurasia.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Oak fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 8 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Pryer, K. M. 1992. The status of  Gymnocarpium heterosporum  and  G .  robertianum  in Pennsylvania. Amer. Fern J. 82: 34--39.</reference>
    <reference>Pryer, K. M. and D. M. Britton. 1983. Spore studies in the genus  Gymnocarpium . Canad. J. Bot. 61: 377--388.</reference>
    <reference>Pryer, K. M., D. M. Britton, and J. McNeill. 1983. A numerical analysis of chromatographic profiles in North American taxa of the fern genus  Gymnocarpium . Canad. J. Bot. 61: 2592--2602.</reference>
    <reference>Pryer, K. M. and C. H. Haufler. 1993. Isozymic and chromosomal evidence for the allotetraploid origin of  Gymnocarpium dryopteris  (Dryopteridaceae). Syst. Bot. 18: 150--172.</reference>
    <reference>Sarvela, J. 1978. A synopsis of the fern genus  Gymnocarpium . Ann. Bot. Fenn. 15: 101--106.</reference>
    <reference>Sarvela, J., D. M. Britton, and K. M. Pryer. 1981. Studies on the  Gymnocarpium robertianum  complex in North America. Rhodora 83: 421--431.</reference>
    <reference>Wagner, W. H. Jr. 1966b. New data on North American oak ferns,  Gymnocarpium . Rhodora 68: 121--138.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial blade surface glabrous or moderately glandular, abaxial blade surface and rachis moderately or densely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Adaxial and abaxial blade surfaces and rachis essentially glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades glabrous on adaxial surface; proximal pinnae and basiscopic pinnules of proximal pinnae curving toward apex of leaf and apex of pinna, respectively; pinnae of 2d pair almost always sessile with basal pinnules ± equal in length to adjacent pinnules.</description>
      <determination>4a subsp. parvulum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades moderately glandular on adaxial surface; proximal pinnae and basiscopic pinnules of proximal pinnae ± perpendicular to rachis and costa, respectively; pinnae of 2d pair usually stalked, or if sessile with basal pinnules shorter than adjacent pinnules.</description>
      <determination>5 Gymnocarpium robertianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of 2d pair and basal basiscopic pinnule of proximal pinnae stalked.</description>
      <determination>1 Gymnocarpium appalachianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of 2d pair sessile or rarely stalked; proximal basiscopic pinnule of basal pinnae sessile.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of 2d pair sessile with basal pinnules unequal in length (basiscopic markedly longer); ultimate segments of proximal pinnae slightly lobed to crenate, apex often crenulate, acute; blades 8-24 cm.</description>
      <determination>2 Gymnocarpium disjunctum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of 2d pair rarely stalked, if sessile with basal pinnules ± equal in length (basiscopic = acroscopic); ultimate segments of proximal pinnae crenate to entire, apex entire, rounded; blades 3-14 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sessile basal basiscopic pinnule of proximal pinnae with basal basiscopic pinnulet (division of pinnule) ± equal in length to adjacent pinnulet; pinnae of 2d pair usually sessile, with basal pinnules ± equal in length to adjacent basal pinnule; spores 34-39 µm.</description>
      <determination>3 Gymnocarpium dryopteris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sessile basal basiscopic pinnule of proximal pinnae with basal basiscopic pinnulet shorter than adjacent pinnulet; pinnae of 2d pair sessile, with basal pinnules shorter than adjacent pinnule, or 2d basal pinnae rarely stalked; spores 27-31 µm.</description>
      <determination>1 Gymnocarpium appalachianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
