<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="H. Mason &amp; Stockwell" date="1945">washoensis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8: 62. 1945</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species washoensis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 60m; trunk to 1m diam., straight; crown pyramidal.  Bark  yellow-brown to reddish, fissured, plates scaly.  Branches  spreading-ascending; twigs stout, orangish, aging gray, rough.  Buds  ovoid, red-brown, 1.5--2cm, not resinous; scale margins fringed.  Leaves  (2--)3 per fascicle, spreading-ascending, persisting (2--)4--6(--7) years, 10--15cm × ca. 1.5mm, slightly twisted, gray-green, all surfaces with stomatal lines, margins finely serrulate, apex acuminate; sheath 1--2cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  cylindric, 10--20mm, red-purple.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter, not persistent, spreading, slightly asymmetric, ovoid-conic before opening, broadly ovoid when open, 7--10cm, tan or pale red-brown, sessile, abaxial surface of scales darker and sharply contrasting in color with adaxial surface; apophyses slightly raised, low pyramidal; umbo central, narrowly pyramidal, tapering into short, reflexed, fine prickle.  Seeds  ellipsoid; body ca. 0.8cm, gray-brown; wing to 16mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Dry montane forests;</description>
  <description type="elevation">2100--2500m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif., Nev.</description>
  <number>26</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Washoe pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus washoensis often occurs in large stands and resembles P . jeffreyi . The number and posture of seed-cone scales fall within the ranges given for P . jeffreyi . The abaxial surface of these scales has a significantly darker pigmentation, however; such a color contrast is not apparent in P . jeffreyi . Forest geneticists have developed hybrids between P . washoensis and related yellow pines, but no natural hybrids have been observed. Some workers regard P . washoensis as closely related to---or even conspecific with--- P . ponderosa .</discussion>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
