<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
    <other_info_on_meta type="mention_page">40</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="unknown">Selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus Selaginella</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  radially symmetric, not articulate; creeping stems with closely spaced, dichotomous forks; upright stems unbranched; vessel elements absent.  Rhizophores  absent.  Leaves  loosely spirally arranged, monomorphic, lanceolate to lanceolate-triangular, thin, soft; margins short-spiny; stomates scattered throughout abaxial surface; axillary leaves absent.  Strobili  solitary, cylindric.  Sporophylls  loosely spirally arranged, larger and slightly different shape from vegetative leaves, most sporophylls fertile, megasporophylls and microsporophylls same size, auricles absent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumboreal and Hawaii.</description>
  <number>1a</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Karrfalt, E. E. 1981. The comparative and developmental morphology of the root system of  Selaginella selaginoides  (L.) Link. Amer. J. Bot. 68: 224--253.</reference>
    <reference>Page, C. N. 1989. Compression and slingshot megaspore ejection in  Selaginella selaginoides ---A new phenomenon in pteridophytes. Fern Gaz. 13: 267--275.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on aerial stems dimorphic, arranged in 4 ranks (2 median, 2 lateral), axillary leaves present at branching points; rhizophores present. 1c. Selaginella subg. Stachygynandrum</description>
      <next_statement_id>1</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves on aerial stems monomorphic, not in distinct ranks, axillary leaves absent at branching points; rhizophores present or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Strobili cylindric; sporophylls spreading; leaves thin, soft, margins short-spiny; stomates throughout abaxial surface of leaf; rhizophores absent. 1a. Selaginella subg. Selaginella (S. selaginoides)</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Strobili quadrangular; sporophylls usually appressed; leaves thick or fleshy (seldom thin), firm, margins dentate, serrate, or ciliate (never spiny); stomates in abaxial groove; rhizophores present. 1b. Selaginella subg. Tetragonostachys</description>
      <next_statement_id>1</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
