<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Alan R. Smith</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Newman" date="unknown">grammitidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1802">Grammitis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(2): 3, 17. 1802</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grammitidaceae;genus Grammitis</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek gramme, line, alluding to the elongate sori in a few species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  often less than 15 cm [rarely more than 50 cm].  Blade  pinnatifid [simple to 1-pinnate or rarely more divided], bristly [or glabrous], glandless [or glandular]; setae dark reddish brown [to transparent].  Veins  simple or 1-forked [to pinnately veined] in each segment, free, ending in hydathodes adaxially.  Sori  round [to oval or elongate], not forming a coenosorus, not sunken; paraphyses absent [or present].  x  = 32, 33, 36, 37.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical, North America, South America, Asia, Africa, Pacific Islands, Australia.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <discussion>The total number of species is based on acceptance of a relatively broad circumscription. Our sole species belongs to the group (genus or subgenus) formerly called Xiphopteris , a name that is now treated as a synonym of Cochlidium (L. E. Bishop 1978). This group comprises perhaps 30 species and is defined by the following characteristics: stem scales not clathrate, often marginally bristly; veins simple or with a single acroscopic branch in each segment; blades linear, usually pinnatifid or pinnatisect; lack of a marginal black border around blade; one sorus per segment; and hydathodes present. It probably warrants generic status under the name Micropolypodium Hayata, a primarily neotropical genus with representatives in eastern Asia (Malaysia, China, Sikkim, Taiwan, and Japan).</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 300 or more (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bishop, L. E. 1978. Revision of the genus  Cochlidium  (Grammitidaceae). Amer. Fern J. 68: 76--94.</reference>
    <reference>Farrar, D. R. 1967. Gametophytes of four tropical fern genera reproducing independently of their sporophytes in the southern Appalachians. Science 155: 1266--1267.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
