<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="C. Presl" date="unknown">blechnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Smith" date="1745">woodwardia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) T. Moore" date="1857">areolata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Index Fil.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>45. 1857</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family blechnaceae;genus woodwardia;species areolata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Acrostichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">areolatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1069. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Acrostichum;species areolatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lorinseria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) C. Presl" date="unknown">areolata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lorinseria;species areolata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  long-creeping, slender; scales brown, many, broadly lanceolate.  Leaves  dimorphic, deciduous, few, well separated; sterile leaves 40-58 cm, fertile leaves 49-70 cm.  Petiole  reddish brown proximally, straw-colored distally; base not swollen, with sparsely set brown scales.  Blade  bright green, generally lanceolate, scaly-glandular upon emergence but soon glabrate; sterile leaves pinnatifid, 13-26 cm; fertile leaves pinnate, sharply contracted, 20-27 cm.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, arranged in 7-12 alternate pairs; sterile pinnae lanceolate, 3-11 × 1-2.5 cm; fertile pinnae contracted, linear, 3-11 × 0.2-0.5 cm.  Veins  anastomosing into 2 or more rows of areoles between costae and margin, free only at blade margin.  Sori  linear-oblong, deeply sunken into blades, nearly occupying full breadth of blade.  Indusia  ± membranous, lacking thickened cells, tucked under sporangia, not recurving but mostly disintegrating with age. 2 n  = 70.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Acidic bogs, seeps, and wet woods, rarely on rock of siliceous cliffs and ledges on northern edge of range;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="acidic bogs" />
        <character name="habitat" value="seeps" />
        <character name="habitat" value="wet woods" />
        <character name="habitat" value="rock" constraint="of siliceous cliffs and ledges" />
        <character name="habitat" value="siliceous cliffs" />
        <character name="habitat" value="ledges" />
        <character name="habitat" value="northern edge" constraint="of range" />
        <character name="habitat" value="range" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0-600 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.S.; Ala., Ark., Conn., Del., Fla., Ga., Ill., Ind., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Miss., Mo., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Okla., Pa., R.I., S.C., Tenn., Tex., Va., W.Va.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <discussion>Woodwardia areolata is most abundant on the coastal plain of the eastern United States, scattered in the Ouachita and Boston mountains, Ozark and Cumberland plateaus, and the Piedmont, but not in the high Appalachians, the heavy gumbo soils of the Mississippi Valley, or the limestone regions of the Interior Low Plateaus. It apparently has been extirpated in Maine where it is known only from specimens collected in the 1860s.</discussion>
  <discussion>Features such as extreme leaf dimorphism, sunken sori, and expanded persistent indusia set Woodwardia areolata apart from all others in the genus. The existence of closely related transitional species in Asia, however, makes generic segregation uncertain. Those who wish to recognize a monotypic generic segregate based on Woodwardia areolata must coin a new name because Lorinseria C. Presl (1849) is an orthographic variant of Lorinsera Opiz (1839). For a detailed discussion of the ecology and geography of this species, see R. Cranfill (1983). Sterile specimens of this species are sometimes confused with Onoclea sensibilis .</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves strongly dimorphic; sterile blades ± pinnatifid, with 2 or more rows of areoles between costae and margin, veins free only at margin. 1. Woodwardia areolata</description>
      <next_statement_id>1</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ± monomorphic; sterile blades pinnate, with 1 row of areoles adjacent to costae or costules, veins free to margin.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems forming stout caudex covered with petiole bases, suberect; petioles straw-colored and densely covered with orangish scales at base; pinnae not articulate to rachis. 3. Woodwardia fimbriata</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems relatively slender to ca. 1 cm diam., long-creeping; petioles blackish and glabrate at base; pinnae articulate to rachis. 2. Woodwardia virginica</description>
      <next_statement_id>1</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
