<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martius" date="unknown">hymenophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">trichomanes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kunze" date="1845">holopterum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Farrnkräuter</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 185. 1845</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hymenophyllaceae;genus trichomanes;species holopterum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  epiphytic.  Stems  erect, slender, bearing clustered leaves and numerous, slender, wiry roots, clothed at apices with dark, multicellular, gland-tipped hairs.  Leaves  lanceolate-oblong, pinnatifid, 2.5--10 × 0.5--2 cm, with sparse, 2-celled glandular hairs on veins; petioles shorter than blades.  Venation  pinnate, without unconnected false veins.  Soral involucres  terminal on vein ends at pinna apices, broadly conic and flaring at mouth.  Gametophytes  composed of proximal filamentous network supporting aerial blades tipped by gemmae.  Gemmae  regularly 4-celled with 2 green body cells and 2 nongreen rhizoid primordia. 2n = 128.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Epiphytic on decaying stumps and logs of bald cypress in dense cypress swamps;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="epiphytic on decaying stumps and logs of bald cypress in dense cypress" />
        <character name="habitat" value="swamps" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">below 10 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.; West Indies.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Entire-winged bristle fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Although mature sporophytes of Trichomanes holopterum are very rare, gametophyte colonies are relatively common and more extensive and usually bear numerous young sporophytes, most of which seem unable to grow beyond a height of 1--2 cm. Persistence and vegetative reproduction by the gametophyte generation appear primarily responsible for maintenance of the species in the flora (C. E. Delchamps 1966; D. R. Farrar and W. H. Wagner Jr. 1968). The species probably also occurs elsewhere in cypress swamps along the Gulf Coast.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
