<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="D. K. Bailey" date="1970">longaeva</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>57: 243. 1970</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species longaeva</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Engelmann" date="unknown">aristata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(D.K.Bailey) Little" date="unknown">longaeva</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species aristata;variety longaeva;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 16m; trunk to 2m diam., strongly tapering; crown rounded, flattened (sheared), or irregular.  Bark  red-brown, shallowly to deeply fissured with thick, scaly, irregular, blocky ridges.  Branches  contorted, pendent; twigs pale red-brown, aging gray to yellow-gray, puberulent, young branches resembling long bottlebrushes because of persistent leaves.  Buds  ovoid-acuminate, pale red-brown, ca. 1cm, resinous.  Leaves  mostly 5 per fascicle, upcurved, persisting 10--30 years, 1.5--3.5cm × 0.8--1.2mm, mostly connivent, deep yellow-green, with few resin splotches but often scurfy with pale scales, abaxial surface without median groove but with 2 subepidermal but evident resin bands, adaxial surfaces conspicuously whitened with stomates, margins entire or remotely and finely serrulate distally, apex bluntly acute to short-acuminate; sheath ca. 1cm, soon forming rosette, shed early.  Pollen cones  cylindro-ellipsoid, 7--10mm, purple-red.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds and falling soon thereafter, spreading, symmetric, lance-cylindric with rounded base before opening, lance-cylindric to narrowly ovoid when open, 6--9.5cm, purple, aging red-brown, nearly sessile; apophyses much thickened, sharply keeled; umbo central, raised on low buttress, truncate to umbilicate, abruptly narrowed to slender but stiff, variable prickle 1--6mm, resin exudate pale.  Seeds  ellipsoid-obovoid; body 5--8mm, pale brown, mottled with dark red; wing 10--12mm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Subalpine and alpine;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="subalpine" />
        <character name="habitat" value="alpine" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">1700--3400m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif, Nev., Utah.</description>
  <number>13</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Intermountain bristlecone pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus longaeva is considered by dendrochronologists to be the longest-lived tree. One tree was estimated to be 5000 years old.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
