<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>W. Carl Taylor , Neil T. Luebke , Donald M. Britton , R. James Hickey , Daniel F. Brunton</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Reichenbach" date="unknown">Isoëtaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Isoëtaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  tufted, grasslike, heterosporous (megaspores and microspores not alike), perennial; evergreen aquatics to ephemeral terrestrials.  Rootstock  brown, cormlike, lobed.  Roots  arising along central groove separating each rootstock lobe, simple or dichotomously branched, containing eccentric vascular strand and surrounding lacuna.  Leaves  linear, simple, spirally or distichously arranged, dilated toward base, tapering to apex, containing 4 transversely septate longitudinal lacunae, a central collateral vascular strand, and frequently several peripheral fibrous bundles; ligule inserted above sporangium.  Megasporophylls and microsporophylls  usually borne in alternating cycles; hardened scales and phyllopodia occasionally surrounding leaves.  Sporangia  solitary, adaxial, embedded in basal cavity of leaf, velum (thin flap extending downward over sporangium) partly to completely covering adaxial surface of sporangium; megasporangium with several to hundreds of megaspores; microsporangium with thousands of microspores.  Megagametophytes  white, endosporic, exposed when megaspore opens along proximal ridges; archegonia 1 to several, indicated by quartets of brownish neck cells.  Microgametophytes  9-celled, endosporic, antheridium releasing 4 multitailed spermatozoids.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Quillwort Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genus 1, species ca. 150 (24 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Jermy, A. C. 1990. Isoëtaceae. In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 1+ vol. Berlin etc. Vol. 1, pp. 26--31.</reference>
    <reference>Pfeiffer, N. E. 1922. Monograph of the Isoëtaceae. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 9: 79--233.</reference>
    <reference>Reed, C. F. 1953. Index Isoëtales. Bol. Soc. Brot. 27: 5--72.</reference>
    <reference>Tryon, R. M. and A. F. Tryon. 1982. Ferns and Allied Plants, with Special Reference to Tropical America. New York, Heidelberg, and Berlin.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
