<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Link" date="1841">pellaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Mettenius ex Kuhn" date="1869">glabella</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 87. 1869</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus pellaea;species glabella</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales uniformly reddish brown, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, thin, margins sinuous, entire to denticulate.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered on stem, 2--40 cm; croziers sparsely villous.  Petiole  brown, lustrous, rounded adaxially, occasionally with prominent articulation lines near base.  Blade  linear-oblong to ovate-lanceolate, 1--2-pinnate proximally, 1--8 cm wide; rachis brown throughout, straight, rounded adaxially, nearly glabrous.  Pinnae  somewhat ascending, decurrent on rachis, usually with 3--7 lobes or ultimate segments; costae when present straight, 1--50 mm, often shorter than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  oblong-lanceolate, 5--20 mm, leathery to herbaceous, glabrous except for occasional hairlike scales abaxially near midrib; margins recurved on fertile segments, covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, erose-denticulate; apex obtuse.  Veins  of ultimate segments usually obscure.  Sporangia  long-stalked, containing 32 or 64 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands.</description>
  <description type="distribution">only in the flora.</description>
  <number>12</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pelléade glabre</other_name>
  <discussion>Pellaea glabella includes four geographically and genetically isolated taxa treated here as subspecies. D. B. Lellinger (1985) recognized three species in this difficult group, but isozyme analyses (G. J. Gastony 1988) showed that one of these ( P . suksdorfiana ) is an autotetraploid derivative of the diploid known as P . occidentalis . As a result, Gastony recognized just two species: P . glabella (with two varieties) and P . occidentalis (with two subspecies). The few morphologic features that distinguish these taxa, however, are subtle and environmentally plastic, and the isozyme data indicate that they are less divergent genetically than any other pair of Pellaea species in North America. Therefore, a more conservative taxonomic treatment seems warranted.</discussion>
  <discussion>Subspecies 4:</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporangia containing 32 spores; spores averaging 60-72 µm diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sporangia containing 64 spores; spores averaging 38-52 µm diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Some ultimate segments (especially terminal segments) with hairlike scales abaxially near midrib; e North America (with outlying station in Texas panhandle).</description>
      <determination>12a subsp. glabella</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments essentially glabrous; w North America.</description>
      <determination>12b subsp. simplex</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments (especially terminal segments) with hairlike scales abaxially near midrib; Missouri.</description>
      <determination>12c subsp. missouriensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate segments glabrous; w North America.</description>
      <determination>12d subsp. occidentalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
