<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>R. David Whetstone , T. A. Atkinson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Berchtold &amp; J. S. Presl" date="unknown">Osmundaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Osmundaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial, herbaceous, frequently in clumps.  Stems  creeping, beset with old petiole bases and black fibrous roots; scales absent; older stems seldom persisting.  Leaves  monomorphic or dimorphic.  Blades  1--2-pinnate (2-pinnatifid); rachises grooved.  Pinnae  monomorphic or dimorphic.  Indument  of reddish to light brown hairs.  Veins  dichotomous, running to margins.  Sori  absent; sporangia born on slightly modified fertile segments of blades also possessing fully expanded pinnae, or sporangia covering blades lacking green expanded pinnae, clustered in marginal zones, indusia lacking.  Spores  green, all alike.  Gametophytes  green, aboveground, obcordate to elongate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, temperate and tropical regions.</description>
  <number>7</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Royal Fern Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Osmundaceae are considered intermediate in several respects between eusporangiate and leptosporangiate ferns. In the absence of sori, simultaneous maturation of spores, and development of sporangia from several initial cells, they are much like eusporangiate ferns. Their large prothalli with projecting antheridia are similar to those of leptosporangiate ferns.</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera 3, species 16--36 (1 genus with 3 species and 1 hybrid in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bobrov, A.E. 1967. The family Osmundaceae (R.Br.) Kaulf. Its taxonomy and geography. Bot. Zhurn. (Moscow &amp; Leningrad) 52: 1600--1610.</reference>
    <reference>Hewitson,W. 1962. Comparative morphology of the Osmundaceae. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 49: 57--93.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
