<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Miller" date="1768">virginiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict., ed. 8</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>Pinus no. 9. 1768</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species virginiana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 18m; trunk to 0.5m diam., straight or contorted to erect or leaning; crown irregularly rounded or flattened.  Bark  gray-brown with irregular, scaly-plated ridges, on upper sections of trunk reddish, scaly.  Branches  spreading-ascending to spreading-descending; twigs slender, red- or purple-tinged, often glaucous, aging red-brown to gray, rough.  Buds  ovoid to cylindric, red-brown, 0.6--1cm, resinous or not resinous; scale margins white-fringed.  Leaves  2 per fascicle, spreading or ascending, persisting 3--4 years, 2--8cm × 1--1.5mm, strongly twisted, deep to pale yellow-green, all surfaces with inconspicuous stomatal lines, margins serrulate, apex narrowly acute; sheath 0.4--1cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid-cylindric, 10--20mm, red-brown or yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter, persisting to 5 years, symmetric, lance-ovoid or lanceoloid before opening, ovoid when open, 3-- 7(--8)cm, dull red-brown, nearly sessile or on stalks to 1cm, scales rigid, with strong purple-red or purple-brown border on adaxial surface distally; apophyses slightly thickened, slightly elongate; umbo central, low-pyramidal, with slender, stiff prickle.  Seeds  compressed-obovoid, oblique apically; body 4--7mm, pale brown, mottled darker; wing narrow, to 20mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Dry uplands, sterile sandy or shaly barrens, old fields, and lower mountains;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="dry uplands" />
        <character name="habitat" value="sterile sandy" />
        <character name="habitat" value="shaly barrens" />
        <character name="habitat" value="old fields" />
        <character name="habitat" value="lower mountains" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">0--900m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Del., Ga., Ind., Ky., Md., Miss., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., S.C., Tenn., Va., W.Va.</description>
  <number>34</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Virginia pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus virginiana is weedy and fire successional and often forms large stands. It is mostly too small and too profusely branched to be valued except as pulpwood.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
