<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greville &amp; Balfour in A. Murray bis" date="1853">balfouriana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Murray bis,Bot. Exped. Oregon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8: no. 618, plate 3, fig. 1. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species balfouriana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">balfouriana</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(R.Mastrogiuseppe &amp; J.Mastrogiuseppe) Silba" date="unknown">austrina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species balfouriana;variety austrina;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">balfouriana</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="R.Mastrogiuseppe &amp; J.Mastrogiuseppe" date="unknown">austrina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species balfouriana;subspecies austrina;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 22m; trunk to 2.6m diam., erect or leaning; crown broadly conic to irregular.  Bark  gray to salmon or cinnamon, platy or irregularly deep-fissured or with irregular blocky plates.  Branches  contorted, ascending to descending; twigs red-brown, aging gray to drab yellow-gray, glabrous or puberulent, young branches resembling long bottlebrushes because of persistent leaves.  Buds  ovoid-acuminate, red-brown, 0.8--1cm, resinous.  Leaves  5 per fascicle, upcurved, persisting 10--30 years, 1.5--4cm × 1--1.4mm, mostly connivent, deep blue- to deep yellow-green, abaxial surface without median groove but usually with 2 subepidermal but evident resin bands, adaxial surfaces conspicuously whitened by stomates, margins mostly entire to blunt, apex broadly acute to acuminate; sheath 0.5--1cm, soon forming rosette, shed early.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid, ca. 6--10mm, red.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds and falling soon thereafter, spreading, symmetric, lance-cylindric with conic base before opening, broadly lance-ovoid or ovoid to cylindric or ovoid-cylindric when open, 6--9(--11)cm, purple, aging red-brown, nearly sessile; apophyses much thickened, rounded, larger toward cone base; umbo central, usually depressed; prickle absent or weak, to 1mm, resin exudates amber.  Seeds  ellipsoid to narrowly obovoid; body to 10mm, pale brown, mottled with deep red; wing 10--12mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Timberline and alpine meadows;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1500--3500m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <number>11</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Foxtail pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus balfouriana is the true "foxtail pine." In leaf character it is hardly, if at all, distinguishable from P . longaeva , but its strongly conic-based cones with distinctly shorter-prickled, sunken-centered umbos at once distinguish it from that species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants shown to be genetically distinct from the type (differences in chemistry, form, foliage, cone orientation, and seeds) have been called Pinus balfouriana subsp. austrina R.Mastrogiuseppe &amp; J.Mastrogiuseppe. As in several other species or species complexes in Pinus , however, there is a problem with a character gradient involving related taxa. The evidence presented by D.K. Bailey (1970) and later by R.J. Mastrogiuseppe and J.D. Mastrogiuseppe (1980) could as well be used to indicate that P . balfouriana (with its two infraspecific taxa) and P . longaeva represent a single species of three subspecies or three varieties. The more conservative view of Bailey is followed here.</discussion>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Mastrogiussepe, R.J. and J.D. Mastrogiuseppe. 1980. A study of  Pinus balfouriana  Grev. &amp; Balf. (Pinaceae). Syst. Bot. 5: 86--104.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
