<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Carol A. Jacobs , James H. Peck</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ching" date="unknown">dennstaedtiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Gleditsch ex Scopoli" date="1760">Pteridium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Carniol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>169. 1760</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dennstaedtiaceae;genus Pteridium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pteridion, a small fern]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial, often forming colonies or thickets.  Stems  subterranean, slender, long-creeping; hairs pale to dark, jointed; scales absent; true vessels present (absent in other Dennstaedtiaceae genera in the flora).  Leaves  widely spaced, broadly deltate, 0.5--4.5 m.  Petiole  glabrous to short-hairy, without prickles, with stem buds near base, vascular bundles numerous, U- or O-shaped in cross section.  Blade  2--4-pinnate, rachis and costae grooved adaxially; rachis without prickles; nectaries at base of proximal and sometimes distal pinnae.  Segments  pinnately divided, ultimate segments ovate to oblong to linear, base extending proximally on costae (decurrent) or proximally (surcurrent), margins entire.  Veins  free or joined at margin by commissural vein beneath sori, pinnately 2--3-forked.  Sori  ± continuous, covered by recurved, outer false indusium and obscure, extrorse, inner true indusium.  Spores  tetrahedral-globose, trilete, very finely granulate.  x  = 26.</description>
  <description type="distribution">almost worldwide.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <discussion>Species 1 (1 species, 4 varieties in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Page, C. N. 1976. The taxonomy and phytogeography of bracken---A review. J. Linn. Soc., Bot. 73: 1--34.</reference>
    <reference>Perring, F. H. and B. G. Gardener, eds. 1976. The biology of bracken. [Symposium.] J. Linn. Soc., Bot. 73(1--3): i--vi, 1--302.</reference>
    <reference>Tryon, R. M. 1941. A revision of the genus  Pteridium . Rhodora 43: 1--31, 37--67.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
