<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="1806">cheilanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Davenport" date="1877">viscida</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 191. 1877</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus cheilanthes;species viscida</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  short-creeping, usually 4--8 mm diam.; scales uniformly brown, linear-subulate, strongly contorted, loosely appressed, persistent.  Leaves  clustered, 6--30 cm; vernation circinate.  Petiole  dark brown, flattened or slightly grooved distally on adaxial surface.  Blade  narrowly oblong to linear, 3-pinnate-pinnatifid at base, 1--4 cm wide; rachis flattened or slightly grooved adaxially, lacking scales, with monomorphic pubescence.  Pinnae  not articulate, dark color of stalk continuing into pinna base, basal pair slightly smaller than adjacent pair, ± equilateral, appearing glandular pubescent adaxially.  Costae  green adaxially for most of length; abaxial scales absent.  Ultimate segments  oblong to lanceolate, not beadlike, the largest 3--4 mm, abaxially and adaxially glandular-pubescent with short, sticky, capitate glands.  False indusia  marginal, weakly differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  usually discontinuous, concentrated on apical and lateral lobes.  Sporangia  containing 64 spores.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporulating late spring--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Cliffs and rocky slopes, usually on igneous substrates;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="cliffs and rocky slopes , on igneous substrates ;" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">200--1300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.; Mexico in Baja California.</description>
  <number>24</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Viscid lip fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Cheilanthes viscida is confined to a relatively small region in the deserts of California. Variations in spore size among populations suggest that the species may include more than one cytotype.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
