<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Willkomm in Willkomm &amp; Lange" date="unknown">selaginellaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Palisot de Beauvois" date="1805">selaginella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Palisot de Beauvois) Baker" date="1883">Stachygynandrum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21: 3. 1883</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family selaginellaceae;genus selaginella;subgenus Stachygynandrum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Palisot de Beavois ex Mirbel" date="unknown">Stachygynandrum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Lamarck &amp; C. de Mirbel, Hist. Nat. Vég.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 477. 1803[1802?]</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>subgenus Stachygynandrum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems  creeping, cespitose, erect, climbing, or vinelike, upperside and underside structurally different, usually highly branched, articulate or not; vessel elements absent.  Rhizophores  borne on underside or upperside, or in axils of branch forks, always present.  Leaves  of different shapes and sizes, in 4 ranks (2 median, 2 lateral), linear-lanceolate to ovate, thin and papery to thick and stiff, margins entire, dentate, or ciliate; stomates arranged throughout abaxial surface or sometimes also on adaxial surface; axillary leaves present.  Strobili  usually quadrangular, sometimes flattened.  Sporophylls  highly differentiated from the vegetative leaves, most sporophylls fertile (strobili with only 1 basal megasporangium in  S .  kraussiana ), seldom with megasporophylls larger than microsporophylls, in 4 alternating ranks, with or without prominent auricles.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical regions.</description>
  <number>1c</number>
  <discussion>Selaginella subg. Stachygynandrum is treated here in the broad sense, including Selaginella eatonii and species belonging to the Selaginella apoda complex.</discussion>
  <discussion>Previous to J. G. Baker (1883, 1887), and more recently to A. C. Jermy (1986, 1990b), all species with dimorphic vegetative leaves were placed in Selaginella subg. Heterophyllum (Spring) Hieronymus. These species are now referred to each of the currently recognized subgenera (e.g., subg. Stachygynandrum , subg. Heterostachys ), according to Jermy's system. Selaginella subg. Stachygynandrum has priority over subg. Heterophyllum .</discussion>
  <discussion>Species probably more than 650 (11 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Buck, W. R. 1977. A new species of  Selaginella  in the  Selaginella apoda  complex. Canad. J. Bot. 55: 366--371.</reference>
    <reference>Buck, W. R. 1978. The taxonomic status of  Selaginella eatonii . Amer. Fern J. 68: 33--36.</reference>
    <reference>Buck, W. R. and T. W. Lucansky. 1976. An anatomical and morphological comparison of  Selaginella apoda  and  Selaginella ludoviciana . Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 103: 9--16.</reference>
    <reference>Somers, P. 1982. A unique type of microsporangium in  Selaginella  series  Articulatae . Amer. Fern J. 72: 88--92.</reference>
    <reference>Somers, P. and W. R. Buck. 1975.  Selaginella ludoviciana ,  S .  apoda  and their hybrids in the southeastern United States. Amer. Fern J. 65: 76--82.</reference>
    <reference>Webster, T. R. 1990.  Selaginella apoda  X  ludoviciana , a synthesized hybrid spikemoss. Amer. J. Bot. 77(6,suppl.): 108.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems articulate or swollen; rhizophores on upperside of stems; strobili with only 1 basal megasporangium; megasporophylls larger than microsporophylls.</description>
      <determination>35 Selaginella kraussiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems not articulate; rhizophores on underside of stems, axillary, or seldom on upperside (S. lepidophylla); strobili with many megasporangia, megasporangia basal or throughout length of strobilus; megasporophylls and microsporophylls similar (except in S. apoda complex).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems tufted, curling inward when dry, rosette-forming; leaves thick and stiff; growing in seasonally dry and exposed areas.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems prostrate, creeping or erect, never rosette-forming; leaves delicate, papery; growing in mild humid areas, very often in shady places.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves ovate-deltate to deltate, apex acuminate; margins with wide transparent portion, ciliate at base and dentate or ciliate toward apex; base nearly cordate.</description>
      <determination>29 Selaginella lepidophylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves lanceolate (slightly falcate), apex long-bristled, bristle 1/3--1/2 length of leaf; margins with narrow transparent portion, entire or with scattered teeth; base rounded to truncate.</description>
      <determination>30 Selaginella pilifera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants with large aerial, erect, vinelike (high climbing) stems, or bushy.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants with rather short-branched, prostrate or creeping stems.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems mostly erect, covered with stiff hairs; median leaves long-acuminate to bristled; base of axillary leaves truncate.</description>
      <determination>34 Selaginella braunii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems vinelike, climbing, or shrublike, without hairs; median leaves acute, tip rounded; base of axillary leaves with 2 auricles.</description>
      <determination>32 Selaginella willdenowii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of lateral leaves entire or basally ciliate; stems long-creeping, lateral branches 2--3-forked.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of lateral leaves dentate to serrate; stem short-creeping or long-creeping (as in S. ludoviciana), lateral branches 1--2-forked.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves cuspidate with 2 ciliate auricles at base, outer auricle larger and more ciliate than inner auricle; lateral leaves ciliate at base; margins green.</description>
      <determination>31 Selaginella douglasii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves acuminate, without auricles; lateral leaves not ciliate; margins transparent.</description>
      <determination>33 Selaginella uncinata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves linear or narrowly lanceolate, 0.7--1.2 mm; apex long-bristled; plants minute, forming small mats less than 6 cm diam.</description>
      <determination>36 Selaginella eatonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves ovate to ovate-lanceolate, (1--)1.25--1.5(--1.8) mm; apex acute to acuminate; plants not minute, forming mats larger than 6 cm diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins with 3--5 rows of transparent cells; stomates of lateral leaves confined to midrib region on adaxial surface.</description>
      <determination>37 Selaginella ludoviciana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins undifferentiated in color or with 1(--2) rows of slightly paler cells; stomates of lateral leaves scattered over adaxial surface.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves with long-attenuate, veined apices.</description>
      <determination>39 Selaginella eclipes</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Median leaves with acute apices or, if attenuate, usually keeled and without midrib extension.</description>
      <determination>38 Selaginella apoda</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
