<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">pinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="D. Don" date="1836">radiata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London, Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 442. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pinaceae;genus pinus;species radiata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pinus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas ex Loudon" date="unknown">insignis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pinus;species insignis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees  to 30m; trunk to 0.9m diam., contorted to straight; crown broadly conic, becoming rounded to flattened.  Bark  gray, deeply V-furrowed, furrow bases red, ridges irregularly elongate-rectangular, their flattened surfaces scaly.  Branches  level to downcurved or ascending, poorly self-pruning; twigs slender, red-brown, sometimes glaucous, aging gray, rough.  Buds  ovoid to ovoid-cylindric, red-brown, ca. 1.5cm, resinous.  Leaves  (2--)3 in a fascicle, spreading-ascending, persisting 3--4 years, (8--)9--15(--20)cm × 1.3--1.8(--2)mm, straight, slightly twisted, deep yellow-green, all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins serrulate, apex conic-subulate; sheath (1--)1.5--2cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid-cylindric, 10--15mm, orange-brown.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter, but often serotinous and persistent 6--20 years, solitary to whorled, spreading to recurved, curved, very asymmetric, ovoid before opening, broadly ovoid when open, 7--14cm, pale red-brown and lustrous, scales rigid, stalks to 1cm; apophyses toward outer cone base increasingly mammillate, those on inward cone side and middle and apex of cone more level; umbo central, mostly depressed, with small central boss or occasionally with slender, deciduous prickle.  Seeds  compressed-ellipsoid; body ca. 6mm, dark brown; wing 20--30mm. 2 n =24.</description>
  <description type="habitat">
    <statement id="habitat_0">
      <text>Coastal fog belt;</text>
      <biological_entity id="hab_o0" name="whole_organism" name_original="" type="structure">
        <character name="habitat" value="coastal fog belt" />
      </biological_entity>
    </statement>
  </description>
  <description type="elevation">30--400m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.; Mexico in Baja California [600--1200 m].</description>
  <number>36</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Monterey pine</other_name>
  <discussion>Pinus radiata has an extremely narrow natural range: three coastal areas in California (one in San Mateo and Santa Cruz counties, one in Monterey County, and one in San Luis Obispo County) and off the coast of Baja California, Mexico (Guadalupe Island and debatably also on Cedros Island). Some natural populations of the species are under protection. Along the California coast it has escaped from cultivation, and from there into southern coastal Oregon it shows signs of naturalizing.</discussion>
  <discussion>Pinus radiata is a much better-formed tree and of greater silvicultural value within its introduced range (Africa, Australia, Europe, and New Zealand, where it is a principal timber tree) than in its native range. It hybridizes naturally with P . attenuata ( P . × attenuiradiata Stockwell &amp; Righter).</discussion>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
