<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David M. Johnson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Herter" date="unknown">dryopteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Todaro" date="1800">Matteuccia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Giorn. Sci. Nat. Econ. Palermo</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 235. 1866, name conserved Ostrich fern [for Car. 1800</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dryopteridaceae;genus Matteuccia</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Car 1863, physicist at the University of Florence, Italy]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial.  Stems  obliquely ascending to erect, stolons present or absent, not wiry.  Leaves  strongly dimorphic, sterile leaves with longer and wider pinnae than fertile ones, sterile dying back in winter, fertile persistent, brownish, hardened.  Petiole  of sterile leaf ca. 1/10--1/5 length of blade, petiole of fertile leaf ± equaling length of blade, bases swollen, persisting as trophopods over winter; vascular bundles 2, lateral, lunate in cross section.  Blade  elliptic (sterile) or narrowly oblong to oblanceolate (fertile), pinnate-pinnatifid or sometimes pinnate with lacerate pinnae in fertile leaves, gradually to nearly abruptly reduced distally to pinnatifid apex, sterile blades herbaceous.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins entire (sterile); proximal pinnae (several pairs) greatly reduced, sessile, equilateral; costae shallowly grooved adaxially, grooves not continuous from rachis to costae; indument absent on both surfaces or deciduously hairy abaxially.  Veins  free, simple.  Sori  in 1 row between midrib and margin, ± round, covered by hardened revolute pinna margin; indusia vestigial, triangular, persistent but not easily seen in mature leaves.  Spores  greenish, with low folds and minute echinate-cristate elements.  x  = 40.</description>
  <description type="distribution">north temperate regions.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Ostrich fern</other_name>
  <discussion>Matteuccia is one of several genera known to store starch grains in long-persistent petiole bases (trophopods) (W. H. Wagner Jr. and D. M. Johnson 1983). Struthiopteris Willdenow is a later homonym of Struthiopteris Scopoli and hence illegitimate. Pteretis Rafinesque, even though it is the oldest legitimate name, has been rejected in favor of Matteuccia .</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1935. Critical plants of the upper Great Lakes region of Ontario and Michigan. Rhodora 37: 197--222.</reference>
    <reference>Hill, R. W. and W. H. Wagner Jr. 1974. Seasonality and spore type of pteridophytes in Michigan. Michigan Bot. 13: 40--44.</reference>
    <reference>Lloyd, R. M. 1971. Systematics of the onocleoid ferns. Univ. Calif. Publ. Bot. 61: 1--86, 5 plates.</reference>
    <reference>Wagner, W. H. Jr. and D. M. Johnson. 1983. Trophopod, a commonly overlooked storage structure of potential systematic value in ferns. Taxon 32: 268--269.</reference>
    <reference>Lloyd, R. M. and E. J. Klekowski Jr. 1970. Spore germination and viability in Pteridophyta: Evolutionary significance of chlorophyllous spores. Biotropica 2: 129--137. Von</reference>
    <reference>Aderkas, P. 1984. Economic history of ostrich fern, Matteuccia struthiopteris , the edible fiddlehead. Econ. Bot. 38: 14--23.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
