<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Clifton E. Nauman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
    <other_info_on_meta type="volume">2</other_info_on_meta>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="E. D. M. Kirchner" date="unknown">pteridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">Pteris</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1073. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed 5, 484. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pteridaceae;genus Pteris</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pteris, fern, derived from pteron, wing or feather, for the closely spaced pinnae, which give the leaves a likeness to feathers]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants  terrestrial or on rock.  Stems  erect or creeping, branched; scales pale brown to black, concolored, elongate, margins entire.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered or closely spaced, 1--20 dm.  Petiole  straw-colored, green, brownish red to purple black, longitudinally ridged, 2--3-grooved adaxially, scaly at base, glabrous or scaly distally, with 1 (less often 2 or more) vascular bundle.  Blade  oblong to lanceolate to deltate, 1--4-pinnate, herbaceous to leathery, abaxially and adaxially glabrous or sometimes pubescent or scaly, adaxially dull, not striate; rachis straight.  Ultimate segments  of blade sessile to short-stalked, linear to oblong-lanceolate, 1.5--8 mm wide; base truncate or narrowed to stalk, stalk when present green, not lustrous; margins plane or reflexed to form false indusia.  Veins  in leaves conspicuous, free (except in sori) and forking well above base of segment, or highly anastomosing.  False indusia  pale, scarious, covering sori.  Sporangia  intramarginal, sori usually continuous except at pinna or segment apex and sinuses, paraphyses present.  Spores  brown, trilete, tetrahedral, rugate and/or tuberculate, usually with prominent equatorial flange.  x  = 29.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide, warm and tropical regions.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Brake</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 300 (5 species and 1 hybrid in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kramer, K. U. 1990.  Pteris . In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 1+ vol. Berlin etc. Vol. 1, pp. 250--252.</reference>
    <reference>Lakela, O. and R. W. Long. 1976. Ferns of Florida. Miami.</reference>
    <reference>Wunderlin, R. P. 1982. Guide to the Vascular Plants of Central Florida. Tampa.</reference>
    <reference>Wagner, W. H. Jr. and C. E. Nauman. 1982. Pteris × delchampsii , a spontaneous fern hybrid from southern Florida. Amer. Fern J. 72: 97--102.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Veins in leaves anastomosing except sometimes near margins of ultimate segments.</description>
      <determination>1 Pteris tripartita</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Veins in leaves entirely free.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not strictly 1-pinnate, at least proximal pinnae pinnatifid-lobed or variously forked or divided.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves strictly 1-pinnate, pinnae not lobed or divided.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of mature leaves decurrent to relatively broad-winged rachis in at least distal 1/2 of leaf.</description>
      <determination>4 Pteris multifida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pinnae of mature leaves not decurrent to relatively broad-winged rachis or only terminal pinna decurrent on rachis.</description>
      <determination>5 Pteris cretica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles and often also rachises densely scaly, scales light to reddish, often grading into hairs on abaxial costae; pinnae appearing not articulate to rachis, apices long-attenuate or sharply acute; sori narrow, with most of abaxial blade surface exposed.</description>
      <determination>2 Pteris vittata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles often sparsely scaly or scaly only proximally, scales dark brown to nearly black, scales absent or few on rachises, abaxial costae with or without hairs; pinnae appearing articulate to rachis, apices acute; sori broad, little or no abaxial blade tissue exposed.</description>
      <determination>3 Pteris bahamensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
